<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The information of Sir Frederick Hammilton, Knight, and Colonell, given to the Committee of Both Kingdoms, concerning Sir William Cole, Knight, and Colonell; with the scandalous answer of the said Sir William Cole, Knight; together with the replication of Sir Frederick Hammilton, in answer to the said scandalous and recriminating pamphlet of Sir William Cole. With divers letters and depositions, for the cleering of the said Sir Frederick Hammilton, from the severall scandals and aspersions in the said answer of Sir William Cole.</title>
            <author>Hamilton, Frederick, Sir, fl. 1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 261 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E284_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200063</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86994)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E284[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The information of Sir Frederick Hammilton, Knight, and Colonell, given to the Committee of Both Kingdoms, concerning Sir William Cole, Knight, and Colonell; with the scandalous answer of the said Sir William Cole, Knight; together with the replication of Sir Frederick Hammilton, in answer to the said scandalous and recriminating pamphlet of Sir William Cole. With divers letters and depositions, for the cleering of the said Sir Frederick Hammilton, from the severall scandals and aspersions in the said answer of Sir William Cole.</title>
                  <author>Hamilton, Frederick, Sir, fl. 1645.</author>
                  <author>Cole, William, Sir, d. 1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 91, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed, anno Dom. 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 17th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cole, William, --  Sir, d. 1653 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158501:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INFORMATION OF Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> Knight, and Colonell, Given to the Committee of Both KINGDOMS, Concerning Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> Knight, and Colonell;</p>
            <p>WITH The Scandalous Anſwer of the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> Knight:</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With the Replication of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> in Anſwer to the ſaid Scandalous and Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Pamphlet of Sir <hi>William Cole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With divers Letters and Depoſitions, for the cleering of the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> from the ſeverall Scandals and Aſperſions in the ſaid Anſwer of Sir <hi>William Cole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, Anno Dom. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:158501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:158501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Impartiall READER.</head>
            <p>HE that doth moſt Service, when he hath leaſt encouragement, ſhews his principles to be Noble, and that he leaſt intends himſelf; and if his more particular imployment, chance to expire with his attendance, it may weaken his fortune, but cannot impair his credit: It is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe that onely makes a man to be uſed too long, whiles he that hath really done his part, need not to repine, though men of weaker abilities have better fortune. Thus it is task enough for great ſpirits to be patient, when they finde themſelves neglected for doing Service, and in ſuch a caſe, to keep humble and contented, well knowing, that at a low water there is time to mend the Banks, aad whiles the Ship is in the Harbour, it may be dreſſed and trimed, and made able to endure rough Seas and Tempeſts: I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, it is not the firſt time I have had to do with men of the ſame rank and condition, which the enſuing diſcourſe hath brought upon the Stage, not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by any deſire of mine, for I am inforced to this Vindication of my ſelf, or muſt have lyen under thoſe baſe asperſions, which no other then a ſon of him that ruleth in the Ayr, could without ſhame and bluſhing, have publiſhed to the World; but his boldneſſe herein, I doubt not, but will appear to be void, both of Counſell and Religion, his diſhoneſty ſufficiently ſhewing his diſhonour, and puſilanimity; for a magnanimous man will be juſt, but ſuch favourites will be ſlaves at laſt, who to advance themſelves, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrall their poſterity, betray their Countrey, abuſe their friends, and by an intollerable baſeneſſe, and brutiſh demeanour, traduce thoſe that ſtand next in the way of their preferments, whoſe timorouſneſſe commonly for want of courage and judgement, makes them ſo ſuspitious, that they raiſe jealouſies, and preoccupate evils, never plotted any where, but in their own Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations; to which they are led, by prejudicate opinions, and unwarrantable fancies; and ſuch Beasts as theſe, do uſually run under great Trees in a ſtorm, for ſhelter and protection, where they leave nothing but dung and filth behinde them for their ſtanding, when the Tempeſt is once over: You may perceive, it hath been my zeal (and not too much officiouſneſſe, as ſome would have it) that hath carried me on unto this undertaking, with which, if you ſhall conſider the Injunctions of State laid upon me, how could I have done leſſe, if not to have muzled my Conſcience, and ſown up my Lips, to all relation whatſoever: I confeſſe, he that diſchargeth his duty, though be doth not deſerve thanks, yet he meriteth encouragement, and not diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<pb facs="tcp:158501:3"/>for his endeavour; but he that at any time, ſhall over act his part, be too forward for his Countreys good, be it never ſo advantagious to the Publike, ſhall many times be thought more preciſe, then wiſe, peradventure be accounted but a mad man for his labour: Envy will not want wayes and means to vent it ſelf againſt the innocent. I have not yet throughly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it to be an offence, to uſe the ſword with the moſt keen, and ſharpeſt edge, againſt a cruell and bloody Rebell: Yet I have ſometimes heard of a Milk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, ſet up in the ſtead of a <hi>Joſhua,</hi> but then it was to do the enemy a good turn; and that with more ſecurity they might make ſpoil and havock of their Adverſaries: Thus ſome man may with more ſafety ſteal a Horſe, then another man may look over the Hedge. And if this mans ſufferings be concluded for an Argument of his guilt, or that it be a warrantable proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to condemn him upon no better ground and evidence, then his adverſaries accuſation, I ſee not who can be ſafe or free in this world; but Juſtice layes the Gold to the Touchſtone, and findes out the counterfeit Mettall, and eſteems of both, according to their value: Let the Cosk then have the Barley Kernell; let the Lapidary take the Jewell that knows the price and value of it. And I beſeech you, judge of me as you ſhall finde the truth for to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in that which follows, wherein I have dealt freely and cleerly, and deſire to be interpreted as the whole ſhall hold out unto you, the matter to be reſolved, for him to live or die in your opinion, that ſtrives to be yet a more lover of his Countrey, and to ſhew himſelf zealous and faithfull, in all his undertakings, and more particularly in this <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158501:3"/>
            <head>A COPY of the ORDER, by Vertue whereof Sir <hi>Frederick Hamilton</hi> exhibited Articles againſt Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> and others.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Lunae,</hi> 23. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1644.</date> At the Committee of both Kingdoms, at <hi>Derby</hi> Houſe.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Ordered,</p>
            <p>THat S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> be deſired, that if he hath any thing that he can inform this Committee of, concerning any miſcarriage of any perſons in the Service of the Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> That he will give it in to the Committee in Writing, on Thurſday next, in the Afternoon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By Command of the Committee, <hi>Gualter Froſt</hi> Secretary, to the ſame Committee.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="deposition">
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lords, and others, the Committee of both Kingdoms. The Information of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> Knight, and Colonell, againſt Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <p>Shewing,</p>
            <p>FIrſt, That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had notice of the intended Plots of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to break out into Rebellion, above a fortnight before the Rebels took up Arms, as it is generally given out in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and yet did neither timely inform the State, nor his Neighbours, for to prevent the miſchief, and to defend themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> That having a Commiſſion from His Majeſtie to be a Colonell onely of five Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Foot, he notwithſtanding taketh on nine Companies, making them beleeve, as if he had Commiſſion for a thouſand. And when he had made uſe of their Service, neer a yeer and a half; when Proviſions were ſent him by the Parliament, whereof they expected a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158501:4"/>ſhare, he caſhier'd four of the moſt deſerving Captains, and their Companies, of purpoſe to gain all the ſaid Proviſions to himſelf, and his Son in law, Dea<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Barkley,</hi> who was his Agent to the Parliament, for thoſe Proviſions.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> About the beginning of the Rebellion, there were two Engliſh Papiſts, whoſe Sirnames were <hi>Hetherington,</hi> who joyned themſelves with the Rebels, and plundered one Serjeant <hi>Abrels</hi> houſe, a Tenant unto Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> and afterwards burned the Houſe, which was certified to Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> by Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> with the Depoſitions of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain witneſſes, proving the ſame fact: And it was deſired, that Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> would make them ſure for Juſtice, they being then daily imployed by him, which he refuſed to do, aleadging that they had done good ſervice to him, and afterward ſuffered them to eſcape.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>IV.</hi> That whereas Sir <hi>Frederick Hamilton</hi> had taken one <hi>Robert Parck,</hi> one that complied with the Rebels, and had him in cuſtody a yeer and more, and had likewiſe gained the Command of the Caſtle, which was of great advantage and ſervice to the Parliament: And by means whereof, the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> did daily much ſpoil, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy the Rebels. The ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> knowing the conſequence thereof, and how well affected the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> ſtood unto the Rebels, on a time after that horrid Ceſſation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the Rebels; and when he knew that Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> himſelf, his Wife, and Children were gone for <hi>London-Derry,</hi> ſome ſixtie miles from <hi>Mannor Hammilton:</hi> The ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> upon the Marquis of <hi>Ormonds</hi> commands, ſends his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign with <hi>40.</hi> Muskettiers unto Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> ſaid Garriſon, and by permiſſion of the ſaid Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> Lievtenant, who commanded in his abſence, and correſponded with him, as it ſhould ſeem, be took away the ſaid <hi>Parck.</hi> And whereas he was by the ſaid Order to have conveyed him unto <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Dublin,</hi> be firſt feaſted him as his Caſtle, and then returned him back amongſt the Rebels, who received him with all gladneſſe, and after they had rejoyced a while together, they go along with him to <hi>Dublin,</hi> where after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be procures an Order of the State for reſtitution of his Caſtle, with whatſoever Arms and Goods were in it; which he accordingly obtained in Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> abſence: Which he, and the Rebels, now make good againſt the Parliament, to the great prejudice of the Parliaments Service, and the danger and hazard of all thoſe parts of <hi>Conaught.</hi> And this done, albeit, the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> well knew, that Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> had refuſed to deliver the ſaid Priſoner, upon ſeverall Orders, and Commands, ſent unto him by the ſaid Marquis for that purpoſe, as well knowing the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> to be an utter Enemy to the Parliament here, and their proceedings. And one for whom the Lord Viſcount <hi>Taaffe</hi> (that Arch-rebel) had by his Letters ſolicited the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> for his delivery.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>V.</hi> That the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> did in the moneth of <hi>February,</hi> next after the ſaid Ceſſation, apply himſelf unto the Marquis of <hi>Ormond,</hi> who then, and long before, was declared an Enemy to the Parliament. And complained againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> and his Souldiers to the ſaid Marquis, for taking of a prey from the Rebels; which Rebels the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had then protected, and gained an Order from the ſaid Marquis for reſtitution thereof, which notwithſtanding was diſobeyed.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>VI.</hi> That before the ſaid Ceſſation, the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> correſponded with the Rebels, and took <hi>100.</hi> of them at the leaſt into his Protection, and formed them into a Company, conſiſting of a Captain and Officers; and imployed them for ſome time, with the reſt of his Regiment, who did him ſervice in getting of Preys, but did great diſ ſervice unto the State, in giving Intelligence againſt all the Brittiſh of their proceedings; and more particularly, did much grieve and offend Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> Garriſon at <hi>Mannor hammilton,</hi> who at the laſt, took their opportunitie, and turned Rebels again.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:158501:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>The ſaid Sir</hi> Frederick <hi>could inform many other particular Omiſſions and Diſ ſervices, which the ſaid Sir</hi> William Cole <hi>hath committed in this time of his imployment, ſince the Rebellion began in</hi> Ireland, <hi>which becauſe they do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern himſelf in a more neer relation, he ſhall therefore forbear to mention. And the ſaid Sir</hi> Frederick <hi>is ready to juſtifie himſelf in whatſoever that any man can object againſt him; And humbly prayeth, that this honourable Committee will not think the worſe of him, for diſcharging his duty to God, and the State, by the informing of theſe Miſcarriages, which in Conſcience, he holds himſelf bound to relate in purſuance of his ſolemn League and Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Frederick Hammilton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords, and others, The Committees of both Kingdoms. The humble Anſwer of Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> Knight, and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, to the Information of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> Knight, Exhibited againſt him to your Lordſhips, the 26. of <hi>December,</hi> 1644.</head>
            <p n="1">I. FOr anſwer to the firſt Article, he ſaith; That he had no certain notice of the intended Plots of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to break out into Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, as is ſuggeſted by the Informer; but ſaith, That upon the eleventh of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. <hi>Bryan mac Coconaght Magwire</hi> Eſquire, and one <hi>Flartagh mac Hugh,</hi> informed him of ſome jealouſies of ſuſpitions, that they then apprehended of ſome evil Intentions and practiſes of the Lord <hi>Magwire,</hi> Sir <hi>Phelem roe O Neil, Neil mac Kennay, Hugh oge mac Mahon,</hi> and others of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentry of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> of which he gave advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by his Letter, to the then Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with all poſſible ſpeed; alſo intimating his deſires, That their Lordſhips would be ſo pleaſed, to take that matter into their ſerious conſideration, as that they would ſtrictly examine the ſaid Lord <hi>Magwire,</hi> and others of his Complices concerning the ſame, who he underſtood were ſhortly after to be at <hi>Dublin;</hi> which Letter, or a Copie thereof, this Reſpondent underſtands, was tranſmitted by their Lordſhips to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and remains with the Clerk of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, and was one of the chiefeſt evidences and motives (upon the Diſcovery made by <hi>Owin O Connallie</hi>) to induce the State to be upon their Guard, and alſo of the apprehenſion of the Lord <hi>Magwire, Hugh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158501:5"/>oge mac Mahon, Coconaght Magwire, Redmond Magwire, Tirlagh oge mac Hugh,</hi> and others of their conſorts in <hi>Dublin,</hi> the 23. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. or thereabouts. And for proof of this advertiſement, he can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their Lordſhips letter in anſwer of his, which he received before the Rebellion broke out. And further ſaith, That upon the 21. of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1641. the ſaid Plot being more fully diſcovered unto him, by the ſaid <hi>Flartagh mac Hugh,</hi> by direction from the ſaid <hi>Bryan Magwire,</hi> and by one <hi>Fargus O Howen,</hi> how the Rebellion was to break out uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> on the 23. of that Moneth. He not onely poſted away a Meſſenger with a ſecond letter,
<note place="margin">Notice was given of this Rebellion, from the Reſpondent to Sir <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick Hammilton,</hi> at <hi>London-Derry,</hi> the <hi>22.</hi> of October, <hi>1641.</hi> by <hi>rancis Barnaby.</hi>
               </note> to ſignifie the ſame unto the ſaid Lords Juſtices and Councell (which was intercepted by the way at <hi>Loghramar,</hi>) but alſo the ſame day haſtened eighteen Meſſengers with ſo many Letters, to notifie the ſame to his Neighbours at <hi>Monea, Caſtle-Balfour, Newtown, Newpurtton, Lowtherſtown, Archdale, Bowſſland, Clogher, Glaſslogh,</hi> and elſewhere, as far as in ſo ſhort and diſtracted a time he could poſſibly do, being fully buſied to draw his Neighbours and Tenants together, and to Arm and put them into a poſture of War, for the defence of the Caſtle and Town of <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> and the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts; and amongſt others, did then direct particular advertiſement thereof, to be given unto <hi>Mannor-hammilton,</hi> (where the Rebellion broke not out in a Moneth after) and of which, the Informer could not afterwards be ignorant, though he himſelf was then abſent; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, of all men, hath leaſt reaſon to lay this as a crime to the Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents charge, had he not wanted other matter.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To the ſecond Article he anſwereth, That the Commiſſion therein mentioned (as he hath heard) was the firſt ground of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers envy, and diſcontent, not onely againſt this Reſpondent, but alſo againſt all the other Brittiſh Colonels then in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> that received Commiſſions from His Majeſtie at that time, for the raiſing of their Regiments, and proſecuting of the Rebels, taking it in great diſdain, that there was not the like Commiſſion then ſent unto him; whereas for ought this Reſpondent could ever hear, none of the ſaid Colonels knew any certainty of the ſaid Commiſſions, untill they were brought unto them; neither did this Reſpondent receive his ſaid Commiſſion, untill almoſt a yeer after the Rebellion began (at which time he gave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof unto all his Captains) for that (during the greateſt part of that yeer) he was ſo incloſed on all ſides with multitudes of the enemies (being above fourty miles diſtant from any that were able to give him relief) that he could not receive any intelligence, how the ſtate of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158501:5"/>Proteſtants of that Kingdom ſtood, in any part thereof, though he had often uſed his beſt endeavours to gain the ſame to his exceeding great charges, and the hanging of twelve or fourteen of his Meſſengers, by the Rebels. And the ſaid Informer finding this Reſpondent next unto him, and conceiving him eaſieſt to be dealt withall, hath ever ſince uſed his uttermoſt indeavours by invective Calumnies, to aſperſe and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value both him and his actions, which he hath ever envied, ſo that by extolling his own unknown ſervices, he laboureth as much as in him lieth, ſo eclipſe thoſe well know ſervices performed by this Reſpondent, and all other the Commanders and Officers in <hi>Ulster</hi> and <hi>Conaught:</hi> And this Reſpondent further ſaith, That by vertue of a Commiſſion from the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to him directed, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the ſaid Rebellion, for raiſing, Arming, and Banding, all the Brittiſh within the County of <hi>F<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmanaugh,</hi> he (with the help of his friends) raiſed, Armed, and Banded, the nine Companies in the ſaid ſecond Article ſpecified, together with a Troop of Horſe; by vertue whereof alſo, he might have raiſed, Armed, and Banded, as many of the Brittiſh as he could have drawn together, for their own mutuall defence, and proſecution of the Rebels, by whoſe aſſiſtance (and Gods great bleſſings) ſundry good ſervices have been performed, whereof this Reſpondent did often give intimation, both to the Honourable Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, that in reward of their good ſervices they might be liſted into the Parliaments pay, and Regimented under his Command. But inaſmuch as he could not obtain that favour, by reaſon of the troubles then hear, though earneſtly ſollicited by his friends, and that but 500. of his Foot, and his Troop, was inliſted and taken into the Parliaments pay, from the firſt of <hi>July,</hi> 1642. as appears by Order of the 21. of that Moneth, and Proviſions of Cloaths, and Victuals, being onely ſent for them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſolicitation of his Agent, Maſter <hi>Robert Barklay;</hi> this Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent was conſtrained to deliver out the ſaid Cloaths unto the Officers and Souldiers, of the ſaid five Companies, (not being able to divide the ſaid 500. Suits amongſt 900. men) <hi>viz.</hi> Unto his own Company, his Lievtenant-Colonels, his Serjeant-Majors, to the Company of Captain <hi>John Cole,</hi> and to the Company of Captain <hi>Hugh Roſſe,</hi> of whom, three are Scottiſh Officers, and whom without prejudice to the others mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he conceived very deſerving of the Imployment. Offering at the very ſame time, to the other four Captains, and their Companies, an equall divident of all other Proviſions ſent him, then by the Parliament, and of what ſpoils they could get from the Rebels, if they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue with him in the Service, promiſing alſo, to uſe his beſt endeavours
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158501:6"/>to have them taken into pay, and added to his Regiment. But the Cloaths being thus divided (which could not be otherwiſe) the ſaid four Companies were ſo diſcontented, that of their own accords they disbanded themſelves, and went to ſeek their fortunes elſewhere, and yet the greateſt part of their beſt and ableſt men, were perſwaded to continue in the Garriſon; ſo that this Reſpondent denieth, that he did caſhiere four of the ſaid Captains and their Companies, of purpoſe to gain all the ſaid Proviſions to himſelf, and his ſon in law, Maſter <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay,</hi> as is ſuggeſted by the Informer, but was ſo far from doing ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt an act, that during the ſtay of the ſaid four Captains, and their Companies in the Garriſon, they received an equall and proportionable ſhare of the Victuals ſent by the Parliament unto his five Companies onely; and moreover, he then, and about that time did procure upon the credit and obligations of himſelf, and his friends, worth 1300 l. more in Corn, and other Proviſions, for his ſaid five Companies and Troop, beſides thoſe Proviſions before mentioned to be ſent them from the Parliament, without which care and charge, it was impoſſible for him to keep his Souldiers together, and to do ſervice for the publike, in a remote Garriſon, invironed then with Rebels on all ſides.</p>
            <p n="3">III. To the third Article, this Reſpondent ſaith, That one <hi>James Dunbar</hi> Eſquire, and ſon and heir of Sir <hi>John Dunbar</hi> Knight (whoſe Lands, with a good Iron-work thereon, lies next adjoyning, to part of the Lands of the Informer, whoſe deſire to intrude upon and gain their Rights to himſelf (as they often affirmed to this Reſpondent) begot much contention amongſt them, (as it did between him and all others, alſo who were his Landed Neighbours) which bred ſuch malice in the heart of the Informer againſt the ſaid <hi>James,</hi> that he not onely exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly thirſted after his life, but after the Lives alſo of his two ſervants the <hi>Hetheringtons,</hi> in the ſaid Article mentioned, (not Papiſts as therein is ſurmiſed) but then, and now Proteſtants, who as well to ſhun the malice of the Informer, as the fury of the Rebels, came with his ſaid Father unto this Reſpondent in <hi>December,</hi> 1641. Who intruſted the ſaid <hi>James</hi> with the cuſtody of the Caſtle of <hi>Liſſgole</hi> neer <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> with 74. perſons with him, where he was aſſaulted the 18. of <hi>December,</hi> 1641. or thereabouts, by a powerfull party of the enemy under the conduct of <hi>Rorie Magwire,</hi> brother of the Lord <hi>Magwire,</hi> who then took and burned the ſaid Caſtle, and maſſacred all that were in it, except the ſaid <hi>James Dunbar,</hi> whom the Rebels kept in priſon, untill <hi>May</hi> or <hi>June,</hi> 1642. At which time he made an eſcape, and came again (accompanied with the ſaid two <hi>Hetheringtons</hi>) unto this Reſpondent, where the ſaid <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> went to Church, and did many good and acceptable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158501:6"/>ſervices, behaving themſelves honeſtly and valiantly in all that time, and as he is informed, or both together with their Maſter at this time, in the ſervice of this Honourable Parliament, under Generall Major <hi>Monroe</hi> (whoſe Kinſman the ſaid <hi>James Dunbar</hi> is.) And where he and his ſaid men, are ready to anſwer ought the Informer can lay to their charge; but this Reſpondent ſaith, That he never knew, or heard, that the ſaid <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> joyned themſelves with the Rebels, or plundered the ſaid Serjeant <hi>Abrels</hi> houſe, or afterward burned it; neither was their any proof thereof made by the ſaid <hi>Abrel,</hi> or any witneſſes upon Oath, or otherwiſe produced, before the Reſpondent; neither did he deem it requiſit upon the bare Letters of the Informer, (knowing his malice towards them for their Maſters ſake) to commit them to Priſon, where they might have ſtarved for want of ſuſtenance; neither did he ſuffer them, as Fellons, or Traitors, to eſcape, for that they in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, did deſtroy divers Rebels, and Traytors, whileſt they remained at <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> under this Reſpondents command.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. To the fourth Article of the ſaid Information, this Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſaith, That upon the firſt of <hi>July</hi> 1642. or thereabouts, the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former having a deſign upon the Town of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> about ten miles from his houſe, marched to the Caſtle of <hi>Robert Parck</hi> Eſquire, in the ſaid Article mentioned, an Engliſh Proteſtant, and a Juſtice of Peace; which before the Rebellion, was poſſeſſed of an eſtate of about 1000 l. a yeer, and one that was of very good repute and eſteem amongſt his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and who (as this Reſpondent hath been often informed by cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible perſons) had (to the beſt of his power) oppoſed the Rebels in the beginning of that Rebellion, without complying, or any way correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponding with them. And under colour of going forward with that deſign, procured the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> with 30, or 40. of his Souldiers to accompany him to <hi>Sligoe;</hi> and when they came neer the ſaid Town, both Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Souldiers, and thoſe of the Informers entered the Suburbs thereof; and having burned ſome few houſes in it, and received ſome Brittiſh Proteſtants that eſcaped unto them from the Rebels, they brought them unto the Informer, where he ſtood aloof with the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck;</hi> two of the ſaid reſcued Proteſtants, namely, <hi>John We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therspin</hi> the father, and <hi>James Witherspin</hi> his ſon, both Scotchmen, were queſtioned by the Informer, wherefore they were amongſt the Rebels. The father anſwered, that by reaſon of his age (being about 70 yeers old, or upwards) and that he was ſick and Bedridden three moneths before, he could not get away, but lived upon the Alms of the people; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon one of the Informers ſervants told him, that this old man was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Tenant to one <hi>John Waldrome</hi> Eſquire, (a Gentleman that had an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158501:7"/>eſtate neer the Informers Lands in that Countrey) and had borne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe upon Oath on his Land-lords part, in matter of title of Land, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Informer, by means whereof, the cauſe was decreed for Maſter <hi>Waldrome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note, that this <hi>John Whether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpin,</hi> conceived to have been the Father, was not the man the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> ſhot, as aforeſaid, yet was hanged by him, but it was another old ſick Bedridden Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that was ſo ſhot, and kild by him, in manner aforeſaid.</note> againſt the Informer, or matter to that purpoſe. Upon which (without uſing any more words) he ſhot, and kild the poor decreeped old man, which was the firſt, and laſt man, the Informer kild with his own hands ſince the Rebellion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as ſome of his own ſervants and Souldiers affirmed. Whereupon, being informed by <hi>James Wetherspin,</hi> the ſon, that the Forces of the County of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> were upon their march, to joyn with the <hi>O Roirkes,</hi> for to trouble <hi>Mannor-hammilton,</hi> he together with Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> and both their Companies, haſtened back to Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> houſe, where at the importunitie of the Informer (as this Reſpondent hath been credibly informed) he got the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> and his Company (for the better guard of him, and his men) to accompany him to <hi>Mannor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hammilton.</hi> And although in the way they were hard beſet by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, inſomuch, as the Informer in a Bog, was unhorſe't, and his Horſe, with Furniture, and Piſtols, taken by the Rebels; by whom, he had been then ſlain, or taken, if by the care and valour of the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> and ſome of his Souldiers, he had not been horſed again, and brought off.
<note place="margin">Note, that there were Suites de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending both in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in <hi>England,</hi> between Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>James Wetherſpin,</hi> ſome yeers before the Rebellion. And that the ſaid <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſpin,</hi> being ſerved in <hi>Ireland</hi> with a Command, Dated the <hi>14.</hi> of <hi>January, 1640.</hi> under the hand of the Speaker of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> at the inſtance of the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> he appeared here in <hi>London, 7. April. 1641.</hi> where having attended the Houſe to anſwer Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> complaint, untill the <hi>20</hi> of <hi>September, 1641.</hi> And (not being able longer to ſtay) he returned into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> became his Judge and Executioner, as in this Anſwer is declared.</note> Yet when they had eſcaped that danger, and were come to the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers houſe (as this Reſpondent hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly heard) he took the ſaid <hi>James We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therspin</hi> (for having formerly witneſſed with his Father againſt him, as aforeſaid) and twiſted a Cord with a wrinch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his head ſo hard, that his blood ſtreamed forth of his Ears, Eies, Noſe, and Mouth; in which tortures, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued him during his pleaſure, and then eaſing him of that, did caſt him into a Dungeon, where he continued him lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing for hunger, from Thurſday untill the Wedneſday following: And did cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly puniſh a poor Scotſh-woman, which in pitty did caſt him an handfull of Oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal under the door, which the miſerable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158501:7"/>man, did lick with his Tongue from the dirt, his hands and feet, being faſt tied together with Cords or Withes; and upon the Wedneſday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, cauſed him to be hanged. Who at the beginning of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, with a Horſe, Sword, and Fowling-Peace, came to him, offering his ſervice againſt the Rebels, from whom, not withſtanding he took the ſaid Horſe and Arms, commanding him to be gone out of his Garriſon, and that if he did not, he would hang him, or if ever he got him again, he would be his death; which he faithfully performed, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And alſo upon the Informers entrance into his Caſtle, he made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſhews of welcome to the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> whileſt in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, he cauſed all his Souldiers to be diſarmed, and they put in reſtraint in ſeverall lower Rooms in his houſe; and then, when he perceived no danger of oppoſition, he arreſted the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> charging him with Treaſon, and committed him cloſe Priſoner, where he detained him in durance, the ſpace of a yeer and upwards, without ſuffering any man, except Serjeant Major <hi>James Galbraith,</hi> to ſpeak unto him, which was but once, and that upon much importunitie; whoſe extreme miſery, was lamentably bewailed by all the men that were in that Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. And then he not onely ſeized upon, and kept his Caſtle of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town,</hi> putting a Guard of his own into it; but alſo plundered, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to his own uſe, all his Money, Plate, Arms, Houſholdſtuff, Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Furniture, and all other his Goods whatſoever, which he had then as wel without, as within doors there, not ſuffering his Souldiers to come out of reſtraint, or uſe their own Arms, untill he had unlawfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled them, to take an Oath to ſerve as Souldiers under his onely Command. By reaſon whereof, the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> was utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to perform far greater, and much more advantageous Services, in every degree, in that place, for this Honourable Parliament againſt the Rebels, then ever the Informer did, or could do there, as this Reſpondent hath been credibly informed, as well by the Teſtimony of ſundry other honeſt men, as by the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>Whereupon Sir <hi>Edward Pavie</hi> Knight, whoſe daughter was the Wife of the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> together with others his friends (being advertiſed of his extreme hard uſage) Petitioned the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for his removall to <hi>Dublin,</hi> to anſwer ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as the Informer had to lay to his charge, and entered into Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of 10000 l. for his appearance, upon which their Lordſhips by Order dated in <hi>May</hi> 1643. or thereabouts, required the Informer, to ſet the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> at libertie, to be ſent either to Captain <hi>Folliot</hi> to <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhannan,</hi> or unto this Reſpondent to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> together with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that he had to object againſt him. That ſo he might be conveighed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158501:8"/>by them, or one of them to <hi>London-Derry,</hi> to be ſent from thence to <hi>Dublin.</hi> But the Informer (notwithſtanding the ſaid Order, was ſhewed unto him) denied obedience thereunto, and detained the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> ſtill in durance, untill his ſaid friends procured ſeverall Orders, commanding his inlargement, yet nothing would prevail to that effect with him, untill that about the beginning of <hi>Septtmber,</hi> 1643. Captain <hi>King</hi> coming with a Troop of Horſe from <hi>Conaught,</hi> into <hi>Vlster,</hi> about ſome buſineſſe he had with Sir <hi>William Stuart,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Stuart;</hi> he came about the thirteenth of that moneth to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> unto this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent, who ſent his Enſign with fifty Muskettiers, to guard the ſaid Troop to the Abbey of <hi>Boyl</hi> in <hi>Conaught,</hi> which is about fourty miles from <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> who were ſo far from knowing, or allowing of the ſaid Ceſſation, mentioned in the ſaid fourth Article, that they fought with, and kild ſome Rebels in the paſſe of <hi>Ballinafadd,</hi> and took a prey from thence to the <hi>Boyl;</hi> whence upon return of the ſaid Enſign, he came to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> in his way, where he delivered a Letter from this Reſpondent, to Lieutenant <hi>Leſley,</hi> the Informers Lievtenant, it being directed to the Informer, or in his abſence, to the Officer in chief at <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> with an Order of the Copy of an Order, which the Reſpondent received from the ſaid Captain <hi>Foliot,</hi> in it directed alſo as aforeſaid, from the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the inlargement of the ſaid <hi>Parck,</hi> to be ſent to <hi>Iniskillin</hi> or <hi>Ballyſhannon,</hi> which this Reſpondent left to his choice to do, or not to do, as beſt pleaſed the Informer, or his ſaid Officer; who ſent the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> along with the ſaid Enſign, and becauſe he was ſenſible of the great miſery which he had wrongfully ſuſtained by his Captains ſeveritie, he deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> two of his own Horſes, with ſome other little help, toward his charges, as the ſaid <hi>Parck,</hi> told this Reſpondent when he came to <hi>Iniskillin;</hi> before which time, this Reſpondent was never acquainted with him, neither did this Reſpondent know, or ever heard, that he was affected to the Rebels, neither did he know any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of certainty of the concluding of the Ceſſation with the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, untill he received advertiſement, together with a Proclamation to that effect, from the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the 23. of <hi>October,</hi> 1643. or thereabouts, nor did he, or could he obey the ſaid Ceſſation, before, or ſince that day; neither did he take any notice, whether the Informer, or his Wife and Children, were gone to <hi>London-Derry;</hi> neither was the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> at that time, Lord Juſtice, Lord Deputy, or Lord Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor did this Reſpondent receive any ſuch commands from his Lordſhip, to ſend to the Informer, as in the ſaid fourth Article is ſurmized; neither did this Reſpondent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158501:8"/>look for, or expect any indirect correſponding from the Informers Lievtenant.</p>
            <p>And this Reſpondent ſaith, That as a Priſoner, and poor diſtreſſed Engliſhman, his Countrey-man (being under bail and mainprize as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid) he gave ſome entertainment unto the ſaid <hi>Parck,</hi> for ſome few weeks in his houſe, far ſhort of feaſting, as the Informer terms it, and not finding ſafety to convey him by the neereſt way to <hi>Dublin,</hi> he ſent a guard together with one <hi>Henry Langford,</hi> and other Engliſh and Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with him, to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> again, where he heard he was lodged for a night, and where the Informer, or his Officer, might have detained him if they pleaſed: But from thence he was conveyed by the ſaid <hi>Langford</hi> and others, to the Abbey of <hi>Boyl,</hi> whence after, he reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered of a Feaver (whereof he had almoſt died) he repaired to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and according to the condition of his ſaid friends Recognizance, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared before the Lords Juſtices and Councell, at the Councell Board there, where how he was proceeded withall, this Reſpondent knoweth not, neither did this Reſpondent return him back amongſt the Rebels, neither doth he know, whether any of them did company him to <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> neither doth this Reſpondent believe, that the ſtate there would grant him an Order for Reſtitution of his Caſtle, with whatſoever Arms, or Goods, were in it, unleſſe it appeared to them, that he was wrongfully expulſed by the Informer. And this Reſpondent ſaith, That he heard, that by vertue of ſuch Order of the State, the ſaid Caſtle was reſtored unto him, and that he keeps it, as the reſt of the Brittiſh Forces in <hi>Conaught</hi> doth their Holds, for the Parliament forces. For upon the 25. of <hi>March</hi> laſt paſt (as this Reſpondent hath been informed,) the ſaid <hi>Parck,</hi> his Souldiers of <hi>Newtown,</hi> with the Informers Souldiers, did ſpoil and prey the Rebels at <hi>Dromahear,</hi> within ſix miles of <hi>Caſtle-ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> and two miles of Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Caſtle of <hi>Newtown,</hi> ſo as the Informers allegation, that he and the Rebels, makes good that Caſtle againſt the Parliament, to the prejudice of the Parliaments ſervice, and the danger and hazard of all thoſe parts of <hi>Conaught,</hi> is meerly ſurmiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, invented, and deviſed, of purpoſe (as this Reſpondent conceives) to make him odious on the one ſide, that the Informer may thereby, the better work his malice againſt him, and on the other ſide, to bring the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> into the diſpleaſure of the Parliament, whereby he may make way to gain his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>And this Reſpondent further ſaith, That he never knew, or heard of any Orders or Commands, ſent unto the Informer, by the ſaid Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> to the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck;</hi> neither did he know, or doth beleeve, the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> to be an utter enemy to the Parliament, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158501:9"/>their proceedings, nor doth he know, neither doth it concern him, whether the Lord Viſcount <hi>Taaffe,</hi> did by his Letters ſolicite the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, for the delivery of the ſaid <hi>Parck.</hi> But this Reſpondent doth beleeve in his conſcience, That if the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> had but 1000 l. in the world, he would give 500 l. of it to be here now, to be a moſt humble Suiter to this Honourable Parliament for remedy, againſt the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, for theſe and many other intollerable wrongs, and high op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions done him, by the ſaid Informer. And this Reſpondent hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly craveth leave, to declare further, the behaviour of the ſaid Informer, towards <hi>Thomas Abbercromy</hi> Eſquire, a Proteſtant, and principall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker in that Plantation, and ſometimes High-Sheriff of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whoſe Eſtate there bordered upon the Informers, within a mile of his Caſtle, whom he alſo Impriſoned, and kept in miſerable durance, for a long time, out of the malice, which in particular, he bore to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and alſo unto his Father in law, Sir <hi>John Dunbar</hi> Knight, and <hi>James Dunbar</hi> Eſquire, his Brother in law, not ſuffering any to waſh his linnen, but was neceſſitated, with his own hands, to waſh his ſhirts in his own Urine: And at length being ſet at liberty, the poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with his Wife, and Children, came (in great want of all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> to this Reſpondent, who uſed means to releeve them untill he conveyed them towards his native Countrey of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further this Reſpondent ſaith, That (as he hath been credily In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by divers honeſt Proteſtants, who well knew the Informers evil carriages to thoſe that were under his command, and more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Proteſtants that fled from Sir <hi>John Dunbars</hi> Iron-works, to his houſe, for ſafeguard of their lives) the Informer compelled many of them (without ſending guards or convoys with them) to depart from his Garriſon, inſomuch, as by their endeavouring to travell twenty miles over Mountainous wayes, towards <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> many of them were murthered in their journey, by the Rebels. And in particular, twelve or fourteen perſons at one time, and divers of them famiſhed through hunger and cold, which will be proved by ſundry men and women of the ſame Companies, whoſe Fortune it was (through Gods Providence) to eſcape thoſe dangers. And are now reſident partly under this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent at <hi>Imskillin,</hi> and others of them diſperſedly dwelling amongſt other Regiments in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
            <p n="5">V. To the fifth Article this Reſpondent ſaith, That he did not know in the Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> after the ſaid Ceſſation, whether or no, the ſaid Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> was Lord Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor whether he was declared an Enemy to the Parliament, nor did he hear any other, then that he was gracious and acceptable unto the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158501:9"/>untill this Reſpondent was now upon his journey to <hi>London,</hi> and ſaith, that after concluding of the ſaid Ceſſation (which how acceptable it was to the Parliament, this Reſpondent being ſo remote, underſtood not,) he by vertue of a Commiſſion, dated in <hi>November</hi> or <hi>December,</hi> 1641. from Sir <hi>William Parſons,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Borlace,</hi> then Lords Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Councell there, did upon the 29. of <hi>January,</hi> 1643. or thereabouts, receive <hi>Tirlagh oge mac Gawran,</hi> and ſome follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his, being Inhabitants of the Barony of <hi>Tallaghagh</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cavan,</hi> together with their Goods into protection, appointing them ſome quarters to dwell and graſe upon, neer <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> untill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to the contrary, ſhould come from the Parliament, and that upon agreement, that they ſhould pay 70 l. in Money or Victuals, by a time limited, towards the better ſubſiſtance of the Souldiers of this Reſpondents Regiment, for the preſerving of that Garriſon, whoſe proviſions being then neer ſpent, had no hopes to be ſupplied by the State there, and as little expectation to be furniſhed in due time from hence, and the ſaid protected men having delivered in one of their Kinſmen unto this Reſpondent, to remain in priſon at <hi>Iniskillin</hi> in pledge as well for their Loyalties, during their continuance upon the ſaid Protection, as the paying of the ſaid Contribution, and performing other duties, conformable to their agreement, gathered their Goods from remote parts, and upon the ſecond of <hi>February,</hi> 1643. or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, were coming to the quarters aſſigned to them by this Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; but by the way, the Souldiers of the Informer, incountering them, declared, that they were in want of Victuals in their Garriſon; and although they would forbear to kill them (for ſo far they agreed to the ſaid Protection) yet they would, and muſt borrow ſome Cows from them upon Ticket, to be payed by the State, out of their entertainment, and thereupon took from them three or four hundred Cows, whereof their Officers at <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> (upon the mediation of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondents Lievtenant Colonell) cauſed the greateſt part to be reſtored again unto the ſaid Owners, but refuſed to deliver the reſt. Of which (upon the next occaſion, that this Reſpondent had to write to <hi>Dublin</hi>) at the requeſt of the ſaid Owners, he gave intimation unto the then Lords Juſtices and Councell; and thereupon, the ſaid Lord Marqueſſe being newly then, Lord Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> did by his Warrant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, not onely the reſtoring of the reſidue of the ſaid Goods unto the Owners; but withall, required better correſpendency to be obſerved for the future, between the Officers and Souldiers of the Informer, and thoſe of <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> and not to claſh or jar between themſelves; but whether the ſaid latter Order was obeyed, as touching the reſtitution of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158501:10"/>the ſaid Goods; this Reſpondent knoweth not, and faith, That the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers of the ſaid Garriſons, not in obedience to that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but of their own mutuall accords (have ever ſince the Informer left thoſe parts) lived in better amitie, then ever they did, or could do, whileſt he continued there amongſt them: Nevertheleſſe, this Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent faith, That by reaſon of that impediment, offered by the Informers Souldiers, as aforeſaid, this Reſpondent and his Souldiers loſt the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of that bargain, to the great prejudice of that Garriſon.</p>
            <p>And faith further, That the Informer or his Officers, received into his Protection (by what authority this Reſpondent could never yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand) one <hi>Owin,</hi> or <hi>James mac Murrey, Margaret Ny Cabe,</hi> and ſundry other Rebels of the Countie of <hi>Letrym,</hi> and kept them and their Goods upon his own Lands of <hi>Glanfern,</hi> neer his Garriſon in that County, which will be proved by Certificate, and ſundry Letters of the date of <hi>January,</hi> 1643. under the hand of his own Lievtenant and others.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. To the ſixth Article, this Reſpondent denieth, that ever he correſponded with the Rebels, as by the ſaid Informer is therein ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted; but faith, That by vertue of the aforeſaid Commiſſion from the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he did receive into protection, one <hi>Bryan mac Coconaght mac Gwire</hi> Eſquire, with fourty or fifty of his Friends, Servants, and Tenants, who had ſome Goods of their own to live upon, taking Pledges from ſome of them, for Aſſurance of their Loyalties; which Protection, this Reſpondent humbly conceiveth was lawfull for him to grant unto the ſaid <hi>Bryan Magwire,</hi> for the Reaſons following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For that upon the 21. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. he diſcovered unto this Reſpondent by <hi>Flartagh mac Hugh</hi> aforenamed, the purpoſe of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to riſe into Rebellion upon Friday and Saturday, the 22. and 23. of <hi>October</hi> aforeſaid, adviſing him, and all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in the Town of <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> and County of <hi>Farmanagh,</hi> to be carefully upon their defence; which this Reſpondent acknowledgeth, was (by Gods mercy and providence) the principall Motive that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the Murthering of this Reſpondent, and of all thoſe Proteſtants that eſcaped that bloody Maſſacre thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For that the ſaid <hi>Bryan</hi> did refuſe to joyn in any Action with the Rebels, denying to enter into their Oaths of Confederacy and Aſſociation againſt the Proteſtants, for which, he was in great danger to be cut off by them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For that he preſerved under his own Protection, divers of the Brittiſh Nation, Proteſtants; which together with ſeverall of their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158501:10"/>Goods he brought ſafe to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> when he was ſo received into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, as <hi>Ambroſe Carleton, Richard Irwing, Gawan Bettie,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, For that by receiving him, being an eminent man of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and allied unto many Noble Families, (both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>) it exceedingly abated the fury and courage of the Rebels, and diſtracted their Conſultations in thoſe Parts; and wholly dis-joyned the Forces of the Rebels in that County, by dividing themſelves into factions; and no leſſe diſheartned thoſe of the next adjoyning Counties, which in that interim, and for a long time after, did abundantly advantage, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Publike Service.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, For that in further Evidence of his Loyalty to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown and Government, he preſented a Letter unto this Reſpondent, which came unto him from <hi>Owin mac Artt O Neille</hi> (Uncle of the Lord <hi>Magwire,</hi> and Generall of the Rebels in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi>) who lately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, arived in <hi>Ireland,</hi> with Men, Arms, and Ammunition, out of <hi>Weſt-Flanders,</hi> which Letter is as followeth, <hi>vix.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To our Loving and Dear Couſien, <hi>Bryan mac Coconaght Magwire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Loving Couſin,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>KNow that I am arived at this Harbour, nine or ten dayes paſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſent before me, as much Ammunition as I deemed needfull, to anſwer the neceſſitie of this Countrey: And that I have here now, Men and Proviſions, ſuch as (by the leave of God) will give great comfort and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour unto this whole Kingdom. But beloved Couſin, I am given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that (not withſtanding your ſufferance and diſtreſſe) you are abund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly inclined to ſide with the Engliſh Nation, which indecd doth exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieve me; Wherefore, I will have you from henceforth (as you tender your own good) to baniſh thoſe thoughts out of your minde, and not to purſue thoſe Reſolutions, which in the end, may be the occaſion of your own Deſtruction, as I think it will be to all thoſe, whoſe mindes will appear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ours: Let theſe ſuffice with the addage of many ſalutes unto you, from <hi>Caſtle-Do,</hi> the <hi>18.</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1642.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your affectionate Kinſman, Signed, <hi>Owen O Neille.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:158501:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:158501:11"/>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:158501:12"/>
            <p> And beſides, the ſaid <hi>Bryan</hi> gained Intelligence of great concernment, from the enemy, and diſcovered it at all times, and upon all occaſions unto this Reſpondent, who made great uſe thereof, for the furtherance, and advancement of the Publike Service; whereof, this Reſpondent made report by his Letters unto Sir <hi>William Parſons,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> then Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Councell there, to whom he did ſend the ſaid <hi>Bryan Magwire</hi> to <hi>Dublin,</hi> who did not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of this Reſpondents act in receiving of him and his men, into Protection, as aforeſaid, but alſo (as this Reſpondent was informed) did further ſigniſie unto this Honourable Parliament, the affection and ſervice of the ſaid <hi>Bryan,</hi> with their deſires in his behalf, that he ſhould be rewarded for the ſame. And afterward their Lordſhips returned the ſaid <hi>Bryan</hi> unto this Reſpondent, allowing him and his men, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued upon Protection at <hi>Iniskillin:</hi> Neer unto which Garriſon, he remains loyall, even at this time, but in a moſt miſerable condition for want of neceſſaries. And this Reſpondent denieth, That ever he did forme the ſaid protected men into a Company, conſiſting of a Captain and Officers, as in the ſaid ſixth Article is meerly deviſed and ſurmiſed, but did imploy them under the leading of ſome of the Brittiſh Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of his Garriſon, upon Service many times, with the reſt of his Regiment, againſt the Rebels; wherein they were of abundant uſe, as well for Spies and Guides, as by killing and deſtroying the enemy, as effectually as others did; and (for ought known by this Reſpondent) did no diſ-ſervice at any time unto the State, in giving Intelligence againſt all, or any of the Brittiſh of their proceedings; and divers of the ſaid protected men, being taken priſoners at ſeverall times, by the Rebels, were put to death, for taking part with this Reſpondent. But this Reſpondent denieth, That all the ſaid protected men did take their opportunity, to turn to the Rebels again, as is ſurmiſed; but ſome few that did (leaving their Pledge which they gave for aſſurance of their Loyalty, in priſon at <hi>Iniskillin,</hi>) this Reſpondent cauſed him to be hanged, when they proved diſloyall. And this Reſpondent humbly conceiveth, That as <hi>Rahab</hi> and her Parents, Family, and Friends, for her ſake, were preſerved in <hi>Jericho</hi> for ſaving the two Spies of <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> ſo this Honourable Parliament, will be pleaſed to think, That this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent did no diſ-ſervice unto the State, in protecting, and preſerving of the ſaid <hi>Bryan Magwire,</hi> and ſome of his Friends for his ſake; who was the Inſtrument of the ſaving of the lives of many thouſands of Proteſtants (even Gods people) from being utterly deſtroyed by the fury of the ſaid bloody Rebels.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:158501:12"/>
            <p> ANd for anſwer unto that expreſſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſaid Informer ſeems to conclude his Information,
<note place="margin">Note, that ſince this Anſwer was ſent into the Commons Houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> received a Letter of the <hi>8.</hi> of <hi>January, 1644.</hi> Written by one of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of his Regiment from <hi>Iniskillin;</hi> certifying that about that time, four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Horſe, and <hi>120.</hi> Foot of that Garriſon, fought with and routed <hi>500.</hi> Foot, and <hi>3.</hi> Troops of Horſe of the Rebels, conducted by Colonell <hi>Philip O Rely,</hi> wherein they not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued their own Cattle which were Plundered by the Enemy: But alſo kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>140.</hi> of them in the place, and took <hi>55.</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, whereof are Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, one Serjeant Major, <hi>3.</hi> Captains, two Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, with divers Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and other Officers. Whereby it appears, that neither the ſaid Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> or his Souldiers, did any way correſpond with the Rebels, ſince the Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or before.</note> by ſaying, he could inform many other particular omiſſions and diſ-ſervices, which the ſaid Reſpondent hath committed in this time of his imployment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent faith, That he conceiveth the Informer means it, by the ſcandalous calumnies and aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions digeſted in fifteen places of that Pamphlet, Printed at <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1643. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Services are regiſtred, and wherein this Reſpondent and his Captains, Officers, and Souldiers, are moſt injuriouſly taxed, with often reiterations of unworthy and mean carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, for that they did not wait upon him, upon all his calls, which this Reſpondent conceiveth, was more then he was bound to do, further then to this Reſpondent would ſeem fit, for the good of the Publike Service, eſpecially, when as at the ſame very times (which was long before the Ceſſation) he was imployed about ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of far greater and better concernment in the Counties of <hi>Fermanagh, Cavan, Monaghan, Tirone, Donegall, Letrim,</hi> or <hi>Sligoe,</hi> which hath formerly been well known, both in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and elſe where.</p>
            <p>And this Reſpondent further ſheweth, That immediately after the ſaid Ceſſation, this Reſpondents Regiment deſtroyed 296. of the Rebels, and famiſhed many hundreds of them, and alſo took in <hi>Rory mac Gwires</hi> Caſtle, which is now preſerved for the Parliaments uſe: And as well then, as before, did reſcue, or otherwiſe redeem from the ſaid Rebels, 5467 <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Proteſtants, and relieved them for many Moneths, out of the ſpoils gained from the enemy, untill that in his own perſon, he guarded and conveied great numbers of them towards <hi>London-Derry,</hi> where further care was taken for their relief, by the good people there: And ſaith alſo, That he this Reſpondent, was one of the firſt Colonels of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Regiments in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> which did imbrace, and take the Solemn League and Covenant, which he humbly conceives will not be deemed to be Omiſſions or Diſ-ſervices, as the Informer terms them; who ſince his coming hither, hath not onely laboured to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158501:13"/>defame the Reſpondent, but alſo hath taxed the reſt of the Colonels in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> for their neglects in their Service, who (in this Reſpondents o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion) have done much better Service, then either of them.</p>
            <p>Yet did this Reſpondent, ſeverall times, ſhew his deſires in a moſt effectuall manner, to help and relieve the ſaid Informer; for having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a pittifull Meſſage from him, about the 26. of <hi>July,</hi> 1642. That he, his Wife, Children, and Souldiers, were like to be deſtroyed by nine hundred of the Rebels, that then beſieged him: This Reſpondent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly ſent a party of four hundred Horſe and Foot, for his relief, with Orders, that after they had relieved the Informer, they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn within fourty eight hours: This Reſpondent being then threatned to be beſieged, by the Generall of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces <hi>Owin mac Art O Neille</hi> with 6000 men; but when the Reſpondents Lievtenant Colonell came to the Informer with this Party, they found him not at all beſieged, not in no ſuch extremity as he pretended, but perceived he ſent this preſſing Meſſage, onely to get ſome of the Reſpondents men with him, to take in the Caſtle of <hi>Dromahear,</hi> which without Ordnance, they could not have effected, though being come, at his importunitie they attempted, in concluſion, to no other purpoſe, then to deſtroy their men.</p>
            <p>Whereupon his Officers and Souldiers, returned on the 29. of <hi>July</hi> from him, having received many affronts and abuſes. And on the 20. of <hi>May</hi> following, this Reſpondent intending ſome ſervice in the Province of <hi>Conaught,</hi> drew forth about 500. Horſe and Foot, and Leaguring within two miles of the Informers Garriſon, was importuned with much earneſtneſſe to come unto him to Chriſten his Son, which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent (conceiving to be an act of charity and Chriſtianity) conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, expecting ſuch civilitie, as might be anſwerable to ſo neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly an Office. But both himſelf, and thoſe few Officers he carried with him, received ſuch groſſe diſ-reſpect, that he will not deſile your ears with the hearing it.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, God having bleſt the Reſpondent in his journey with ſucceſſe againſt the enemy, he gave him for the relief of his Garriſon two hundred fifty and nine Cows: There going with him in his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of their own accord, of the men belonging to his Garriſon, onely 38. Footmen, and 12. Horſe.</p>
            <p>He moreover then beſtowed upon his good Lady 1000. Sheep, and what he beſtowed on thoſe Gentlemen of his Ladies Kinred, and his Officers, who went in a friendly manner with this Reſpondent, the Informer ſuffered them not to enjoy, but converted to his own uſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe civilities, which this Reſpondent is moſt unwillingly drawn to mention, he conceived might deſerve more thanks, and not to be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:158501:13"/>and his Regiment, exclaimed againſt by the Informer, meerly to rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er him and them odious, in all places where his tongue gets him credit.</p>
            <p>In the time of Peace, his carriage towards hie neighbours, was ſo full of contention, that there was hardly any man of quality or worth neer him, in the Province of <hi>Conaught,</hi> that he had not laboured to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure and oppreſſe, either in their Eſtates or Reputations, if not in both, ſo that before the Rebellion began, ſuch his carriages made him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremly diſtaſtfull to men of all conditions, that lived within twenty or thirty miles of him, in that Province, which will be evidenced by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of his Neighbours, of the beſt qualitie, now in this City, if they may be called upon for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And particularly this Reſpondent, repreſenteth to your further notice, ſomething of the Informers demeanour towards ſome of his diſtreſſed Neighbours in the hands of the Rebels, deciphered in theſe two ſhort inſuing Letters, Printed in the latter end of that Book of his own Services, Page 57. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Sir <hi>Robert Hannay</hi>'s Letter, and other Proteſtants being Priſoners at <hi>Sligoe,</hi> are ſent to <hi>Dromahear</hi> Caſtle.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE the undernamed perſons, having ſuffered in all our whole Eſtates, and being upon our baniſhment, out of this Kingdom, under the ſafe conduct of Maſter</hi> Edmond Bourk <hi>of</hi> Ragagh, <hi>and Maſter</hi> Walter Bourk <hi>of</hi> Ardagh, <hi>towards the North, but moſt oppoſed at</hi> Caſtle-Coner; Eniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromme, Eſcagh-Bridge, Downeill, Arnaglaſſe <hi>and</hi> Tomler, <hi>go by ſeverall Bands of Armed men, purpoſely to ſet for our lives, were not there extreme violence ſuppreſſed by the diſcretion, worth, and care of thoſe two Gentlemen, and we taken Priſoners by the</hi> Mac Swines, <hi>brought before</hi> O Coner-Sligo, <hi>where we now remain, and intended to be ſent to the Caſtle of</hi> Dromahear, <hi>to be kept untill you Sir deliver ſuch Priſoners of the</hi> O Roirks <hi>and others, as you have in your cuſtodie, or to be dealt with, as you do unto them: Sir you are Nobly diſpoſed, ſo that in honour, we hope, the means of relief being in your ſelf, you will not ſuffer us to periſh, who will ever remain Sir</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Yours trulie obliged to ſerve you, Signed,</hi> Robert Hannay, Andrew Adare, Alexander Mountgomery, William Liſton, Thomas Fullerton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:158501:14"/>
            <p> Theſe be the names and number of the Priſoners, Sir <hi>Robert Hannay,</hi> his Lady, his two Daughters, two Boyes, two men, and a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; Maſter <hi>Andrew Adare,</hi> and his Wife, and Siſters Son; Maſter <hi>Alexander Mountgomery,</hi> his Wife, and eldeſt Son; Maſter <hi>William Liston,</hi> his Wife, and Daughter; Maſter <hi>Thomas Fullerton,</hi> and his Wife; <hi>Patrisk Deomand,</hi> Maſter <hi>Adares</hi> man.</p>
            <p>Sir, after the writing of this Letter, we are brought to <hi>Dromahear</hi> Caſtle, and Order left with the Captain to bring us unto the Camp at <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> where we muſt ſuffer death, if thoſe Priſoners with you be not delivered.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Sir <hi>Frederick Hammiltons</hi> Anſwer to the Letter afore-mentioned.</head>
                  <p>SIR, <hi>I have received your Letter, whereby I am given to underſtand of your treacherous ſurpriſall, not with ſtanding of your ſafe conduct promiſed, for the which I am very ſorry. But ſuch is the treacherous falſhood of thoſe diſtoyall Traitors, generally throughout this wholc Kingdom, that hath made me vew and ſwear, in the preſence of Almighty God, That I will never give or take quarter, with them, or any of them, yea, though my own Sons that diſcended from my Loyns, were in your eſtate, I had rather they ſhould die gloriouſly for the cauſe of Chriſt, then I ſhould ſo abaſe my ſelf, as to deal with ſuch Traytors to God and His Majeſtic. Thus beſeeching God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, to ſtrengthen and incourage you, that you may continue conſtant, untill it ſhall pleaſe God, to give you deliverance, either by life or death. In the mean time, I am perſwaded, that they will uſe you with no worſe meaſure, then their Priſoners, who were apprehended by me in the action of Rebellion are uſed: So recommending you to God, I rest,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your very loving friend,</hi> Frederick Hammilton.</signed>
                     <dateline>Caſtle-Hammilton, <date>
                           <hi>January the</hi> 19. 1641.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And after he delivered this Letter unto the Meſſenger, he hanged the chief of the Priſoners (being brother to Colonell <hi>O Roirke,</hi> who was deſired by this exchange) in the ſight of the Meſſenger, before he would permit him to depart, upon whoſe return to the Rebels, they in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge thereof, murthered about ten or eleven of the ſaid Proteſtants, whereof two were godly Miniſters; and yet if their mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, in the midſt of their Barbaritie, had not far tranſcended Sir
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158501:14"/>
               <hi>Frederick Hammiltons,</hi> they had likewiſe put Sir <hi>Robert Hannay,</hi> and his Lady, and Children, and all the reſt to death.</p>
            <p>And that his ill diſpoſition may the more fully appear, he hath with ſtriking, and other ill uſage, ſo behaved himſelf, toward his Officers, that his Lievtenant, Enſigne, Miniſter, and one of his Serjeants, have all forſaken him; ſo that he hath now no Officers, but one Serjeant to command his Company, at <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> conſiſting of ſeventy men, or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>And not withſtanding all this, The ſaid Informer is labouring for the Government of <hi>London-Derry;</hi> and becauſe he conceived he might prevail in that ſuit, if his miſcarriages were not diſcovered, he moved this Reſpondent, that all the differences betwixt them, might be compoſed by the order of friends; which motion, if this Reſpondent would then have accepted, he conceives this Information had never been heard of.</p>
            <p>And as touching the Government of <hi>London-Derry</hi> aforeſaid, this Reſpondent humbly deſires leave to declare, that once it was conferred upon Sir <hi>George Pawlet,</hi> a man whoſe temper in ſome things, was not much unlike this of the Informers, whoſe paſſionate demeanour in his Office, was not onely the occaſion of the loſſe of his own life, but of the loſſe alſo of the lives of many of this Nation there, and the burning of that Town, with the kindling of a violent (though as it hapned) but a ſhort Rebellion in the Countrey thereabouts, which did put the State then, to much unneceſſary expences in the ſuppreſſing of it.</p>
            <p>All which, together with the premiſſes, this Reſpondent humbly repreſenteth as pertinent inſtances, and reaſons, to induce the honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Parliament, not to put the Government thereof into the power of the Informer, whoſe demeanour will never be brooked, by thoſe good people that now inhabit there, upon whom, all the aſperſions that are laid by any late reports or Printed Letters (this Reſpondent beleeves) were invented and contrived by the Informer, or his Inſtruments, of purpoſe to make them deteſtable to this Honourable Parliament, whom this Reſpondent is confident, are as loyall, and wel-wiſhing to the Parliament, as can be expected; and will really witneſſe the ſame, by their ready and joyfull receiving and obeying of any Governour (except Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi>) that the Parliament will be pleaſed to appoint over them. But his conditions are ſo well known unto them, that they will quit their fortunes and ſtations there, which they have hither to preſerved, with ſo much expence and hazard, rather then ſubmit unto his Command.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:158501:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And this Respondent moſt humbly deſires this honourable Committee, would be pleaſed to pardon him, if he have trespaſſed upon your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, in anſwer to the Charge given in by the Informer, being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated thereunto, for his more ample Vindication, by laying open the diſpoſition of the Informer, which he hath moſt unneceſſary drawn upon himſelf, without any provocations given to him, by this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent. And humbly prayes, ſuch reparations as in your Wiſdoms ſhall be thought fit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Exhibited</hi> 
                        <date>11. <hi>of January.</hi> 1644.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed,</hi> William Cole.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="reply_to_answer">
            <head>The Replication of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> Knight, and Colonell, To the Scandalous Recriminating Anſwer of Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> Given in to the Information of the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> Exhibited againſt him, to the Honourable Committee of both Kingdoms, the 26. of <hi>December.</hi> 1644.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> confeſſeth the firſt charge, and for his defence pretendeth, That he gave advertiſement of the ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Rebellion, by his Letters to the then Lords Juſtices and Councell, with all poſſible ſpeed; with advice, That their Lordſhips would ſtrictly examine the Lord <hi>Mac Gwire,</hi> and others his Complices, concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>But if his notice given to the Lords Juſtices, had been ſo timely, as his Information was ſeaſonable, by him confeſſed to have been, twelve dayes before the breaking out of the ſaid Rebellion; without all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, the Lords Juſtices and Councell, would not have neglected the opportunity, of preventing ſo great a miſchief; which had not been eaſily done, if to have underſtood thereof, ſo long before, nor can it be credited for tructh, that the Reſpondent gave them any ſuch timely notice, when it is manifeſt, That the diſcovery thereof, unto the Lords
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158501:15"/>Juſtices and Councell, by Captain <hi>O Connelly,</hi> was with much difficulty to his perſon, very late in the night, immediately before the ſame day it was to have been acted at <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Reſpondent being a Juſtice of the Peace and Corum, and a man inveſted with great power and authority in his Countrey, and of great credit amongſt the people, by the duty of his place, ſhould, as very eaſily he might, and ought to have apprehended the Conſpirators; the ſaid Lord <hi>Mac Gwire,</hi> and the reſt of the chief of them, being his neer neighbours; whoſe perſons, if he had ſecured in ſo long time before the Tragedie was to have been acted, would have prevented their wicked deſigne, and diſheartned the reſt of their accomplices through the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to have proceeded; nor can the Reſpondent, pretend any want of force, to have inabled him in this action, the Kings High Sheriff of that County living within five miles to him; who being an active able Gentleman, could in a very ſhort time, have raiſed for his aſſiſtance, the power of the whole Brittiſh, had he been timely advertiſed, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly he ought to have been: So that for the Reſpondent thus to ſit ſtill in his own Caſtle, and to betray all his Neighbours, untill the very night before this bloody Rebellion broke out, and then to write Letters, as he alleageth, to warn his Neighbours and Tenants of this evill to come, who ſhould have been all in Arms, and apprehending the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators long before: Whether the Reſpondent performed the Office of a faithfull Magiſtrate, or the Duty and Courage of a Judicious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, or the Care and Providence of a good Neighbour, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subject, this Repliant leaveth it to your Judicious Conſiderations; And is verily perſwaded, That if the Reſpondent had timely delivered, but Arms to ſo many men, as he alleageth to have ſent Letters, and to have gone in the head of them, againſt thoſe Rebels, he might have done more good ſervice, for the ſafety of the Publike, his Neighbours, and Tenants, then all the Rhetorick he uſed in his Letters, to warn and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them of this danger: But his chief care appeared, the ſafety of himſelf at home in his Caſtle, to man, and ſecure that place; where much ado there was, (as the Repliant hath been informed) to perſwade the Reſpondent, for all his Regiment, in ſix moneths time, to ſet his Noſe out of that Caſtle, untill the greateſt ſury of the Rebels was paſt; and afterwards, for catching of Cows, and ſuch like plundering imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he proved very active: And that this Repliant, being from home, as the Reſpondent relateth, that he was, and in this caſe, ſhould be advertiſed by the Reſpondent, That there was intended ſuch an Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, it is much like his other aſſertion, That this Repliant herein doth want matter juſtly to accuſe him, as he hath informed: For certain
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:158501:16"/>it is, this Repliant never received Letter, or advertiſment from him, though he knew the Repliant to command the next Garriſon to him; which it pleaſed God, miraculouſly to preſerve, untill this Repliant with no ſmall hazard, returned amongſt them; at which time he did not delay venturing a Meſſenger, with a kinde Letter, to the Reſpondent, whoſe anſwer to the Repliants Letter followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur zeal to His Majeſties ſervice, the common good, and care of us in particular, expreſſed in your Letter of the 29. of this inſtant <hi>October,</hi> hath added comfort and courage to us, your friends, and fellow Souldiers; who do conceive, that our fears are greater (as you alleage) then cauſe requireth; for if the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> had unanimouſly uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Forces at the firſt, we had been able, not onely to have made head againſt the enemy, but alſo erre now, to have been Maſter of the Field: But their policy in giving out, that their Commiſſion was to deſtroy the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to ſpare the <hi>Scots,</hi> hath ſo prevailed with ſome of the more ignorant ſort of that Nation, that they withdraw their aſſiſtance from us, which as it could not but diſhearten us a little, ſo the enemy hath made advantage thereof: But the Sheriff of our County Maſter <hi>Adam Cathcart,</hi> and the reſt of his neighbours, by giving us two viſits with a good Troop of Horſe, with promiſe of Aſſiſtance, hath removed thoſe jealouſies, to which your worthy actions hath added a greater luſter; in ſo much, that I make no queſtion, that if a man of your eminency and worth, of that nation, would but once ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Field; it would not onely turn the Councell of the <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophell</hi> into fooliſhneſſe, but the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe, and all other parts, would reſort together in ſuch Troops, That we ſhould be able to bid them Battle; for we are (I thank God) above 200. ſtrong in the Caſtle, and Town of <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> which is as yet ſafe; and our <hi>Scotch</hi> Neighbours are as many in Foot and Horſe: Therefore I think it the beſt way to finde them out, and not to keep aſunder thus in our ſtrong Holds; for my own part, I do verily beleeve, that they are far ſhort of thoſe numbers, and Ammunition, they give out, except they reckon Boyes, and Calloghes: But the worſt is, we have little intelligence, but what we have from themſelves, who queſtionleſſe will make the beſt of all things, and the worſt for us: As for <hi>Dublin,</hi> I hope it is not taken, whither I ſent a Meſſenger on Saturday laſt, with Letters to the State, whereof I have ſent you here incloſed. <hi>Cavan</hi> we hear holds out, being ſtrengthned with a Troop of Horſe that lay at <hi>Turbbet:</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Atkinſon,</hi> upon what promiſes, I know not, hath yeelded up his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:158501:16"/>Caſtle to <hi>Bryan mac Gwire,</hi> without any reſiſtance, and is with him; and ſo have all the ſtrong holds of this County, except this of <hi>Iniskillin, Tully, Mo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ea,</hi> which we hope with Gods help and the aſſiſtance of our friends to defend in ſpight of our enemy: But they have got all the Goods and Ammunition of the whole County into their poſſeſſion. And though the Plot be Generall as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> give out, yet there is not ſo much ſeverity uſed in any part of the Kingdom, as in this County: So giving you many thanks for your good intelligence; which I intreat you upon all occaſions continue, with aſſurance, that you ſhall receive the like from me: As alſo the contents of your Letter conveyed to the Lords Juſtices, with all convenient ſpeed, with the tender of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to your ſelf, and Honourable Lady. I commit you, and all of us, to the ſafe protection of the Almighty, I reſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your true friend and ſervant, <hi>William Cole.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Iniskillin</hi> Caſtle, <date>the 2. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Together with this Anſwer, the Repliant received a Letter, ſigned by the forementioned Captain <hi>Adam Cathcart,</hi> then High Sheriff, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>William Acheſon,</hi> now Lievtenant Colonell to the Reſpondent: Who by that Letter, offered themſelves with their ſeverall Companies, which they then Commanded, to put themſelves under the Command of this Repliant, refuſing to take on with Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> at all: But this Repliant otherwiſe adviſed them, for the ſafety of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that they ſhould joyn themſelves with Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> hoping to have found him, a more faithfull Neighbour, then he proved. Some few dayes after this Letter received, Captain <hi>Hugh Roſſe,</hi> having former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been Chirurgion, for ſeverall yeers to the Repliants Foot Company, brought with him to the Repliants Garriſon, at <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> Captain <hi>George Greir,</hi> who had with them, two able Companies of the Repliants Countrymen, who were come a purpoſe to tender their ſervice unto him, who had much ado to perſwade them to return, or have any medling at all with Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> whoſe baſeneſſe in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kindes they much complained off, yet at laſt, the Repliant having uſed them, and their men kindly, with free-quarters in his Caſtle for two nights, did afterwards give every one of their Souldiers Money, and every Captain, and Officer, a proportion of Salt, whereof they were ſcarce at that time, and perſwaded them to return, promiſing to acknowledge themſelves as Companies ingaged to the Repliant, when he ſhould think fit to command them, who afterwards joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:158501:17"/>in the Reſpondents Regiment; and without thoſe four Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, could not have made up a Regiment there, though he proved very unthankfull to the Repliant afterwards. And whereas the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent mentioned in his Letter, Captain <hi>Roger Atkinſon,</hi> an Ancient Servitour in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, and a Noble Houſe-keeper, for many yeers together, living within a mile to the Reſpondent; who with his Wife and Family, had in former times received many charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Neighbourly helps and reliefs, from the ſaid <hi>Atkinſon</hi> and his vertuous Bedfellow, who was a neer Kinſwoman, to the now Earl of <hi>Leiſter:</hi> Nevertheleſſe, did the Reſpondent indeavour to caſt aſpertions upon this worthy Gentleman, as if had baſely parted with his Caſtle to the <hi>Iriſhes;</hi> whereas the fault ſhall appear in the Reſpondent, and his Treacherous and unneighbourly uſage of him, mentioned in this Letter, ſent by Captain <hi>Atkinſon</hi> to the Repliant, in Vindication of the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions caſt upon him by the Reſpondent as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ACcording to your deſire, you ſhall be pleaſed to underſtand the manner, how I left my houſe the 22. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. Towards night I received a note from Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> wherein he made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he had notice given him that day, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> was to make ſome attempt on the morrow, or ſoon after; and therefore wiſhed me to have ſome people about me, and to be upon my guard, Captain <hi>William Atcheſon</hi> being then within, to whom I ſhewed my Letter; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he went preſently to Sir <hi>William,</hi> to know the manner, and did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to come and acquaint me, how all things went that night, which he did; and withall, I ſent my man to call all my truſtieſt Tenants, to be with me preſently; ſome did come and went home again to bring ſome of their Goods, but did not return back again, ſo that night I cauſed charge all the Peeces I had, that was fixed; the next morning being Saturday, there came ſome Scotchmen by me, who dwelt towards <hi>Ballibalfoor,</hi> who told me, that all the Countrey that way was in fire, and that <hi>Rory mac Gwire</hi> was coming that way with a great many men all in Arms; and that Lough, which my Lady <hi>Goure</hi> lived in, was full of Boats and Cotts, with men and Arms, and that <hi>Rory mac Gwire,</hi> did not meddle with any Scotchmen at all, or their Goods; whereupon, all thoſe that were with me, went away home, and left me, and I having no more Powder then to charge my Peeces once again, took occaſion to ſend my man <hi>Humphrey,</hi> to Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> with money, deſiring him to ſend me twenty pound of Powder, and if not ſo much, to ſend me twelve, in regard I had ſent to <hi>Dublin</hi> a twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158501:17"/>before, to Captain <hi>Pinner,</hi> to get me ſome Powder out of the Store-houſe, which he did, but not ſo much as I wrote for; who ſent me word, That the Clerk of the Store-houſe promiſed to write to Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> to furniſh me with what I ſtood in need off, becauſe he had enough in his keeping; his anſwer returned me, was, That a pound of Powder was worth a pound of Silver: So Saturday, and Sunday, none came at me; but I perceived burning every where. On Munday morning, Sir <hi>William</hi> went to perſwade me for to leave my Houſe, and if I would come to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> he would ſend me a guard of fourty men Armed, to conduct me: Whereupon, I acquainted theſe few men that were with me, who all wiſhed me to go; and if I would not, that they all would go, for they all knew that I had no Ammunition: I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to write to Sir <hi>William,</hi> if he would ſend me the guard he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, I would come; and preſently got Horſes, and did lay all my Arms, and ſundry other things, waiting ſtill for my guard, till towards night, but none came; ſo when it was dark night, one brought me word, that <hi>Bryan mac Gwire</hi> was at my Mill, with a great many men: Whereupon, I ſent <hi>Zachery Rampion,</hi> and <hi>Humphrey Holland,</hi> to know his intention; his anſwer, he was not acquainted with the intention of the Natives, But upon a word my Wife ſent him, he had gotten theſe men together, and had come for my good, and ſent them back, deſiring me to meet him, and another with him, at my utter Gate: I took my Wife with me, becauſe I durſt not truſt any other interpreter betwixt us, Commanding the reſt of the people to keep within; but before I come to the utter Gate, I looked back, and ſaw men and women fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after me; whereupon, I put them back again: In the mean time, my Wife was with Maſter <hi>Bryan</hi> at the Gate. When I met him, and asked him the reaſon of his coming, his anſwer was, He had received word from my Wife, to come for my good, and to preſerve me, and my Houſe, and Goods; ſhewing me, that three Counties, <hi>Tiron, Manna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghan,</hi> and <hi>Cavan,</hi> were gathering together to come in theſe parts, and ſeeing that I had no men to defend my houſe, if it pleaſed me, he would put ſome men of his in it, till they were gone, with a ſolemn Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That he would redeliver it, and all my Goods, ſafe unto me back again; and in the mean time, preſerve me from the Tyranny of the enemy, that meant no good to me; and as ſoon as any Army came from the King, or that I could get any competent number of men, to defend, or guard me, and my houſe, that he would ſafely ſurrender it up with all my Goods; and finding his love unto me, and of my ſelf not able to ſecure it, by reaſon that my people left me, and likewiſe, that I had no Ammunition, was contented to give him leave to put ſome of his men
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:158501:18"/>into the Houſe, to be a guard to preſerve me from <hi>Rory,</hi> and the reſt of his Forces, being perſwaded that he would not attempt the Houſe, it being in Maſter <hi>Bryans</hi> cuſtody; he likewiſe, gave me leave to make choice of the Natives, which were my own Tenants, for my guard; he came once a week to ſee me, that no man wronged me: And as ſoon as I perceived ſome of them that was my guard, to grow a little ſawcy, he put them out, and put others in. About three weeks after, he and <hi>James Duffe mac Gra,</hi> came to my houſe, whom I found deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to have a protection, I told them, I would go to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> to ſpeak to Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> concerning that, who were thankfull to me for the motion; they ſent ſix Horſemen with me to Sir <hi>William,</hi> and told him their deſire; and deſired him to write to Sir <hi>William Stuart,</hi> for <hi>Bryan</hi> and his Son, and Maſter <hi>Magra</hi> and his Son, which Sir <hi>William</hi> did, and ſent the Letter with me to them, to be ſent to Sir <hi>William Stuart,</hi> Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had not then received his Commiſſion: And likewiſe, at the ſame time, Maſter <hi>Bryan</hi> willed me to get ſome men to guard my Houſe, for he would not willingly leave it; for theſe men he left to keep it: He was forced to pay them then fourteen pounds for their wages, or otherwiſe, he deſired me to get a note under Sir <hi>Williams</hi> hand, not to beſiege the Caſtle, or elſe none of his people would ſtay in it for him, to preſerve me, for fear of Sir <hi>William Cole:</hi> Which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to give me under his hand, but paſt his word to my ſelf, ſo long as I was in the Houſe he would not attempt it; then I deſired him, to ſend ſome of his men along with me, and <hi>Bryan</hi> would render it up to him; which he refuſed to do, becauſe he could ſpare none: So at my return again, they were pleaſed with Sir <hi>Williams</hi> Letter to Sir <hi>William Stuart,</hi> likewiſe with Sir <hi>Williams</hi> promiſe, That he would not invade my Houſe, <hi>Bryans</hi> guard were the more willing to ſtay with me: I ſtayed one moneth after that in my own Houſe; and finding the guard to grow a little more inſolent, I ſent for Maſter <hi>Bryan,</hi> and did ſhew him his mens carriage, and deſired him to furniſh me with ſome Horſes, to carry ſomethings to <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> which he willingly granted, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me a day, when I ſhould go, and deſired me, to procure Sir <hi>Williams</hi> Licenſe for my Convoys ſafe return, which was granted by Sir <hi>William;</hi> and likewiſe Sir <hi>William</hi> wrote unto me, That he had no room in his Caſtle, but for ſome little things, being bepeſtered, and there was no ſafety in the Town for any thing; which made me leave moſt of my things behinde me: And when I left my Houſe, <hi>Bryan</hi> deſired me to procure a guard from Sir <hi>William,</hi> and he would preſerve my Houſe, and all my Goods ſafe, for ten or twelve dayes, and deliver it up upon my Letter. I told Sir <hi>William,</hi> that my Houſe would be delivered, if
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158501:18"/>he would be pleaſed to ſend a guard to receive it, his anſwer was ſtill alike, That he could ſpare none: The next morning after my coming to <hi>Iniskillin, Rory</hi> came to my Houſe, and fell very foul with <hi>Bryan,</hi> for giving me way to go for <hi>Iniskillin;</hi> for at this ſame time, <hi>Rory</hi> was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of more men, and the word was to fire my Houſe, which moved Maſter <hi>Bryan</hi> to put more men in it, to preſerve it. Upon the Friday ſeven-night thereafter, Sir <hi>William</hi> ſent his men out to attempt the Caſtle, and burnt all my Office Houſes: And the ſame night, thoſe that was in the Houſe, ſet it on fire, leaving the Houſe within the Bawn, and the two Flanckers unburned, and themſelves went away: And the next day, Sir <hi>William</hi> ſent to fetch ſuch things, as were found there; and upon relation of thoſe that was ſent, that the Houſe and Flanckers ſtood unfired; he ſent the next week, and cauſed to fire the ſame, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Mills. So Sir, this is the true manner, with the whole paſſages of my leaving of my Houſe; and to affirm all this to be true, one <hi>Bryan mac Gwires</hi> part of his love, for my ſafety, he hath acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged it ſince, before Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> my Couſin, Captain <hi>William Atcheſon, Ambroſe Carleton, Torlaugh mac Gra,</hi> and <hi>Owen mac Gra,</hi> that he had no other deſigne, but for the preſervation of me, my Wife, and Goods, in regard he knew that <hi>Rory</hi> aimed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for me, and did acknowledge, that he would have cauſed me to give up the Houſe without aſſaulting, if it had been demanded: and thoſe that were in it, did ſet it on fire, after they were aſſaulted by Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> people, before he knew of it; ſince which, he did never look upon his Nephew, whom he left in charge with the Houſe, for burning of it: And moreover, That ſame day that I left my Houſe with <hi>Bryan,</hi> he gave the Warders fourteen pound more, and ſent a guard with thoſe ſmall Goods that I brought with me; and came himſelf to ſee me ſafely at the Waters-ſide. This with remembrance of my ſervice, and my wifes, to your ſelf, and to my Lady, beſeeching God to grant you victory over your enemies, ſtill I reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours ever to Command, <hi>Roger Atkinſon.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> 
                        <date>the 10. of <hi>October,</hi> 1642.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I did hear Maſter <hi>Bryan</hi> acknowledge, before theſe forenamed perſons, that his onely aym was, in keeping of my Couſins Houſe, to preſerve it for his uſe, from all others that intended no goodneſſe to him; and would have ſure rendered it at my Couſins pleaſure.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Will. Atcheſon.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:158501:19"/>
            <p> The Originall of this Letter, the Repliant can produce, whereby doth appear, what an unthankfull, and unnaturall Neighbour, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent proved to this diſtreſſed old Gentleman, and his vertuous Wife, who ſuffered much miſery by the Reſpondents cruell neglect of them, and had ſuffered much more, had not the Repliant made means divers times to relieve them, as they lay miſerable at the Reſpondents Garriſon, untill they were by the Reſpondent diſgracefully ſent away, amongſt ſeverall hundreds of poor Robbed people; who were ſent to the <hi>Derry,</hi> without getting any ſhare of the 1200. Suites of old apparell, and five hundred pound in Money and Victualls, ſent in charitie, by the Parliament; for the comfort and relief of the poor Proteſtants of that County.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To the Reſpondents Anſwer, to this Repliants ſecond Charge, this Repliant ſaith; Foraſmuch, as upon the matter, the Reſpondent denyeth not, what therein is alledged againſt him: This Repliant might acquieſſe therein, without more ado, and ſubmit that unto judgement: But foraſmuch, as the ſame is alſo ſtuft with calumnies, and aſpertions, caſt upon this Repliant, by way of Recrimination, this Repliant craveth leave to Vindicate himſelf therein, and ſaith, For his part, he hath been ſo far from the envying the Reſpondent in his Commands, or any other, the Brittiſh Colonels in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> as that if it were pertinent to the queſtion, he is well able to make it appear, That he hath contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted much to their aſſiſtance, and the Cauſe in hand; ſo far, as the force he had was able, and was not wanting unto the Reſpondent, in all good Offices, That to his power might advance the War againſt the Rebels, or further his proceedings in any particular; yet this Repliant muſt confeſſe, That he underſtanding the Reſpondents Forces, to be very conſiderable, as is confeſſed in his Anſwer, and able to have done great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſervice at the beginning againſt the Rebels, if he had been active; but many times, the Ronſpondent lay ſtill about his own Town and Caſtle, while as his Officers and Souldiers were moſt deſirous to have been in action; and did many times ſolicite the Reſpondent, to relieve the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant, whileſt he was in great danger with multitudes of Rebels to be deſtroyed, being ſeverall times blockt up in his Caſtle: But to this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the Reſpondent was found both ſlow, and backward; which much troubled this Repliant, That ſuch a man profeſſing ſo much Neighbourly love, and being ſo well provided for the Service, ſhould thus delay and forbear, relieving ſo many Brittiſh ſouls, in ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger, as then they were in; which was a Juſt cauſe to raiſe a Jealouſie in this Repliant, That either the Reſpondent did it out of a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:158501:19"/>careleſſe diſreſpect to this Repliant, and his Charge, or to the Cauſe it ſelf, or for ſome other private ends; which did miniſter an occaſion, for this Repliant to be more watchfull over himſelf, and that poor handfull of men, which he commanded; ſetting before his eyes, no other ends, but the King and Parliaments Service, and the rooting out of thoſe bloody Rebels, who would have deſtroyed us all.</p>
            <p>This Repliant cannot but admire the Reſpondents weakneſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in his Anſwer, That he ſhould think to perſwade any rationall man, that in caſe the Reſpondent ſhould juſtly ſuffer for his miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages in the matters charged againſt him; and ſhould be therefore ſet by all imployment in that Army, that it could not in the leaſt, adde any thing to this Repliant in his preferment; and ſince the Reſpondent adminiſtereth the occaſion, this Repliant craveth leave, to let him know, That he was ſo far from envying the Reſpondents Honour, and greatneſſe, in the Commiſſions he received from His Majeſtie, for that imployment, that it was neither in thoughts or expectation, to believe, that His Majeſtie would joyn him in the ſame Commands with the Reſpondent, and the reſt of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> Colonels, the Repliant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time (as was thought) in ſome disfavour with His Majeſtie, for proſecuting the late Earl of <hi>Strafford.</hi> And this Repliant further ſaith, That as the Reſpondent never did any ſuch actions, to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this Repliant, that deſerved to be envied: So hath this Repliant been as far from extolling any thing, done by himſelf, by Gods aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that yet may better pretend to merit: Surely, he hath learned bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, then from any vain-glorious Honour, to expect the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any thing, but folly; from which, the Reſpondent himſelf is not altogether then free, whiles he indeavoureth by ſuch petty, and vain aſſumptions, to raiſe an opinion of popularitie, and that ſo great honour was conferred upon him, and laid down at his own doors without acquiſition, or other indeavours of his own; and nothing more then what fame hath raiſed him unto before. And this Repliant further ſaith, That ſince of his own ſhowing, it doth appear, that of the nine Companies raiſed, Armed, and Banded by him, as he alledgeth, he onely gained five hundred of them, to be inliſted, and his Troop of Horſe; and if but Victuall and Cloathing for ſo many was alloted him, yet it had been the leaſt, to have rewarded the four Companies (which he caſhiered) with the reſt, for the good ſervice they had done him then formerly, in defending his Caſtle and Town: And their diſcontent, which he confeſſeth, and the disbanding themſelves, doth cleerly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his courſe uſage of them, and that the truth is as hath been charged againſt him; for it is not to be credited, That if they might have ſhared,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:158501:20"/>and pertaken of thoſe Proviſions, that they would have parted in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, or disbanded themſelves, and leave their kindly poſſeſſions and intereſt, in that Countrey, where many of them had been bred and born: Nor is it likely, that needy and neceſſitous men, would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his offer, to have pertaken of thoſe Supplies ſent them, if they might have had a proportion thereof for their relief: And ſurely, it had been but equall, that the Reſpondent had ſhared and divided, the twelve hundred Suites of old Cloaths, ſent from this Citie of <hi>London,</hi> by his ſaid Son in law, with theſe four caſhiered Companies: Albeit, he would not let them have any part of the new, he keeping and diſpoſing of which, and of five hundred pound worth more of Contribution Money, ſent for the relief of the diſtreſſed Proteſtants in thoſe parts, as pleaſed himſelf, and his ſaid Son in law, Maſter <hi>Dean Barkley;</hi> they have not delt ſo candidly and conſcionably in this, as men of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſhould, and ought to have done: But if it be true, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reported there, That Maſter <hi>Dean Barkley</hi> ſold ſuch Corn, and other Proviſions, as was bought with that Money, for relief of the diſtreſſed Proteſtant Brittiſh, in thoſe parts, and ſent from hence, and therewith hath made himſelf a ſtock, where withall, he now drives a great Trade, by Tanning of Leather, at the Reſpondents Town of <hi>Inis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killin,</hi> and cannot be done without the Reſpondents privity and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: This Repliant ſubmiteth it to judgement, if it be well done, thus to rob the Spittle; and what bleſſing can attend ſuch proceedings: And for the thirteen hundred pound worth of Corn, and Proviſions, which he alledgeth to have procured, upon his own credit, for the more ſupply of himſelf, and his Souldiers: This Repliant is certainly informed, That he hath put it to the Parliaments accompt, which thoſe his credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have taken for ſatisfaction, and are, and muſt be contented with ſuch payment, when it may be well ſpared.</p>
            <p n="3">III. To the Reſpondents Anſwer to the third Charge, this Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſaith, That it conſiſteth onely of invectives, fabulous inventions, and ſcandalous calumnies, made, and contrived, by the Reſpondent of purpoſe, to aſperſe this Repliant, without ground or colour; which appears, in that there is nothing therein materiall that concerns himſelf, but ſuppoſitions of things done to others, meerly framed and hatched out of the inventions of his own vindictive brain; and yet of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence and concernment to this Repliant, That if the Reſpondent ſhall not make good his allegations, which he ſhall be never able to do, this Repliant prayeth, that repair from him, as ſhall be fit, and craveth leave, to let the Reſpondent know, That he underſtandeth better, what
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:158501:20"/>the danger is by Law, for any man to conſpire the taking away of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans life, where with he accuſeth this Repliant, then to attempt it, and what ſuch a falſe malicious accuſation intendeth, and deſerveth, this Repliant is aſſured, is underſtood by thoſe that are their Judges; and it ſeemeth ſtrange to this Repliant, That the Reſpondent ſhould thus impudently overſhoot himſelf, and his reaſon, as that he ſhould imagin his vain and idle words, could poſſeſſe any man with a belief, That the malice of an adverſary could ſo charge the frame of the Law, as by that means he could inherit and poſſeſſe his Eſtate. Say it were in a peaceable time, and how unlikely it is, That ſuch a cruell and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous diſpoſition, ſhould poſſeſſe the Repliant, who at that time had his thoughts taken up with other kinde of cares, then by ſuch means, to purchaſe his Neighbours Lands, while as he daily looked to be devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by multitudes of bloody Rebels; and how black thoſe drops are, which hath faln from his Lips, by which he hath charged this Repliant, That he can indure no Neighbourhood, is plain to all that hears it, and that underſtands the carriage, and converſation of this Repliant, for many yeers paſt, beſides the incredibilitie thereof, that this Repliant ſhould be ſo irregular, as not to ſubmit unto Order and Government; to which, he muſt have been compelled: And denieth, that there was ever any ſuch conteſtation, betwixt the ſaid <hi>Dunbar,</hi> or the <hi>Hethering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,</hi> and this Repliant, as is moſt falſely pretended by the Reſpondent. But it appears, the ſaid <hi>Dunbar</hi> was his creature, whom he ſo truſted with the keeping of a Caſtle at the beginning of this Rebellion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is credibly reported, the ſaid <hi>Dunbar</hi> ſo baſely behaved himſelf, as he made his own conditions with the Rebels, for himſelf and his Wife, ſacrificing above fourſcore of Brittiſh ſouls to the Rebels cruelty, who were all burned to death in an inſtant: As to the <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> having done that ſpoil upon this Repliants Tenants, and their ſaid Eſtates and Goods as aforeſaid; and the ſaid <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> having lived amongſt the Rebels with the ſaid <hi>Dunbar,</hi> for a long time, it muſt needs be, that they were Papiſts, as is well known, or otherwiſe, they ſhould not have been ſuffered to have lived amongſt them, as they did; and for ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices as they did for the Reſpondent, for which he gives them ſo great commendations; it is onely known unto himſelf, and not believed or underſtood of any other that knew them formerly; nor doth it (under favour) any wayes excuſe the Reſpondent of his miſcarriages of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, and making uſe of them, being Papiſts and Rebels, for they were no better; and in refuſing to bring them unto a Legall tryall, when required for ſuch offences, which was Treaſon by the Law of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, let the Religion be what it will: And whereof they were ſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:158501:21"/>accuſed by His Majeſties good Subjects; and the Reſpondent being a miniſter of Juſtice, that upon ſuch complaint, ought to have ſecured their perſons, untill tryall of the matters objected; and if it be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient excuſe to free him from the accuſation, becauſe as he ſaith, no proof of the crime laid againſt them, appeared, proved, unto him, who (by his leave) was not a competent Judge of himſelf, to determine the facts and offences, charged againſt them: And this Repliant cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to tell him further, That beſides it was unneighbourly, thus to ſet them free, after this intimation againſt them, made from this Repliant: So it argueth, how little he underſtood himſelf, and the Office of a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that will voluntarily ſuffer a Priſoner to go at large, though but verbally at firſt accuſed, before he had examined the matter, and that they were legally acquited; and from all that he hath ſaid in his defence, from the guilt of this third Charge, informed againſt him, appeareth to be nothing, but meer matter of Recrimination, and without weight, that ſo he is ſtill unexcuſable of the crime objected.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. As to the Reſpondents Anſwer to the fourth Charge, given in againſt him by this Repliant: This Repliant ſaith, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent in the preceding parts of his Anſwer, having made ſhipwrack of a good conſcience, and not ſpared the telling of many untruths, to ſerve his own turn; caſting much dirt in the Repliants face, thereby hoping, that ſome will ſtick, and ſo to imploy this Repliant in waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf; that in the mean time, the Reſpondents foul offences may be forgotten, or he eſcape the hands of Juſtice for the ſame, have therefore left nothing unattempted, which may any wiſe, ſcandalize this Repliant, and bring him into diſrepute, and diſeſteem, with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or ſuch as knows him not, hoping thereby to work out his own ends the better; but that his malice and impudence may the more cleerly appear in his defence to this Charge, as in all the reſt of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers. This Repliant further ſaith, That howſoever the Reſpondent from the relation of others, as he conceiveth, is pleaſed to magnifie the ſaid <hi>Parck,</hi> both for his eſtate, and qualities, yet thoſe that were his Neighbours for many yeers before this Rebellion broke out, (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have more reaſon to know, and underſtand him better, then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent) are able to ſay and prove otherwiſe: And that the Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent onely makes thoſe many flouriſhes, concerning his reputation, as an inſinuation to win credit, that he was an honeſt man, and ſo to weaken the belief of that which is objected againſt him, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent, concerning him; and yet it hath been found true by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, That ſince this Rebellion began, many men, who in the time of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:158501:21"/>Peace, lived orderly, and in good repute, and were imployed in Offices and affairs, of great concernment, concerning that Kingdom; yet ſome ſuch men out of covetous deſires, to ſave their Eſtates, and for other by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends of their own, have baſely betrayed their Religion, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and joyned with the Rebels againſt the Parliament, and their Forces there, of which ſort, this Repliant doubteth not, but he ſhall make Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> appear to be one; and that if this Repliant had not upon intimation of his purpoſes and reſolutions, taken and ſettled to go this way, as to ſecure his perſon and Caſtle, he had been out in action amongſt the thickeſt of them, and ſo would have done much hurt unto the Proteſtant party there; and without peradventure they are Birds of the ſame Feather, from whom, the Reſpondent hath had his Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to the contrary, if they be not meerly fictious, and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his own; which the Repliant the rather beleeveth, for beſides the certain Information which the Repliant had of <hi>Parcks</hi> reſolutions to joyn with the Rebels, and of his daily compliance with, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe between them, he being then ordered by the State to obſerve this Repliants Commands, and to joyn with him in all things againſt them; the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> not withſtanding, had contemned ſeverall times to obey this Repliants Directions and Orders, and altogether declined what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſervice he thought, might provoke or prejudice the Rebels; and yet this Repliant was ſo far from deſiring the ſaid <hi>Parcks</hi> Eſtate, (which the Reſpondent hath moſt falſly, and ſcandalouſly alleaged) as that onely for the King and Parliaments Service, put in an Officer of his own, to command that Caſtle of Importance, being far from that baſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of coveting other mens Lands, having ſo much (by Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his own) as he had ſmall hopes at that time to our live the danger he was in, much leſſe to injoy other mens Lands. But as it ſeemeth, the Reſpondent judgeth other men by his own known covetous humour, witneſſe his barbarous uſage of his worthy Neighbour, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Roger Atkinſon,</hi> whoſe houſe and Land lay within a mile to the Reſpondent, which now he holds as his own, having in a manner baniſhed the old Gentleman, and his Wife, whom he grudged a little charitable relief in his houſe, they having many times bountifully and freely ſupplied, and entertained the Reſpondent, with his Wife, and children, while as the Reſpondent was held a much inferiour man in qualitic and condition to Captain <hi>Atkinſon,</hi> whom the Reſpondent ſent away amongſt a Company of poor diſtreſſed Beggers, with his Convoy to <hi>London-Derry,</hi> where the Gentleman, and his diſtreſſed Wife, might have ſtarved, if upon the Repliants credit, they had not been there relieved with five pounds to convoy them to <hi>Dublin,</hi> where
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:158501:22"/>they hoped to have met with me Lord <hi>Lyle,</hi> who was a neer Kinſman to this Gentlewoman; and miſſing of him there, this Repliant is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, That thoſe two vertuous ſouls live ſtill in great miſery at <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> by reaſon of the cruell, barbarous, and unneighbourly uſage of the Reſpondent, who might at firſt, conveniently have inabled them to have made good their own houſe, or otherwiſe to have helped them off with a great deal of their beſt Goods, and Houſhold-ſtuff, which the Reſpondent for other baſe ends of his own, expoſed all to ruin, much invying in time of Peace, the worthy and good eſteem, which both the State and Neighbours in the Countrey had of Captain <hi>Atkinſon,</hi> and his vertuous Bedfellow, for the free and charitable way of living, to the comfort of all ſorts of good people, both of great, and mean condition, who uſed to travell in that Countrey.</p>
            <p>As concerning the two <hi>Witherspins,</hi> both father and ſon, that they were Scotchmen; it is confeſſed, But ſo much the more unworthy to be of that Nation, as they proved Traitours and Rebels againſt the King and Parliament; concerning whoſe carriage, it was in manner follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That theſe men whom the Reſpondent pleaſeth himſelf to give ſo much commendation, as if naming ſuch two Scotchmen, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the Nation to adhere to his poor Recriminating way of vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Witherspin,</hi> the Son being married to a meer Iriſh woman, and known to be of a moſt wicked baſe diſpoſition from his childhood, and one who had been accuſed of Fellony, and found guilty before the Rebellion; and upon the firſt breaking out thereof, ſoon after himſelf and his Wife, joyned themſelves with the Rebels, leaving his Father and Mother (two old people) in the Repliants Garriſon, which the Repliant had juſt reaſon to ſuſpect, as Spies, many times adviſing them to keep by themſelves, ſince their Son and Daughter had joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Rebels. And about the moneth of February, before the ſuppoſed firſt of July, mentioned in the Reſpondents Anſwer, alledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that old <hi>Witherspin</hi> to be taken in <hi>Sligoe,</hi> and ſhot to death by this Repliants own hand; in which moneth of February, the ſaid <hi>James Witherspin</hi> the ſon, was then (in actuall ſervice and rebellion, againſt the King and Parliament) a Muskettier with the Rebels, under the Command of <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk,</hi> who then lay incampt, with a many others, about this Repliants Caſtle, and Garriſon; whereof this Reſpondent well knew, and had ſtrength enough to have relieved this Repliant, and was many times importuned by Captain <hi>Cathcart,</hi> and others of his Officers, to have endeavoured the Repliants relief; but the Reſpondent with frivolous excuſes, being deſirous (as ſince, and now
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:158501:22"/>it doth appear) to have the Repliant rather to be cut off, did ſuffer him with his handfull of men, to take their hazards, envying the Repliants activeneſſe with ſo poor a handfull, as may appear by his vindictive humour, againſt this Repliant, whom God Almighty proſpered ſo well, as with his own handfull, one morning the rogues were ſurprized in their Camp, their ſiege raiſed, and a many of the Rebels killed; the foreſaid old <hi>John Wither spin,</hi> taken priſoner amongſt the Rebels, who the night before had ſtoln out of the Repliants Garriſon, to meet with his ſon <hi>James Witherſpin;</hi> where that night, he confeſſed to be much made off by the Colonell <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk,</hi> to whom he delivered twelve pounds ſterlin, in ready money, which he intended for his ſon <hi>James Witherspin:</hi> So that for this Treaſon, upon his own confeſſion, the Father was undoubtedly hanged in February, which the Repliant is ready to prove with ſufficient witneſſes, now in Town: How the Reſpondent ſhall prove, that in July after, the Repliant ſhould meet with a man ſo many moneths dead before, and ten miles diſtant from the place of his buriall; let him prove his being there, and the Repliant hopes to be excuſed for ſhooting ſuch a one with his own hand. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſires no further vindication of his own honour, from this ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, baſe, Libelling way of recrimination of the Reſpondents, then what credit this hiſtory brings him, amongſt all indifferent, and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall readers. And as for the ſaid <hi>James Witherspin</hi> the ſon, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that the firſt of July, being the night, the Repliant with his ſmall handfull, attempted the burning of that Town of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> which then ſheltered a many bloody Rebels, who had murthered and maſſacred many poor Brittiſh in it, which ſtuck much in the Repliants ſtomack, whom God made his weak Inſtrument, to revenge that night that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood; where amongſt the reſt of the Rebels, the foreſaid <hi>James Witherspin</hi> was taken priſoner, and brought home to the Repliants Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; where upon his own confeſſion, That he had ſerved as a Musket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier amongſt the Rebels, and had done his beſt at ſeverall times, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ruin and deſtruction of the Repliants Garriſon; upon which confeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Wither spin,</hi> he was juſtly hanged as this Repliant concerveth, and for no ſuch cauſe, as is falſly and ſcandalouſly alledged by the Reſpondent; and how apt this Reſpondent is to take up any thing upon truſt, and credit of others, that may vent his ſpleen againſt this Repliant, doth eaſily appear, though it be nothing materiall to this purpoſe, for the vindicating of himſelf, but rather of the Rebels, and their treacherous adherents.</p>
            <p>And this Repliant further ſaith, That the Reſpondent faileth migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily in his Anſwers, wherein he attributes it to the information of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:158501:23"/>
               <hi>Witherspin,</hi> and the aſſiſtance of <hi>Parck</hi> and his men, That in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants return from burning of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> he eſcaped the ſurprize of the Rebels, who was lying in waite for him, with a great Body of men in his way homeward, which was eaſily perceived by our Scouts, that went before us, to which we gave better credit, then to <hi>Witherspins</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: And for <hi>Parck,</hi> it is true, This Repliant carried him along with him as a Priſoner, and not to guard his perſon; neither is it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unlikely, but the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> had a hand in that meeting of the Rebels that day, which was thought ſhould have been the day, the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> ſhould have put himſelf and his Caſtle, in the hands of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, had not God put it in the heart and head of this Repliant, to do as he did the night before, in ſeizing upon the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> and his Caſtle, and burning of the ſaid Town of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> which were the firſt actions that ever gave comfort or probable ſecurity, to the Repliant, and his handfull. As for the Reſpondents other expreſſions, and ſcurvy ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous aſpertions in his Anſwer to this fourth Article, more proper to come from the mouths of Carmen and Oyſter-wives, then from the head and hand of ſo couragious a Colonell, as the Reſpondent would ſeem to be at his yeers, being paſt date before his preferment came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; and had not this Repliant received a Copy of the Reſpondents Anſwer, under his own hand, he ſhould not have believed there had been a man in the world, having any drop of a Gentlemans blood in him, that could have invented ſo many groſſe ſlovenly falſhoods, much leſſe to have preſumed to publiſh ſuch untruths to ſuch an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee, and Aſſembly, whom the Repliant holds more wronged, then he dare preſume to expreſſe; for in many of his Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, his malice rageth without limit or moderation: And it behoves him (we ſay) that tells untruths, to have a good memory. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent ſeems very week this way, That either through the infirmity of doting age, or through ſome other weakneſſe, forgets ſo much, as that he ſaith, and unſaith the ſame thing again, firſt he would have it believed that this Repliant plundered Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> and then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confeſſeth, That both his Caſtle and Goods were (by Order of the Councell Board in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſits as chief, executed by the Reſpondents Commands, and his Souldiers in the time of the Ceſſation made with the Rebels, and in this Repliants abſence from home) reſtored to him again; and howſoever, he would mince the matter, and ſet a fair gloſſe herein upon his proceedings; he doth not deny his guiltineſſe of the crime objected, and ſo to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plier with the Rebels, as to that Ceſſation, and by obeying their Orders, who holds it with them: And as this Repliants compelling the ſaid
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:158501:23"/>
               <hi>Parcks</hi> Souldiers to obey his commands; why ſhould the Reſpondent think it an offence, when both <hi>Parck</hi> himſelf, and they (before the Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) were injoyned to it by the Councell Table in <hi>Ireland.</hi> And this Repliant further ſaith, That the Reſpondent is pleaſed to leſſen and extenuate the Repliants ſervices, which for want of his aſſiſtance, this Repliant was not able to do, what he might have done, and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he did with that handfull of men he had; he can approve, that he did more by much, then the Reſpondent who had ten times the Repliants number, under his command, by the Reſpondents own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. And this Repliant humbly prayeth, it may be underſtood, That the Reſpondent indeavoureth to blemiſh this Repliant in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Parliament; for that he refuſed to ſet <hi>Parck</hi> at liberty, by command of the Orders of the Councell Board in <hi>Ireland,</hi> having then concluded a Ceſſation of Arms with the Rebels; and being therefore declared enemies to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> by which tacitly, and by conſequence, he himſelf approveth thereof; and by executing their Orders and Commands, in this perticular, declareth himſelf obedient to their directions; which he cannot ſhift from his ſhoulders by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying two faces in one hood, and pleaſing himſelf as free, by (holding a deteſtable neutrality at the beſt) that he can ſay for himſelf; And as for that information of the Reſpondents, in his Anſwer concerning <hi>Abber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croomy,</hi> this Repliant ſaith, That therein he alſo follows the ſame tract, as concerning Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> indeavouring firſt to raiſe him high in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion for his Abilities in time of Peace, which to be true, as it is not ſo, as the Reſpondent ſetteth forth, yet if <hi>Abbercroomy,</hi> or any man ſnall in ſuch time, be never ſo juſt, and ſerviceable to the ſtate wherein he liveth, if in ſuch a time of Rebellion as this, he ſhall fall away from his dut<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and the obedience he oweth to God and his Countrey, as a ſubject, and ſhall joyn with, aid, or adhere to Idolatrous Rebels, againſt his King and Parliament, either unworthily to ſave his eſtate, or upon any pretext whatſoever, he hath thus (under favour) forfeited the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of whatſoever was good and commendable in him before, and is to be looked upon in the preſent condition wherein he ſo remains. Then the ſaid <hi>Abbercroemy</hi> refuſed to joyn with this Repliant againſt theſe Rebels, forſook his own houſe, and willingly joyned himſelf with the Rebels, and was afterwards taken by this Repliant amongſt them; and what the ſaid <hi>Abbercroomy</hi> deſerved in this caſe, this Repliant ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteth to judgement; yet did not the Repliant uſe him after that faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Reſpondent is pleaſed to inform, but gave him better enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, then he was worthy off that had ſo behaved himſelf, and commanded, that he ſhould not want any thing that was ſufficient for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:158501:24"/>him, being himſelf ſtraitned, and in a hard condition in an enemies Countrey, and without hope of other help, then what he could get from the Rebels by his Sword, having no expectation to be relieved, but by the Reſpondent; Whoſe affection towards him, and care to preſerve him, and his family, from deſtruction (in ſo great danger and extremity) is wel underſtood by this Reſpondents relations, in his anſwers ſet forth, this Repliant is confident, is but a meer ſuggeſtion of the Reſpondent; for if the ſaid <hi>Abbercroomy</hi> had any cauſe of complaint, againſt the Repliant in the leaſt, he was in <hi>Scotland</hi> a long time together with this Repliant, where he ſhould have been ſure to have had juſtice done him; and if he were ſo ingrate towards this Repliant, as to inform any ſuch thing to the Reſpondent, it had been greater wiſdom in him, by much (under favour) not to have believed the report of a diſcontented man in his own cauſe, but to have buried it in ſilence rather, being altogether without proof, and not thus to have ſhewn his weakneſſe in the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, which he can never be able to make good; and if to have been ſo (as it is not) are without conſideration at all: the Reſpondent might with more diſcretion alſo, have ſpared to proclaim his charity towards him, which makes the verity thereof more ſuſpected; but having ſeldom done ſo before, if ſo he did, he could not forbear to tell it as a thing unuſuall, and rare in him, to have been performed to neerer Neighbours. And this Repliant further ſaith, That he doth not beleeve the Reſpondent did, or was able to receive Cloath, and feed all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of that Countrey where he lived; and doubteth not to prove, that he ſent hundreds away alſo from himſelf, whom he was no wayes able to harbour and maintain, and that ſome of them alſo by accident, periſhed in their journey; and yet this Repliant will be more charitable towards him, then for to believe he did it of any other intent, then that he might the better preſerve himſelf, and thoſe under his Command; for charitie hath never before this time, been blamed to begin at home; and yet the Reſpondent had in this caſe, means, and hopes of ſuccours, and ſupplies, which this Repliant neither had, nor could hope for, or expect, if not by the Reſpondents means, whom this Repliant had by his experience found to be otherwiſe minded towards him, as is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſufficiently diſcovered, which ſhall be all this Repliants anſwer to that particular: more then that he utterly denieth, That ever he did ſend any poor Proteſtant away ſuccourleſſe, that fled to him for relief, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſupplies, and with ſuch convoy and protection in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, as he could ſafely ſpare, and leave wherewith to maintain his Garriſon; nor was there any ſuch differences between the ſaid Sir <hi>John Dunbar,</hi> and his Son, as is alledged by the Reſpondent, meerly to make
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:158501:24"/>out the matter, and to raiſe the untruth unto a higher pitch, nor can this great clamour be poſſibly believed, That whiles there was Peace in that Kingdom, and the Law was open for every mans complaint of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done him, that any man would ſuffer wrong by this Repliant, and not right himſelf, being well known what favour the Repliant might expect from the late Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and the then Viſcount <hi>Rannellagh,</hi> which two commanded both the Kingdom and Province, where this Repliant lived.</p>
            <p n="5">V. To the Reſpondents Anſwer to the fifth Charge, this Repliant ſaith, That foraſmuch as this Reſpondent hath fully confeſſed the ſame, there needeth no reply to be made unto it (under favour and correction) yet in aſmuch as the Reſpondent indeavoureth to extenuate the ſame offence, by his ignorance, and want of knowledge, of the affairs of that State, and how things then moved at <hi>Dublin,</hi> or in the Parliament here, at that time: This Repliant ſaith, That before the Ceſſation concluded at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and whiles it was in agitation, and in Order to the ſame, the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Councell there, made the ſame known unto all the Colonels and Commanders in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> as this Repliant hath heard; and ſo doubteth not to prove; and that the Reſpondent had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation thereof, amongſt the reſt, and his approbation therein was deſired; and likewiſe after the ſame was ſo unhappily concluded, the ſaid Lord Marqueſſe, and Councell, immediatly afterwards intimated the ſame again unto them all, and to the Reſpondent amongſt the reſt, Commanding their obedience, and obſervation thereof, which was in time made, and done, the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of <hi>September,</hi> 1643. above foure moneths before the Reſpondent, by his own ſhowing, received the ſaid Rebels into protection; and it is without all peradventure, and ſo this Repliant doubteth not to prove, that even thoſe Rebels themſelves moved it unto the Reſpondent, as a great perſwaſive to obtain that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour at his hands; and from whom alſo, he had perfect notice of the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> his being then made Lord Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that he was declared an enemy to the Parliament, and the welfare of that Kingdom; the Reſpondent alſo, before this time, was certainl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> informed by thoſe Letters, ſent from the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> by Captain <hi>O Connelly,</hi> and otherwiſe, how that they had declared themſelves againſt the ſaid Ceſſation, and moving the Brittiſh Regiments to receive the ſolemn League and Covenant of the Kingdoms; nor was the Reſpondent ſo ſtraitned in his Quarters, but that he had continuall Intelligences from <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and other parts of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and could not be ignorant of the paſſages of the State, and how things<pb n="42" facs="tcp:158501:25"/>moved at that time there, and in the Parliament here, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>execuſable; and it is ſo far from leſſening, as it doth rather aggravate his offence, that he would receive thoſe Rebels into protection without Order, and without being firſt informed of all theſe paſſages of State, and things, in caſe he had been then ignorant thereof, as he was not; beſides his fears to be ſupplied by the State there, and his little expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be furniſhed in due time from hence, cleerly informs his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe proceedings, and that he reſted then in doubt, and in a deteſtable neutrality, to which ſide he ſhould adhere; and therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the matter, was reſolved to keep both ſides his friends, if poſſibly he could, and would make uſe of the Rebels alſo, to ſerve his own turn, and that ſo he might ſtand well affected in the opinions of them alſo: But as it was not an Act warrantable, and juſtifieable, under the power of any Commiſſion he had; ſo was it indiſcreetly done, and of great diſſervice unto the Parliament, That this Repliant, and thoſe who were invironed by the enemy, and in a great ſtrait, and in much harder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then the Reſpondent, and yet both underſtanding off, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the ſaid Ceſſation, were much diſcouraged and diſheartned, to ſee thoſe Rebels under the Reſpondents protection, to enter their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and places thereabouts; and to rob and ſpoil them of that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they had hope of ſubſiſtance: For the Cows mentioned in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondents Anſwer to the fifth Article, were not the proper Goods of the Reſpondents protected Rebels, but prey which they had taken from the good ſubjects; and therefore, more fit for to have been poſſeſſed by thie Repliants Souldiers, when they had once gotten them, then by thoſe Rebels; and yet ſuch was the Reſpondents zeal and care for them, that by his own confeſſion, he ſent afterwards unto the State of <hi>Dublin,</hi> then in Ceſſation of Arms with the Rebels, complaining thereof againſt this Repliants Souldiers, and gaining Orders from thence, for reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And in the abſence of this Repliant, procured the ſame to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored even to the Parliaments enemies, and to be taken from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments friends, and ſervants; beſides, his further inclination to that Government, is obſervable, Wherein he charges it as a crime againſt the Repliant, That he ſhould not obſerve the Lord Maqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the Commands of that State, even by a compliance with Rebels, his protected crew, before mentioned; Beſides, that he applauds it as an Act of conformity to thoſe Commands, that now in this Repliants abſence, he hath perſwaded the Repliants Souldiers to a neer conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him therein, and deplores it as a great prejudice to his benefit: That as he ſaith by this Repliant and his Souldiers means, he hath thus loſt this bargain, and yet afterwards confeſſeth a many of them to be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:158501:25"/>ſtill within his quarters, faithfully holding the ſaid agreement. And this Repliant further ſaith, That for his part, he diſclaimeth his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any ſuch perſons, as are named in the Reſpondents anſwer, to be by him, and his Officers protected, much more the protecting of them upon his Land; and if the Reſpondents Acts of like nature, hath now drawn it into example, and made the Repliants Officers in his abſence, to fall into ſuch an errour and miſtake, he hopeth it cannot be imputed unto this Repliant for a tranſgreſſion, yet cannot beleeve, that any ſuch thing hath been done; howſoever, that taketh nothing from the Reſpondents offences, but further ſheweth the extent of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and what hurt he would do unto this Repliant, if he were able.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. To the Reſpondents Anſwer to the ſixth Article, or Charge given in againſt him by this Repliant, he ſaith, That it is poſſible that the ſaid <hi>Bryan mac Coconaught mac Gwire,</hi> in his anſwer named, might do the Reſpondent thoſe ſervices alſo, mentioned in his anſwer, to this Charge: But it is very improbable and unlikely to him, that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands him not, or that any Papiſt ſo allied to the very prime and chief of the Rebels, eſpecially where the Rebellion is pretended to be raiſed, to gain the free exerciſe of their idolatrous Religion, and to regain their Lands formerly forfeited, and diſpoſed of from them to the Brittiſh, by the State, ſhould do theſe ſervices for the State: But to admit it to be ſo in his perſon, and that for thoſe reaſons given, the Reſpondent may be, and was well diſpenſed with, for receiving him into protection; yet to receive all thoſe, together with him, if no more then is confeſſed, is not ſo juſtifiable (under favour) eſpecially, when he that is acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the quality and nature of thoſe Iriſh people, the meaner ſort of them, to wholly addicted unto treacheries, and perfidiouſneſſe: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that the principals of their Religion teacheth them to be ſo, and no longer, to hold, and keep Faith with us, whom they call Heretikes, then it ſerves their own turns: That he which is verſt and read in the Hiſtories, the Iriſh Wars, in former ages, or that hath had his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation there amongſt them, can juſtifie all this for truth; and what a great deal of Proteſtant blood they have their ſhed, by breaches of that truſt which have been repoſed in them, by the Engliſh, from time to time, being naturally mercileſſe, and cruell upon advantages; that it hath never been accounted ſafe in the undertakings of any great deſignes, to have them joyned, either in Counſell or Action, being alſo baſe and cowardly ſpirited, where they are ſubjected, and have not been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to perform any great ſervices; but where by treachery or power,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:158501:26"/>they have in an inſtant gotten firſt the maſtery, and then no Salvages have been ſo bloody and butcherly minded, as they; that albeit, this <hi>Bryan mac Coconaught mac Gwire</hi> may be one black Swan amongſt the reſt; yet upon what ground he received ſuch a crew, of his followers into protection with him, and imployed them, whoſe treacheries and revolt, is by himſelf confeſſed, this Repliant muſt ſay, that as yet he neither ſeeth ground, nor good diſcretion for it; and yet this Repliant craveth leave, to tell the Reſpondent this much, That it was a little prepoſterous, and out of order, firſt to do an unlawfull Act, and then to juſtifie it with an allowance afterwards, which is the very beſt of the Reſpondents caſe in this particular: And albeit, ſome times for money and reward, and to ſave their own lives, they have been known to have betrayed their own parents unto deſtruction; yet it hath been ſeldom ſeen, that they have been drawn to do ſuch ſervice in a Military way, and under a Proteſtant Commander, whileſt they have continued to be Papiſts; nor was the hanging of one man (left for a pledge) a ſufficient recompence for the great hurt, and prejudice, they did unto the cauſe, whiles they remained in ſervice with the Reſpondent; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, being with the enemy, to whom no doubt, they related and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, whatſoever they underſtood, that might be any wayes diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to this ſide, and knoweth now the better how to take the opportunities to put them in execution. And as to that Printed relation of the Repliants ſervices performed, and done againſt thoſe Rebels, which the Reſpondent is pleaſed to term ſcandalous calumnies in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places thereof, which concerns himſelf and Officers, this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant ſaith, and muſt ſo far excuſe himſelf, That it was not a thing done immediately by his direction and appointment, or that he deſired it, but was done in a time, when he was then in his Garriſon at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-Hammilton,</hi> and far remote from this City, the ſame being ſent to a friend of his at <hi>London-Derry,</hi> who afterwards coming hither, and by him that is now the Reſpondents, or Colonell <hi>Meevins</hi> Secretary; <hi>Tarlton</hi> tendering it to the publike view, it was directed to be Printed; of which, the Reſpondent may alſo be pleaſed upon a better review, to obſerve thus much concerning it, That it is not a relation of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants own, but of one of his Clerks, who as it ſhould ſeem, kept a Diary of the paſſages and proceeding done by them in that time, which he was deſirous to communicate, for the publiſhing of Gods great mercy towards that handfull, and the Reſpondents arrogancy, and unneighbourly neglect of them: So that if any thing therein contained, is troubleſome and grievous to the Reſpondent, he hath no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to except againſt this Repliant for the ſame; And yet ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:158501:26"/>hath therefore brought him upon the ſtage, he muſt do his Clerk that wrote it, that right, as to juſtifie, and maintain, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is therein contained to be true; nor was there any ſuch waiting upon this Repliant, by this Reſpondent and his Souldiers required, as is imagined; it was for the King and Parliaments Service, the relief of the Repliant, and his diſtreſſed Garriſon, and deſtruction of the Rebels, that this Repliant ſo often importuned the Reſpondent to joyn with him; nor can this Repliant conceive, what ſhould be the cauſe or reaſon of his backwardneſſe, if not that by ſuch delayes, the Repliant might be deſtroyed and cut off; and it had been well, if at this time, the Reſpondent had alſo forborne the relation of his great Services, ſet forth in his anſwer, becauſe he hath upbraided this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant of vain-glory for the like, nay, for not ſo much, if not for nothing, as may be underſtood, by that which hath been ſaid before, and herein, becauſe he confeſſeth the deſtroying of two hundred ninety and ſix of the Rebels, and the famiſhing, and ſtarving of many hundreds of them more, by Preys of Cows, and other ſpoil, which he took from them ſince the Ceſſation, and by reſcuing and redeeming of five thouſand four hundred ſixty and nine <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> Proteſtants, from the hands of the Enemy; for the latter, it follows, to be done in performance of the Articles of the ſaid Ceſſation, and may be verily beleeved, it being done in time after the ſaid Ceſſation, as may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from the Reſpondents Anſwer; and for which, not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reſpondent doth well merit, for the relieving of ſo many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed ſouls: But how this, and the killing of ſo many Rebels in this time, being Acts ſo oppoſite, and of ſo differing a nature, one unto the other, as to keep, and not to keep, the ſaid Ceſſation, is the thing which ſtrikes moſt with this Repliant to beleeve; howſoever, the Preys of Cows, and ſpoil taken, may well be ſo, for this made for the profit and benefit of the ſaid Reſpondent, and his Companies; and who were far enough from the fear, to anſwer any complaint at <hi>Dublin,</hi> for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And as the Reſpondent being one of the firſt Colonells of the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> in <hi>Ulster,</hi> that took the ſolemn League and Covenant: This inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation is as true as the reſt; for it is well known, That all thoſe of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army had taken it before, and had not the Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant been the beſt means of taking it at the <hi>Derry,</hi> it had been hardly taken by the Reſpondent there for all his brags, which ſuites with his other policie; yet he forbears to mention the place where he took it, or in what COMPANY, not having
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:158501:27"/>taken it in the propereſt place for the Reſpondent, to have given good example to his Officers and Souldiers in his own Garriſon at <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> whether the Reverend Miniſters went to tender the ſaid Covenant; and having Preached to the Reſpondent, with his Officers and Souldiers, the Sermon being ended, and the Miniſters about to explain and tender the Covenant; the Reſpondent in a diſreſpective manner, and to the ill example of his Officers and Souldiers, went immediatly out of the Church, thinking a many would have followed him, which doubtleſſe they had, if their mindes had not been better inclining to that ſolemn League and Covenant, and to the King and Parliaments Service, then their Colonell was known to be; who perceiving himſelf in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, fearing what eſteem he might be in amongſt his Officers and Souldiers, and how his carriage might be informed off to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did (it may be out of thoſe earthly ends) take the Covenant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ventured to apply himſelf to the Parliament. Now what thanks this man deſerves in this paſſage and carriage of his, let any indifferent man be Judge.</p>
            <p>And this Repliant further ſaith, That he is not able to judge of the Reſpondents deſires, which he pretendeth he had ſeverall times, to have relieved this Repliant; But of this he is ſure, he never expreſt the ſame in any reall manner, while as the Repliant and his poor handfull, many times were in great diſtreſſe, and therewith did advertize the Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, who was alwayes ready, rather to weaken the Repliant, by debiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Meſſengers, perſwading them to incourage the Repliants Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to run away, as many of them did, and were afterwards diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted and ſheltered under the Reſpondents ſeverall Companies, as may appear by this Copy of a Petition, directed to the Repliant, by one of his run-away Souldiers, as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>The Humble Petition of <hi>John Brooks,</hi> To his Honourable Col. Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> Knight.</head>
                        <p>ACknowledging, that notwithſtanding your Petitioners ſeverall kinde uſages under your Command, far beyond his merit, yet being ſeduced by the baſe perſwaſions, and intiſements of <hi>John Jeyns, William Vinton,</hi> and divers others of your Souldiers, your Petitioner was at laſt perſwaded, contrary to his Oath, to run from his Colours, towards Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> offering our ſelves to be diſpoſed off by him; who immediately ſent for all his Captains, with whom he adviſed how to diſpoſe of us, who reſolved, we ſhould be divided amongſt their ſeverall Companies; and to that purpoſe, did
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:158501:27"/>immediately caſt lots for us, your Petitioner falling to Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Acheſon, Thomas Vinton</hi> to the Serjeant Major <hi>Graham, John Jeyns</hi> to Captain <hi>Cole, Michael Kent</hi> to Captain <hi>Goodfellow, William Vinton</hi> to Captain <hi>Roff<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi> And this being your Petitioners firſt fault, Humbly prayeth, it may be forgiving, promiſing never to offend any more in the like kinde, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By this may appear, the neighbourly carriage of the Reſpondent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Repliant; as likewiſe by theſe Depoſitions following, taken upon the diſcovery of a Trecherous Plot, contrived at Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> Garriſon in <hi>Iniskillin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="depositions">
                        <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>William Wagh, James Wagh,</hi> And divers others of Sir <hi>Fred. Hammiltons</hi> Souldiers.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THe Deponants being duely ſworn, doth prove, That</hi> William Jeniſon <hi>being lately returned from Sir</hi> William Coles <hi>Garriſon at</hi> Iniskillin, <hi>the ſaid</hi> Jeniſon <hi>told the Deponants, that he was deſired by a prime Officer of Sir</hi> William Coles, <hi>to try if he could prevail with ten or twelve of</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-Hammilton <hi>Souldiers to come overwith him to</hi> Iniskillin, <hi>and there to Petition Sir</hi> William Cole <hi>againſt their hard uſage, and ſtrict Diſcipline at</hi> Mannor-Hammilton: <hi>The ſaid Officer promiſing, That if ſo many of them would come over in this manner, that Sir</hi> William <hi>ſhould preſently, either take them on in his own Troop, or otherwiſe divide them amongſt his Captains, as the former run-awayes, who were dispoſed off, ſo as they came not under the number of ten, and what above he could prevail with; for if they came fewer, they would be committed, and returned back again: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which incouragements, the Deponants do confeſſe, to have conditioned with divers others to have run away with them, had not their Plot the night been diſcovered.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="depositions">
                        <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Robert Urwine.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHo depoſeth, that upon Tueſday the</hi> 22. <hi>of</hi> December <hi>laſt, as the Deponant ſtood Centery on the Rock,</hi> William Wagh, <hi>and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> James, <hi>came to this Deponant, telling him, that night, that themſelves, and divers others of their Colonels Souldiers, were to run away to Sir</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Cole, <hi>where they ſhould have greater liberty for plundering, or what elſe they had a minde to, then they had where they were, deſiring the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to go along with them, who replied, he knew not how conveniently ſo</hi>
                           <pb n="48" facs="tcp:158501:28"/>
                           <hi>many of them could get away together, they replied, that the Plot was laid ſo, That ſome Firelocks, which were agreed to go with them, ſhould (after the Parade was ſet, and Caſtle Gate ſhut in) plant themſelves behinde the Rocks, and give an Alarm to the Caſtle in the night, as if the Rebels had ſurpriſed them, which would put ſome confuſion amongſt them in the Caſtle at that time of the night, as they might eaſily be gone far enough out of the reach of being catched before day.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By theſe Depoſitions it may be eaſily geſſed, what comfortable Neighbourhood the Repliant had with the Reſpondent, who in <hi>July</hi> following, being in great diſtreſſe for want of Corn and Cattle, in his own Garriſon, and not to be had in that Countrey neer him; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant having by this time, (through the great power and mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God) with his ſmall handfull, ſo beaten the Rebels from about him, as he brought preys daily from amongſt them, where with he acquainted the Reſpondents then diſtreſſed Garriſon, being deſirous the Reſpondent would have ſpared this Repliant a Partie of his men, having no great imployment at that time neer himſelf for them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the Reſpondent did at that time, ſend his Lievtenant Colonell with a Partie of Horſe and Foot, and a Letter to this Repliant, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning, that he had now ſent by his Lievtenant Colonell, ſuch a Party to be made uſe of by the Repliant, in ſcouring of the County, or in whatſoever other kinde of ſervice this Repliant ſhould think fit to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them in, without limitation of any time mentioned in his Letter, or of any ſuch thing, as is moſt falſely ſuggeſted in the Reſpondents anſwer, That he had ſent them to relieve the Repliant, or that he heard of any ſiege or leagure to be then about him, though at the Repliants meeting with his Officers, and his unfortunate Son in law, <hi>Dean Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> he was told by them, that at their parting with the Reſpondent, they were limited by his Orders from his own mouth, not to be aoſent from their Garriſon above fourty eight hours, quite contrary to the contents of his Letter: Whereupon the Repliant told them, it was an impoſſibility, in ſo ſhort a time, to ingage them in any ſervice, or for the Repliant to make any uſe of them, therefore adviſed them to march back again; which all of them ſeemed moſt unwilling, to retreat to their Garriſon, untill they were once commanded upon ſome ſervice by the Repliant in the fields; who was perſwaded by their importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to march out with them towards a Caſtle called <hi>Dromahear,</hi> being within ſix miles to the Repliants Caſtle: Which ſaid Caſtle of <hi>Droma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear</hi> (at that time) had divers Rebels of great conſequence in it, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Sir <hi>Robert Hannay,</hi> and his Lady, priſoners, the Repliant having
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:158501:28"/>moſt probable hopes to have taken, both the Caſtle and Rebels, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the priſoners, had the Reſpondents officers and Souldiers, ſtuck to this Repliant and his ſmall handfull but one night longer, which all of the Officers had reſolved to have done, if it had not been the baſe, and imperiouſneſſe, of that prophane Son in law <hi>Dean Barkley,</hi> who peremptorily took upon him, to command the Officers of that party of the Reſpondents, to march away, and forſake the Repliant and his Souldiers, whereof he loſt two, being ſhot dead in working at the Walls, having paſt all the difficulties in carrying of the Caſtle; and if we had but lien by it that night (as was confeſſed by Sir <hi>Robert Hannay</hi> himſelf, and divers others that were then in it, which the Repliant can prove by credible Witneſſes that heard them ſpeak it) we had got it. So that the Reſpondents information of the Repliants ſending for his Party, in manner as is alledged, by the Reſpondent in this particular, is notoriouſly known to be moſt falſe: As likewiſe, there was not any uſe or need at all of Ordnance, for the taking in of that Caſtle of <hi>Droma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear,</hi> the Repliant having ſufficient intelligence of the condition and poſture of that Caſtle, before he attempted it; where the Reſpondents Souldiers were never ingaged in any dangerous paſſage of that Service, onely what his Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Acheſon</hi> pleaſed to offer, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himſelf to go on with the Repliant, to ſee his Souldiers ſet a work at the Walls, moſt of the Reſpondents Party having diſperſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in plundering of the Countrey, not being ſubject to Diſcipline, ſcarce owning the Orders of an Officer: Such was the neglect and careleſſeneſſe of the Reſpondent, to have his men Diſciplined, which was known to be the loſſe of a many good men, which he commanded when they pleaſed. As to the Repliants uſage of the Reſpondents Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers, it is well known to be far more bountifull and honourable, then ever the Reſpondent uſed them himſelf, the Officers having well deſerved it; having behaved themſelves civilly, with much regrate, to obſerve the Repliant and themſelves, both ſo abuſed by the private Orders, which their Colonell had given to his indiſcreet Son in law, <hi>Dean Barkley,</hi> who ſo unworthily behaved himſelf, as if he had been ſent a purpoſe with that Party to pick a quarrell, and to put an affront upon the Repliant, not ſparing publikely to threaten all the Officers, who were unwilling to leave that Caſtle of <hi>Droma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear,</hi> being ingaged before it, and ſeeing ſuch probability to have carried it that night: Nevertheleſſe, did the Repliant entertain all the Officers in his Caſtle, as alſo the Souldiers, every man of them, who many times confeſſed, they never expected the like entertainment of meat and drink from their Colonell: This being the greateſt affront,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:158501:29"/>and abuſe the Reſpondents Officers and Souldiers met withall at hat time, all of them acknowledging moſt thankfully their kinde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, thinking fit with one conſent of the Officers, to leave three or four men out of each Company, for a ſmall ſupply to the Repliants number, who were daily a waſting upon ſervice: As likewiſe, the Lievtenant Colonell knowing the great neceſſity and want, the Repliant was in for Powder, did think fit to ſpare him ten or twelve pounds weight, which was no great matter for one Garriſon, in ſuch extremity, to relieve another: Nevertheleſſe, did <hi>Dean Barkley</hi> in a malicious vindictive railing humour, except againſt the Officers, for that ſmall courteſie the Repliant had of them; alledging, the power of that Party to have been committed to his charge and truſt, by his Father in law, and that he would give no conſent, for leaving any Men, or Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the Repliants ſafety or relief, and ſo incenſt the Reſpondent againſt his Officers for that Act, as if they had relieved the Rebels, forcing them very ſhortly after, to write for their men, which ſome of them would not do, telling him, they had rather looſe their Companies, then to be acceſſary to the danger and deſtruction of the Repliant, for want of ſo few men, who had deſerved better of them all. Now let any man judge of the impudent boldneſſe of this Reſpondents informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this particular: There being nothing materiall as an Anſwer to any part of the Charge againſt him.</p>
            <p>And this Repliant confeſſes, That the Reſpondent about the ſaid moneth of <hi>May</hi> following, came with certain Companies of Horſe and Foot towards this Repliant, but denieth, That the Reſpondent came upon any deſigne or intention of his own head, to do ſervice in the Province of <hi>Conaught,</hi> as is moſt untruely ſuggeſted in his ſcandalous anſwer: But the Repliant ſhall truely inform the cauſe and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Reſpondent had for that march, which doth more cleerly appear, by this Copy of a Letter, this Repliant ſent him.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT <hi>hath pleaſed God ſo to bleſſe my ſmall Party, this morning, as they have burnt off a great many Houſes and Villages in the County of</hi> Sligoe, <hi>and Barony of</hi> Caroury, <hi>and have killed a many more of your</hi> Uſter <hi>Rogues, in and about the Caſtle of the</hi> Grange, <hi>neer ſixteen miles from hence, where</hi> Hugh mac Towell O Gailachour, <hi>with divers others, chaſt out of</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter, <hi>hath maned this Caſtle of the</hi> Grange: <hi>From whence, we brought a good Prey of Cows. And as we marched homewards with our Prey an Ambuſh of of</hi> 400. <hi>or</hi> 500, Ulſter <hi>Rebels, was laid for us, which men belonged to</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:158501:29"/>Mannus mac Neal, Garve O Donnel, Torilagh Roe O Boyl, Torilagh mac Caffry O Donnel, <hi>with a many of the</hi> O Gallachours, <hi>who thought th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mſelves ſo ſtrong, as ſome of their priſoners did report, That when they ſaw my Party marching, they ſaid, they would be but a break-faſt to them: But God in his wontedmercy hath ſo bleſſed my men, as for all their hard march laſt night and ſore ſervice about the Caſtle. As I beleeve, theſe</hi> Ulſter <hi>Rogues finde but a poor reckoning of the moſt of their beſt men, our Party having left ſtript upon the Fields, above threeſcore of naked Bodies, of which number, was one</hi> Marcuſſe O Clery, <hi>who had long ſerved the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>in whoſe Poceats were found divers Paſſes written in</hi> Spaniſh, <hi>mentioning ſeverall Services he had performed there. Thus did we beat them; bringing home abundance of their Arms, moſt of them new Muskets, and Calivers, marked with the ſign of the Croſſe on their Prim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pans: We likewiſe took priſoner, he that had charge of the Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with whom we found a great Bag of Powder, a moſt welcome commodity for us; which (as he tells me) was all the Powder that was amongſt them. Now</hi> Sir, <hi>in diſcharge of my duty to God, and His Majeſties Service, I have thought ſit, (not withſtanding your many great neglects and unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes towards me) to acquaint you with theſe paſſages. My men being few, and ſorely wearied out, ſome of them deadly wounded, ſo as I am unable without help, to lay hold on this brave opportunity ſo ſuddenly as is requiſit to perform the reſt of this Service, being credible informed by divers priſoners, that there is</hi> 10000. <hi>of their Cows, within ten miles to this Caſtle, driven hither from</hi> Boylagh <hi>and</hi> Bannagh, <hi>aſſuring you, were my men as freſh now, as they were yeſterday morning, knowing the Rogues Poſture as we have now left th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, we would grudge you, or any man elſe, a ſhare of the ſecond part of this Service, who was not at the firſt. But now as it is, an offer is made you of welcome to the purpoſe, where you ſhall finde (if you will be adviſed) worth your pains to fetch it: So as we may have but your help for killing of the Rogues, you ſhall be your own Carvers for all the Cows; What you do, do it quickly; for this Service can brook no delay, leaſt the Rogues having met with no better welcome into</hi> Conaught, <hi>indeavour to haſten from whence they came. Thus expecting your ſpeedy Anſwer, as you tender Gods glory, the Kings ſervice, and Common Cauſe, I reſt</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, ready to joyn with you, for God, and His Majeſties Service, Fred. Hammilton.</signed>
                     <dateline>Caſtle Hammilton, <date>the 15. of May. 1643.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:158501:30"/>
            <p> By this Letter may appear, the main grounds of the Reſpondents mentioned ſervice, intended for the Province of <hi>Conaught;</hi> to wit, for catching of Cows, being promiſed to be his own Carver, as the Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants Letter mentioned; never formerly having made any ſuch haſt for the Repliants relief, while as he ſtoed in danger of being deſtroyed. And ſince the Reſpondent hath thus ingaged the Repliant to anſwer the ſeverall baſe, unworthy, and moſt impudent untruthes alledged by the Reſpondent in this paſſage, the Repliant craves leave to inform the truth, That hearing the Reſpondent was in perſon with his party with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a mile or two, to this Repliants Garriſon, and being informed, the Reſpondent intended to come no neerer, the Repliant thought fit (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time ſick in Bed) to command the Gentleman, who then commanded the Repliants Horſe, to take with him a party of Horſe to attend the Reſpondent, and to let him know, the deſire the Repliant had (being ſo neer other) that they might ſpeak together, and withall, to inform the Reſpondent of the Repliants ſickneſſe at that time: But it ſeems, the guiltineſſe of the Reſpondents conſcience, did poſſeſſe him with ſome baſe jealouſies, that the Repliant had ſome deſigne upon him, ſo that he abſolutely refuſed to come neer the Repliant, but ſent his Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Acheſon,</hi> and Captain <hi>Adam Catheart,</hi> with orders to go back to the Repliants Caſtle, with his party of Horſe, and that they ſhould deliver from the Reſpondent, a Paper to the Repliant, which contained as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="statement">
                        <opener>
                           <date>
                              <hi>May</hi> 20. 1643.</date>
                        </opener>
                        <p>HUgh oge mac Gwily <hi>informed, that</hi> Heſter Edwards <hi>tells him, That her Brother.</hi> Richard Edwards, <hi>a Souldier of</hi> Mannor-Hammil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>charged her to notifie unto Sir</hi> William Cole, <hi>That Sir</hi> Frederick Hammilton <hi>did purpoſe to lay hold, and impriſon the ſaid Sir</hi> William Cole, <hi>if ever he could get him within the Caſtle of</hi> Mannor-Hammilton, <hi>wiſhing, that this may be a Caveat unto the ſaid Sir</hi> William Cole <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent him.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Upon reading this Paper, which this Repliant received, being in Bed, he asked the Lievtenant Colonell, and Captain <hi>Cathcart,</hi> if Sir <hi>William Col<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had commanded them to deliver that Paper, which it ſeemed, put ſome fear in him, and ſcared his coming neerer: The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant telling them, That he was very ſorry to ſee Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fir abuſed, as to wrong himſelf upon the information of a poor ſimple Women, in harbouring ſo baſe and treacherous a thought of the Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, he having ſo many good fellows at that time about him, to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:158501:30"/>his uſage: The Lievtenant Colonell telling the Repliant, That Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> needed not to have made any ſuch uſe of that Paper; for before they left their Garriſon, he had told Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> that he had heard her Brother <hi>Richard Edwards</hi> to have ſpoken the like; whereupon this Repliant took a Copy of this Paper, atteſted under the hands of the Lievtenant Colonell, and Captain <hi>Cathcart,</hi> returning the principall with them to the Reſpondent; and withall, ſent the Souldier <hi>Richard Edwards</hi> along with them, for the Reſpondents better ſatisfaction: As likewiſe, the Repliant ſent his Miniſter, Maſter <hi>John Long,</hi> to inform and ſatisſie the Reſpondent of the Repliants ſickneſſe, and unability, to go to the Reſpondent; and the great neceſſity there was, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent and the Repliant, ſhould ſpeak together, ſince they were ſo neer, for ordering, and concluding the courſe they meant to take for marching with that party, the Reſpondent and his men, being but ſtrangers in that Province, were to be guided by the Repliants party, the Miniſter having Commiſſion from the Repliant, to make offer to the Reſpondent for his ſafe conduct; if his ſear ſtill continued, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants Wiſe and Children ſhould be ſent as pledges to the Reſpondents party; whereupon, this motion of the Miniſters, the Reſpondent was pleaſed to venture himſelf with a many of his Officers, who (the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant dare ſay) were both kindly, and courteouſly received, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant and his Wife, though he ill deſerved it; howſoever, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſake, the Repliant thought ſit to ſtrain himſelf, and upon their meetings, the Rupliant gave Orders to his Officers, both Horſe and Foot, what party they ſhould draw out, and what courſe they ſhould take, being joyned with the Reſpondents party; which courſe, God bleſſed with ſucceſſe, as the Reſpondents expectation, and the Repliants undertakings were, both well anſwered, the party returning within two dayes, with a Prey of neer 2000. Cows, and very neer ſo many Sheep, beſides abundance of Plundering, which the Reſpondents Souldiers knew well how to go about, though the main thing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant moſt deſired, they came ſhort off, the rogues not daring to face or fight ſuch a great party; The Repliants ſmall handfull having many times made greater execution upon the Rebels, then was performed in that march; upon their return, the Reſpondent made no ſuch ceremony as formerly, in taking up his Quarters at the Repliants Caſtle, where be and ſome of his Officers were better entertained, then his thankfulneſſe by his expreſſions hath deſerved, though it was not ſo good as the Repliant could have wiſhed: Howſoever, the next morning, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoondent ſent betimes for ſeverall of his Officers to his Chamber, where they being together, ſent for the Repliant, to deſire him to ſpeak with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:158501:31"/>them; who coming amongſt them, the Reſpondent told the Repliant, that his deſire to ſpeak with him, was, That he would joyn with him and his Officers, in the dividing, and diſtributing of the Prey, to which motion, the Repliant anſwered the Reſpondent, That it having pleaſed God ſo to bleſſe them in this march, that he hoped the Reſpondent would not be ſo long a ſtranger hereafter; and as for the Prey he well remembered the words of his Letter, which was the incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Reſpondent had, that he ſhould be his own Carver for the Cows, which he meant to make good, deſiring him to take all if he pleaſed; but if there were any wearied Cows, or what was not like to drive much farther, that rather then the Rebels ſhould dog them, and get thoſe wearied Beaſts, he might leave what he pleaſed of ſuch kinde of Cattle in the Repliants Garriſon, which the Reſpondents Officers held too much courteſie, and would fain have preſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant, and his Officers, to have joyned with them in a divident, which by no means the Repliant would do: Hereupon, the Reſpondent and his Officers, thought fit, to leave in the Repliants Garriſon, neer that number of a hundred and fifty of thoſe, weak Cows, they carrying and driving, with their own party, neer one thouſand and ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Cows more, beſides a many Horſes and Mares, loaded with plunder.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Reſpondent moſt uncivilly, and clownniſhly, doth mention, that he beſtowed upon this Repliants good Lady, a thouſand Sheep; which gift of his (if it be fit to be called his gift) was a number of poor Sheep, which his party had left uneaten, and could not drive with them, they having killed abundance for their skins, to carry with them, beſides what they eat: As alſo, he mentioneth his gift to ſome Gentlemen, the Repliants Ladies Kinſmen, and to his Officers, alledging, they went with the Reſpondent in a friendly manner, as not having relation to any Charge under the Repliants Command; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as theſe two Gentlemen, Lievtenant <hi>Vaughan,</hi> and Coronet <hi>Sidney,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Couſin Germans to the Repliants Wife, did mock and jeer, when they heard the Reſpondent (having the whole Prey, beſtowed upon him and his party) to name, three Cows for one of them, and two Cows for another, which they valued not ſo much, as two groats. And thus doth the ſimple old man, think to abuſe Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>Now let any man judge, what cenſure this Reſpondent deſerveth for his falſe, and malicious relation of this paſſage; who being upon his parting that morning from the Repliants Caſtle, it having pleaſed God amongſt the reſt of his bleſſings, to ſend this Repliant a young ſon ſome weeks before that time, whom he thought fit to Chriſten, before the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:158501:31"/>good Company parted; where the Reſpondent amongſt other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, were witneſſes to that charitable Act, aſſuring him, it was none of the Repliants meaning, ever to invite the Reſpondent as a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, though at that time in civility, being in the Repliants own Houſe, he was named to ſtand as a Cipher, for another man, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed was more honour, then the Reſpondent deſerved in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, little thinking he would have made this uſe of it, in bragging, as if he had been invited to that purpoſe, whereas his invitation, and the manner of it, appears by the Repliants Letter.</p>
            <p>By this true relation, let any man judge, of what unworthy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition this Reſpondent is, and how unfit to get credit, in whatſoever he ſayes; whoſe heart is wholly ſet upon greid and covetouſneſſe, which is not unknown to ſuch as are acquainted with his humour, and condition. As to this Repliants civilties, and merit of better thanks, then to have himſelf and his Regiment exclaimed againſt, where the Repliants tongue may get any credit: This Repliant hopeth, that for all the Reſpondents endeavours to traduce him, his tongue ſhall ſtill get credit, and rather more then leſſe, in making diſcoveries to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, of thoſe, which ſeemingly pretend to do great Services for the State, whileſt they onely ſerve themſelves with pay and pillage, ſo long as they can make means to deceive the Parliament, and to waſte the Publiques means, and to caſt Aſperſions upon ſuch, who are about to diſcover their double-dealings, while as apparently they play on both ſides, to ſerve their own turn: Of which number, I pray God the Reſpondent may prove none, if his power were anſwerable to his minde.</p>
            <p>And this Repliant would be glad to know thoſe Neighbours of his, which are of ſuch quality and accompt with the Reſpondent, which will affirm ſuch falſities and untruths, as to charge this Repliant with loving contentions in the time of Peace, or War; or that this Repliant ever laboured to oppreſſe, or injure, any man in that Province where he lived, or elſewhere: But if to defend a mans ſelf againſt violence, and oppreſſions, ſtrong confederacies, and conſpiracies to ruin him, and his Eſtate, be accounted ſo, then this Repliant muſt confeſſe the action: For the truth is, That this Repliant being a ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er born, and living amongſt men, that partly for that reaſon, could not indure his Neighbour-hood, and acquaintance; And therefore, endeavouring by all means poſſible to weary and ruin him out of his Eſtate, and to blemiſh him in his good name and reputation; did ſo multiply ſutes and vexations againſt him, and made ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and incroachments upon his Lands, as that he was inforced
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:158501:32"/>to defend himſelf againſt them, and becauſe he would not be ſo tame as to lay down the Buc lers, and to yeeld that which was his own, to every mans deſires and demands of what they would have had from him, without right or reaſon; and for that it hath been his good hap ever more yet to tree and acquit himſelf from the fury and fierce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of his adverſaries; which have not been of the meaneſt rank and condition and to ſupport his credit and eſtate, by protection of the Law againſt all oppoſition whatſoever, if this hath been any miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in him towards his neighbours or any others, he might confeſſe the Reſpondent and his worthies may have therefore cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of him: But that he hath willingly injuried or done wrong to any man, he utterly denieth, and ſhall be alwaies ready to anſwer the particular complaints of any perſons grieved by him whatſoever; And therefore hopeth that by ſuch generall accuſations as theſe, he ſhall not be concluded guilty in the opinion of thoſe before whom he now ſtandeth in Judgement, who well knoweth it be the uſuall roade wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch detractors do commonly walke the better to obſcure their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts and frauds, intended for the ruin of thoſe they would thus deſtroy.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Reſpondant proceedeth yet further for to arraine this Replyants exceptions concerning Sir <hi>Robert Hannay</hi> and others, then priſoners by the Rebells, he doth acknowledge both the receit of that letter and his anſwer returned unto it, and ſhall give this account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: That this Replyant having then neer twenty foure priſoners in his Caſtle, many of them of the Chief and Prime Rebells in thoſe parts, divers of them the moſt activeſt and dangerous men, of the <hi>O Roirks</hi> who claimed to be Lords of that Country, the Replyant endeavouring what he could to ſuppreſſe the rebellion there, in hopes that aide or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief ſhould have come to his aſſiſtance, as was daily promiſed him by the then Lord Preſident of <hi>Connaught,</hi> thinking till then thoſe priſoners would have been a Curb to the reſt of the Countrie; but obſerving at laſt the deſperateneſſe of the Rebels reſolutions, after their taking in of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> and murthering of ſo many <hi>Brittiſh</hi> ſoules there, and this Replyant hopeleſſe of any relief, well underſtanding that to let theſe men looſe againe upon any conditions whatſoever, would prove fatall and deſtructive to this Repliant, and all the reſt of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> then under his care and charge; and having made ſuch a proteſtation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as is mentioned in his Letter, which he hath inviolably kept and obſerved unto this day; and the Replyant doth utterly deny that moſt malicious, wicked, and deviliſh invention of the Reſpondent, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in preſence of the Meſſenger, who brought him Sir <hi>Robert
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:158501:32"/>Hannayes</hi> letter, that the Replyant ſhould then in a moſt provoking and unchriſtian like manner hang up the ſaid Colonell <hi>O Roerkes</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that thereupon the Reſpondant moſt falſly alledgeth that the Rebels, in a revengefull manner, did murther ten or eleven Proteſtants, whereof two were Godly Miniſters. Whereas the Replyant did not hang a priſoner of his in many daies after; untill ſuch time as the ſaid Colonell <hi>Owen O Roerke,</hi> with divers regiments from other Counties fell into the Replyants Gariſon with neere two thouſand men, and burnt up his Town and all about it cloſe to the Caſtle walls, after which Act the Replyant held it time to diſpatch his priſoners by hanging of them, which was their entertainement after that ſervice done by their friends, this Replyant hoping that it was no diſſervice, but rather a peece of good ſervice to rid ſo many of that viperous brood of idolatrous Rebells out of the way upon all occaſions, for the poyſon will remaine untill the beaſt be killed, and he hopeth that herein he ſhall not undergo the Cenſure of being uncharitable, amongſt thoſe that underſtand and tender the well-fare and ſafety of theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, it being rather an Act of folly and indiſcretion, than of pity and charity, not timely to remove ſuch blocks out of the way, againſt which otherwiſe himſelf and all he commanded muſt be ſure not onely to ſtumble, but to fall; and this Repliant is confident that the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert Hannay</hi> himſelf nor his wife and children will complaine of this as any injury done unto them, knowing the condition and eſtate of the Repliant, who heartily wiſhed well unto them, ſo farre as it might ſtand with the ſafety of him and his, ſo that nothing appeareth but malice in this relation; it being a thing that nothing concerned the Reſpondant to have taken into his mouth.</p>
            <p>And it ſeemeth ſtrange to this Repliant, that the Reſpondant ſhould ſo bitterly mention the Repliants evill diſpoſitions, which in former times he hath held in better eſteem: And how this Reſpondent ſhould come to underſtand more of this Repliants own buſineſſe then himſelf, and that his Livetenant and Officers have been forced to forſake their Gariſon, by reaſon of the Repliants beating of them, which is more (as the Repliant beleeves) then the Reſpondant durſt alledge in the preſence of any of the ſaid Officers, though it is poſſible the Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant hath been endeavouring to ſeduce and draw away the ſaid Officers for the deſtruction of that Gariſon, as he did formerly the Souldiers; and this Repliant craveth that favour to tell the Reſpondant without oſtentation, That he is not to learn from him how to carry himſelf in his commands towards his Officers and Souldiers, having never as yet been chaſt by any of them, as the Repliant is informed, the Reſpondant
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:158501:33"/>hath been by his, which was held no great matter for others his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to do while as the Reſpondant was of a younger and abler yeeres to defend himſelf, though his courage was not obſerved to be then as now, which drawes theſe unexpected preferments upon the Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and makes him fare ſo much better than other, who have been thought to have deſerved informer times as well, if not better, than the Reſpondant.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Reſpondant cannot yet hide the fire he had ſo long kept cloſe in the ſtraw, the venom and malice is apparently in his heart, he endeavoureth yet further to meddle in that, in which he hath nothing to do, and to calumniate this Repliant in a matter he underſtands not, concerning the Governement of <hi>London-derry;</hi> and repreſents this Repliant, as a Petitioner for that imployment, which is but his own fancie, purpoſely moved by him and his Confederates (if he may) to foreſtale all recommendations, which have or might be given of this Repliant for any command whatſoever amongſt them. Leaſt the Repliant ſhould be able to diſcover the reſt of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended juglings: Nay by his good will he would not that the Repliant ſhould be Governour of his own family, a ſtrange proſecution of a mans good name and parts, that would make him unworthy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and of a being in the world: But this Repliant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth that this proceedeth from an opinion, which the Reſpondant holdeth with a Gentleman of a deeper reach than his own, who late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared his exceptions to this Repliants being made Governour of <hi>Sligo,</hi> becauſe he was of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation; which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant hopes ſhall ever be found more faithfull to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, than any that have <hi>Iriſh</hi> blood in them; the Repliant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing long incorporated with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> both by marriage and otherwiſe, alwaies hating and abhorring nationall difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two Kingdomes, yet hath this Repliant never ſought this Governement by himſelf, nor any other imployment, of which the Parliament ſhall not thinke him worthy; but to do them ſervice, this Repliant ſhall thinke no hazard, or other undertakings what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever too much or too hard, wherein he may ſerve and obey their commands, in the like kinde; and thus it doth appeare that the Reſpondants greateſt aym is to ſtop (if he can) the Parliaments favour to this Repliants preferment in any thing whatſoever, which hath cauſed his pen by Generalls to let fall thoſe manifold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, if this Repliant had been informer times ſo foul, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous, and unneighbourly, as the Reſpondent and his accomplices
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:158501:33"/>hath laboured with their ſcandalous tongue and pen, to make him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, the late Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and the late Lord Viſcount <hi>Rannellagh,</hi> and then Lord Precedent of the Province of <hi>Conaught,</hi> this Repliants mortall enemies, and who had then, both the means and power in their hands, to have diſcovered and puniſhed this Repliant to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and who put forth all their ſtrength, to have cruſht, and undone him, if they could, muſt in all this time, aſſuredly have brought to light, the particulars of the Repliants miſdemeanours, with which, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent maketh ſo great a noiſe, which is a meer ſound, and nothing elſe: And this Repliant faith, That untill he found the Reſpondents in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, ſo maliciouſly declared, in thoſe his anſwers towards him, he never apprehended, That the Reſpondent intended any complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as having no cauſe; And it had been ſtrange, That this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant ſhould have deſired (as is moſt untruely ſuggeſted) a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with one whom he never offended, and who had been many times ſolicited by divers Gentlemen of worth, both in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſince he came into <hi>England</hi> for a reconciliation with the Repliant, as is well known to theſe ſeverall Gentlemen ſtill in Town, much wondering how the ſeared conſcience of the Reſpondent, can ſerve him to alledge ſuch notorious known untruths: But this his aſſertion, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant ſhould deſire the Reſpondent to have concealed that which was never thought or acted, is ſo palpable groſſe, and imaginary; that in it ſelf, it appears to any impartiall Reader but meer recrimination, which had never been heard off, if not occaſioned by this Repliants Charge put in againſt him, for his ſeverall miſdemeanours, which this Repliant profeſſeth, was not done out of any hurt intended to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but in zeal to the Publike ſafety; and the deſires he hath, and ever ſhall have to ſerve this Cauſe and Common-Wealth, and to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery whereof, he findes himſelf more particularly oblieged by the late ſolemn League and Covenant.</p>
            <p>And as touching the Reſpondents compariſon, and likening of this Repliant unto Sir <hi>George Pawlet,</hi> mentioned in his Anſwer, being a man dead many yeers ago; which argueth much baſe bitterneſſe, to proceed from the mouth or pen of one in the Reſpondents yeers: So as compariſons are odious in themſelves, and that it is both uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and unworthily done, to knock at a dead mans grave, who in his life time, was eſteemed a man of eminency and worth, and of another kinde of degree and quality, then the Reſpondent; who dares thus kick at him, being dead? which ſheweth more weakneſſe, malice, and ſpleen, then otherwiſe could have been imagined in the man called Sir <hi>William Cole;</hi> ſo much blazed thorow the Citie for his Hypocriticall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:158501:34"/>goodneſſe, hoping after this, whoſoever ſhall reade this paſſage, in his famous vindicating Hiſtory, will alter their opinion of the man here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and becauſe it hath received a ſatisfactory Anſwer herein before, this Repliant will paſſe it by, and impute it, to the infirmity of his doting dayes, or as miſled to it, by other like minded, that dare not appear in it themſelves.</p>
            <p>And as to that his impudent, and ſhamefull cloſe of all his mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious invectives, which he terms pertinent inſtances, and reaſons, for to induce the Parliament, not to put the Government of <hi>London-Derry</hi> upon this Repliant; wherein he pleaſeth himſelf, to term thoſe certain informations given in againſt Colonell <hi>Mervin,</hi> the Major of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and the reſt to be aſperſions, and invented, and contrived by this Repliant and his inſtruments, of purpoſe to make them deteſtable to the Parliament. This Repliant faith, That foraſmuch as all the ſame matter, and much more, and worſe, then hath yet been alledged againſt them, is well known, and manifeſt unto the Honourable Committee of both Kingdoms, to be proved under their own hand writings, and further, to be atteſted againſt them upon all occaſions this Repliant will be further ſilent in it, and will not weary out your patience with making any further reply unto it; But all that hath gone before, doth humbly pray you to obſerve, that the Reſpondent upon the matter hath confeſſed all the Charges given in againſt him by this Repliant, and have made no manner of defence (under correction) that doth in the leaſt cleer him of the crimes and miſdemeanours laid unto his charge. That he hath through his whole Anſwer, infinitly abuſed, and traduced, this Repliant, with unſufferable ſcandals and reproaches, the moſt of them couched under generalls, which imply nothing but abuſes; ſome of them alſo, being matters concerning his own perſonall behaviour in the Government of his own Family and Commands; ſome concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Neighbour-hood, and in the mannaging of his own Eſtate, and in nothing that concerns the Publike; nor in any thing that hath relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the damage or detriment of the Common-Wealth, in caſe they had been true, as they are moſt notoriouſly falſe: And therefore this Repliant humbly craveth, repair againſt him, for theſe intollerable wrongs and injuries done him, in theſe his relations; it being (under favour) againſt the common courſe and practiſe of inferiour Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, That an offender once accuſed, and charged with any wrong done to the Common-Wealth, ſhould be admitted to recriminate any thing in his Anſwer againſt the proſecutor, untill he hath firſt purged himſelf of things, whereof he ſtands accuſed, much leſſe to Print and Publiſh the ſame by way of Anticipation of Juſtice, while
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:158501:34"/>as the matter dependeth unheard, by the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>And he humbly prayeth, it may be remembered, though one <hi>Micaiah</hi> ſuffered for propheſying the truth againſt ſome hundreds of the Court Paraſits of the King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Yet when he was ſmote between the Joynts of his Harneſſe, in <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> that he died, The Prophet was found to have told the truth; albeit, it was too late for the King to repent him of his unbelief.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Copy of the Lord Lievtenant and Councell of <hi>Ireland;</hi> Their Letter procured by Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> againſt the Garriſon at <hi>Castle-Hammilton,</hi> for breaking of the CESSATION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AFter our hearty commendations, We the Lord Lievtenant, and Councell, have lately underſtood by Letters from Sir</hi> William Cole, <hi>Knight. The Souldiers Garriſoned at</hi> Caſtle-Hammilton <hi>in</hi> Conaught, <hi>came out of that Province, and went to the Largin in the Province of</hi> Ulſter, <hi>and there in hoſtile manner, preyed, and took away on the firſt of</hi> February, <hi>four or five hundred Cows in the day time from</hi> Torilagh oge mac Gawran, <hi>and other protected by Sir</hi> William Cole, <hi>upon compoſition made by them, to contribute towards the ſupport of the Regiment, commanded by the ſaid Sir</hi> William, <hi>That by that ſpoil ſo committed on theſe men, the Garriſon of</hi> Iniskillin, <hi>is exceedingly injured, and are like to ſuffer much prejudice: That albeit, he ſent his Lievtenant Colonell with his Letters, to require reſtitution of theſe Cattle to the owners, from you the Lievtenant of Sir</hi> Frederick Hammiltons <hi>Company, to whom he alſo ſent the Letters of this Board, of the</hi> 15. <hi>of</hi> December, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to him, inabling him to agree with ſuch of the Natives, as would come under protection, for contribution to be payed towards ſupport of the ſaid Garriſon of</hi> Iniskillin, <hi>yet no reſtitution is made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Upon conſideration, whereof at this Board, We have juſt reaſon to be highly displeaſed, not onely in that we finde ſuch want of due and friendly correſpondence, rendered by that Garriſon of</hi> Caſtle-Hammilton, <hi>to the ſaid Garriſon of</hi> Iniskillin, <hi>as in wiſdom and reaſon, ought to be expected: But alſo in that, we finde that unadviſedneſſe, accomompanied with ſo high and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:158501:35"/>manifeſt contempt againſt His Majeſties Autheritie, intruſted with this Board: And therefore in favour of you, before we proceed any other way, to puniſh that contempt. We think fit hereby, to admoniſh you, and require you, immediatly upon ſight hereof, to cauſe ſuch due reſtitution, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to be made herein, as Sir</hi> William Cole <hi>may have no further cauſe of complaint: And we do let you know. That we are ſo ſencible, not onely of this unfriendlineſſe, hapned between His Majeſties own Garriſons, who ought to be equally carefull of each other; but alſo of the contempt therein offered to the Honour and Dignity of this Board: As if due and preſent reſtitution be not made immediatly: We will take ſuch other courſe herein, as may not onely be penall to the contemners, but alſo examplary for others, to take warning by. And ſo we bid you farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From His Majeſties Caſtle of</hi> Dublin, <date>26. <hi>of</hi> February, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>R. Bolton, Canc la Dublyn.</signed>
               <signed>Your Loving Friends
<list>
                     <item>John Borlaſſe.</item>
                     <item>Ormonds.</item>
                     <item>Cha. Lambard.</item>
                     <item>Ja. Ware.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Willouchby.</item>
                     <item>Edw. Brabaron.</item>
                     <item>Geo. Wentworth.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:158501:35"/>
            <head>The Copy of Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> Letter, which he ſent in the abſence of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and Garriſon; with the Copy of an old Petition, in the name of Maſter <hi>Robert Parck,</hi> then Priſoner at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle; by which Petition, and the Lords Juſtices and Councell, their Order thereupon may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, how little Warrant or Reaſon, Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had to meddle in that buſineſſe, which he forbore, till after the Ceſſation was concluded; and that he knew Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> to be gone with a Reſolution not to ſubmit to that diſhonourable Ceſſation.</head>
            <head>To his Honourable Neighbour, Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> Knight, or in his abſence, to the chief Officer, Commanding his Company in <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BY the incloſed, which is the Copy of Maſter <hi>Parks</hi> Petition, and the Order of the Lords Juſtices and Councell, including the Lord Ma<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Lievtenant Generall of His Majeſties Army. You may perceive, that Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> with ſuch matters as are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt him, was to be left at the Garriſon at <hi>Balliſhanny</hi> in the County of <hi>Dunnegall,</hi> to be thence ſent with the next Convoy to <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and ſo from thence to <hi>Dublin,</hi> to be there proceeded with, as ſhall be fit.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the poor Gentleman is reſtrained, and not ſent accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; leaſt you cannot ſpare a Guard of yours to convoy him, not yet <hi>Balliſhanny</hi> in this buſie time of Harveſt to ſend for him: I have now ſent the Bearer <hi>Charles Cokis</hi> my Enſign, Serjeant <hi>Graham,</hi> and fourty Muskettiers for him; to whoſe hands, I deſire he may be now delivered, with the matters to be objected againſt him, to be guarded, and ſafely conveyed to the Garriſon of <hi>Balliſhanny,</hi> and thence to <hi>Derry,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Dublin,</hi> as by the ſaid Order is required: Whereunto I doubt not, but you will give all due Obedience. Which leaving to your conſideration, I commit you, and us all, to the protection and direction of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I will reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving friend, William Cole.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Iniskillin,</hi> 
                  <date>18. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:158501:36"/>
            <head>The humble Petition of <hi>Robert Parck</hi> Equire. To the Right Honourable the Lords Juſtices.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HUmbly ſhewing, That your Petitioner being an</hi> Engliſh <hi>man, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Profeſſor of the Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and from the beginning of the preſent troubles zealouſly affected to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Majeſty and the State of this Kingdom, was in</hi> July <hi>laſt called upon by Sir</hi> Frederick Hamilton <hi>Knight, to go with him to his Majeſties ſervice, which the Petitioner moſt willingly aſſented unto; and having with his Souldiers and Servants given the beſt aſſiſtance for the effecting of the ſaid ſervice, the ſaid Sir</hi> Frederick Hamilton <hi>intreated your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner and his men for his ſafer Convoy, to go with him to</hi> Mannor-Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>which your Petitioner did, thinking to returne the next day to his Caſtle; but ever ſince the ſaid Sir</hi> Frederick <hi>hath keept your Petitioner cloſſe Priſoner, not permitting him to go to Divine ſervice, or to hear the Word of God for the comfort of his ſoule, neither will yeld any reaſon to the Petitioner nor to any other for his detaining.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In tender conſideration whereof, and foraſmuch as your Petitioner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained former directions from the Honourable Lords Juſtices and Councell to the ſaid Sir</hi> Frederick <hi>to ſend the Petitioner to the Lord Preſident of</hi> Conaught <hi>to be convoyed hither, to anſwer what could be alledged againſt him. May it therefore pleaſe your Honours once more by your Letters or otherwiſe, as in your grave wiſdomes you ſhall think fit, to ſend directions to the ſaid Sir</hi> Frederick <hi>for the Petitioners inlargement, upon ſuch ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Baile as your Honours ſhall think fit to take for his appearance, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to what Objections ſhall be laid to his charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And he ſhall pray, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>25. <hi>of</hi> May 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>BY Order of this Board of the 24. of <hi>January</hi> laſt, we required Sir <hi>Frederick Hamilton</hi> to cauſe the Petitioner with ſuch matters as are objected againſt him, to be delivered to the Lord Preſident of <hi>Conaught,</hi> to be ſent with the then next Convoy to the Citie of <hi>Dublin,</hi> to be here proceeded with as ſhall be fit. Which Order it ſeems was not convoyed to the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick.</hi> And now we require the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> to cauſe the Petitioner with ſuch matters as are to be objected againſt him, to be left at the Garriſon of <hi>Belliſhanny</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Dunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> to be thence ſent with the next Convoy to <hi>London-derry,</hi> and from thence hither to be here proceeded with as ſhall be fit.</p>
            <closer>Copia vera.
<signed>Signed, <hi>John Borl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe. Hen. Titchborne. Ormond. Roſcomen. Ad. Loftus. Will. Parſons. Gerard Lowther. J<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Temple.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:158501:36"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Copy of Sir</hi> Frederick Hammiltons <hi>Letter to the Lords Juſtices and Councell of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>upon the receit of this Petition and Order thereupon, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Copy of a Letter written by the Priſoner Maſter</hi> Parck <hi>to his Father in Law Sir</hi> Edward Povy, <hi>then in</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blin, <hi>who procured the ſaid Order, as alſo the Copy of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Lord</hi> Taaffe <hi>that Arch-Rebell and wicked Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Lordſhips Order the ſixth of <hi>July,</hi> dated the 25. of <hi>May,</hi> grounded upon a ſcandalous and ſeditious Petition, preſented in the name of <hi>Robert Parck</hi> Equire, now my Priſoner. That he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, a conſtant Profeſſor of the eſtabliſhed Religion, and zealouſly affected to the ſervice of his Majeſty, ſhould have been by me ſurprized and impriſoned without any warrant or reaſon; the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſcandall, as it hath moved your Lordſhips to conceive an Order in the Priſoners behalf, ſo it may make me moſt odious to all men that ſhall give credit to the ſaid ſcandalous Petition; and to be held moſt unworthy of the manifold mercies and favours God hath wonderfully ſhowed me and mine, neer this two yeeres paſt, without any aide or relief, if I prove not able to juſtifie my proccedings againſt that man, to be not onely loyall and conſcientious in this diſtreſſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate condition I have long lived in, but alſo thanks worthy from your Lordſhips being better informed, his great zeale conſiſting in ſuch ſervice as did moſt tend to the utter ruin and ſubverſion of us, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties loyall Subjects, and furtherance of the Rebels, if their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous plots by daily correſpondance, and circumſtances had not been prevented; Which was likely ſhortly to have drawen utter diſtruction upon me, mine, and all others, his Majeſties diſtreſſed <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Subjects, who hath this long ſheltered themſelves within my Caſtle, from the butcherous cruelty of the bloody Rebels, at laſt I was conſtrained, for all our ſafeties, obſerving the danger we were in, upon intelligence from his own Servants and Souldiers, to ceaſe upon his perſon and Caſtle, as well for preventing all our diſtructions (which much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted therein) as that he ſhould be lyable hereafter to anſwer his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:158501:37"/>and treaſonable carriages, which appeareth by the depoſitions of divers witneſſes his own Servants and others taken upon oath; which your Lordſhips taking into conſideration and reſerving the care of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference to me, by whom his diſloyalty and trading with the Rebels ſhall be made appear, if ever it pleaſe God to ſend us relief, that we may both be indifferently brought to the barre of Juſtice, In the meane time depending upon his Divine providence and appointed time, who can eaſe me of this and other burthens, which neceſſity in this miſerable extremity hath laid upon my ſhoulders, intreating your Lordſhips to conſider my miſerable and weak eſtate, not 300. ſtrong to maintaine this Caſtle and Garriſon, living in the bozom of the Rebels betwixt two Provinces, and what danger it were for me with ſuch a Priſoner and the evidence againſt him to be ventured with a ſmall partie of my handfull, for the conveying of him to the Gariſon of <hi>Balliſhannay</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a dangerous long way in another Province, wherein almoſt two yeeres time the ſtrength of the King and Parliaments whole forces that are in this Kingdom, hath held it a difficultie to adventure to comfort and relieve this Caſtle and Garriſon. So that your Lordſhips may judge of my condition, who am daily threatned by <hi>Owen Roerke O Neale,</hi> and moſt of the reſt of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> Rebels, who are driven into this County and Province, and are too neer my Neighbours at this inſtant, all of us apprehending much danger daily, and not a little troubled to ſee meanes made that I ſhall receive ſuch Orders in favours of ſuch as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to the Rebels, and can receive no incouragement by the like means, when we may expect comfort or relief, others our neereſt Neighbours receiving ſupplies from you, as is mentioned in my laſt Letters to your Lordſhips of the 7. of <hi>April</hi> laſt, much fearing the deſperatneſſe of my preſent eſtate, hath incouraged hard hearted and ill natured Neighbours to traduce me with more ſeditious informations as <hi>Parckes</hi> Petition doth mention. But when God ſhall provide for my inlargement, I doubt not to juſtifie my ſelf and my zealous endeavours to their greater ſhame, who are more inclining to envy than pity towards my diſtreſſed condition; Thus humbly craving pardon that I cannot part with my Priſoner as your Lordſhips Order doth require, untill God provids otherwiſe for us all, till which time and ever I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humbleſt ſervant, <hi>Fred. Hammilton.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Caſtle</hi> Hammilton <date>6. July 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:158501:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Copy of Maſter</hi> Parcks <hi>Letter to his Father in Law.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT hath not been my happineſſe ſince the beginning of theſe troubles, to have heard from you, the firſt week onely I received a Letter, untill this morning, it pleaſed Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> to ſhew me a Letter of yours with a Petition therein cloſed, in my name, directed to the Lords Juſtices; mentioning that I being an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, and a conſtant Profeſſor of the Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was by him kept cloſe Priſoner without yeilding any reaſon; wherein he findeth himſelf much grieved, as unfit aſperſions to be caſt upon him; for either of theſe reaſons mentioned in the Petition, I cannot ſay that I found them any wayes or motives that induced him to detaine me as Priſoner, and would have been glad they had been omitted in the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for the reſt of the Petition, That evening I came to his Caſtle having taken me the night before out of my Caſtle for diſobeying to come to him upon a Warrant he had from the Lords Juſtices to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me and other of that County, the Copy whereof he had ſent me the night before by a partie with his Lievtenant <hi>Leſly,</hi> and having car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me along with him to the burning of <hi>Sligo,</hi> at his returne to his Caſtle, after ſupper I was that night by him committed and had liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for three <hi>Sabbaoth</hi> dayes together to heare Sermons, and afterwards I was committed cloſe Priſoner upon divers informations and depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt me, charging me with ſeverall unbeſeeming carriages dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe troubles, which is the very truth of theſe particulars; I have not much more to write, but that God hath undoubtedly, in his ſpeciall providence, wonderfully preſerved and bleſt this handfull of men here in a more than ordinary manner, and let Col. <hi>Hammilton</hi> uſe me as he pleaſeth, I am bound to ſay the truth of him, that ſuch ſervice as he hath done here, even with a very few men and with ſo ſmall loſſe of them, is not to be parallelled (as I verily believe) in any Kingdom, but it is Gods doings and is moſt miraculous in all our eyes, the whole relation whereof would take up a volum to be written.</p>
            <p>Although the abſence of me from my wife and your ſelf hath bred me much diſcontent, yet I cannot but rejoyce that in my abſence your are not forgetfull of me, My unfaigned duty attend you, my Mother, and all yours, and my true conſtant affection to my poore Wife; and ſo the King of Heaven keep you and us all in his protection.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull Servant and Son in Law <hi>Ro. Parck.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Caſtle</hi> Hammilton, <date>6. July 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:158501:38"/>
            <head>A Copy of the Lord <hi>Taaffes</hi> Letter, after I had hanged and killed, divers of his Kinred, and Friends, who had robbed me, and my Tenants, and had beleagured me divers times in my Caſtle.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Came ſome two nights ago into this Countrey, where I ſhall not remain longer then Saturday next, being ingaged to be at <hi>Dublin,</hi> on the Tueſday following, where (if I may do you any ſervice) I ſhall faithfully perform your Commands: I beleeve Sir, the moſt welcome news I can give you a relation off, is the good ſucceſſe and prosperity of His Majeſtie, which with confidence, I give you an aſſurance off, having of late, infinitely prevailed againſt his moſt malicious, and diſloyall enemies, in that high degree; as I am confident, they will very ſuddenly ſubmit, and render themſelves to his moſt mercifull protection.</p>
            <p>Sir, I underſtand that moſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> of this Nation, pretend the having of a Commiſſion from our King, to countenance their actions, which is a moſt falſe ſurmiſe, he being ſo far from incouraging them in their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as he deemed them Rebellious, and ſolely intended to the deſtruction of the Engliſh Nation, and Government. There is ſince my coming into this Countrey, an Army of theirs, came into the County of <hi>Reſcommen,</hi> what their number is, I cannot advertiſe you, but their intention is to take all the Garriſons in that County, and to deſtroy ſuch of the Kings Army, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide there; the prevention whereof, muſt be laboured by all ſuch as hath, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power or authority. Sir, a great number of my Tenants complain unto me, how you have deſtroyed them, which I am confident they deſerved, being erroneouſly blinded by ſuch, as for their own particular intereſt, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Generall: I have laboured in ſome meaſure to reform ſome, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I cannot reſide here, I muſt refer them to your protection, being confident, that for the future, they will neither misbehave themſelves, nor labour to hinder any of your deſignes.</p>
            <p>Sir, I herewith ſend you a Petition of Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> with the Lords Juſtices and Councels Order thereupon: And though my Lord Precedent be not in the Province to receive him, I will under take (if you will truſt him to my care) to convey him ſafe to <hi>Dublin,</hi> with what examinations of his you ſend: I ſhall expect to receive your Commands, and in the interim remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant Taaffe.</signed>
               <dateline>Bellimote, <date>the 12. of July, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:158501:38"/>
            <head>A Copy of the ſeverall Depoſitions of Witneſſes, taken by Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> Knight, and Colonell, concerning Maſter <hi>Robert Park,</hi> and his Brother <hi>William Parck,</hi> their carriage ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Rebellion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THomas Powell</hi> Maſon, being duely ſworn, depoſeth, that ſome three or four dayes after the news came to the Caſtle of <hi>Droma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear,</hi> that the Rebels had burned the Iron-works, called the Garriſon, Maſter <hi>William Parck</hi> living at that time in the ſaid Caſtle of <hi>Dromahear,</hi> did upon the news, tranſport moſt of the Goods he had within that Caſtle, and delivered them a keeping, to the Friers, then dwelling at <hi>Crimley,</hi> not half a mile from the ſaid Caſtle of <hi>Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahear:</hi> At which time, the Deponant heard <hi>Owen O Roirk,</hi> deſire <hi>Walter Harriſon</hi> of <hi>Crimley,</hi> to ſpeak to <hi>William Parck,</hi> that he would leave him the ſaid <hi>Owen O Roirk</hi> in the poſſeſſion of the ſaid Caſtle, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition, That if came peace, the ſaid Caſtle ſhould be ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered unto the ſaid <hi>William;</hi> and if it continued wars, That as the ſaid <hi>Owen O Roirk</hi> ſaid, was more more kindly unto him, then to any other of his name: To which motion, <hi>William Parck</hi> in the Deponants hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, anſwered, He had already diſpoſed of the Charge of that Caſtle, to one <hi>Teage oge mac Quin,</hi> who to the Deponants knowledge was, and is, for any thing the Deponant knoweth, the chief ſervant and follower of <hi>Owen O Roirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, this Deponant ſaith, That <hi>William Parck</hi> having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in his Goods to the Friers, locked in the Caſtle Gates of <hi>Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahear,</hi> not leaving one man in it; and that very day tranſported him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Wife, to his Brother <hi>Robert Parcks</hi> Caſtle at the <hi>Newtown;</hi> From whence the ſaid <hi>William Parck</hi> returned to the ſaid Caſtle of <hi>Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahear</hi> the next morning, and with a Ladder, went over the Band-Walls, and ſtayed ſome ſhort time within the Caſtle, returning by the ſaid Ladder as he went, leaving the Caſtle without men, and the Gate barred in the inner ſide, and ſo returns back to his Brother at the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town;</hi> the next night one <hi>Hugh O Roirk,</hi> Grandchild to <hi>Mac Naw,</hi> with many Rogues in his Company, poſſeſſed himſelf of <hi>Dromahear</hi> Caſtle, who the next morning, was diſpoſſeſſed by <hi>Owen O Roirk,</hi> who
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:158501:39"/>alledged to the Deponant, and others living there at that time, that the Keyes of the Caſtle Gate was delivered him by <hi>William Parck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Deponant further ſaith, That he the Deponant remained at <hi>Dromahear,</hi> neer to that Caſtle, almoſt five weeks after <hi>Owen O Roirk</hi> had poſſeſſed himſelf thereof, his Souldiers daily robbing him, and ſome few Brittiſh more, whoſe lives were daily threatned, till at laſt, the Deponant was forced to beg leave to be gone; which was granted him upon condition, that he ſhould neither go to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> nor to the <hi>Boyl,</hi> but to Maſter <hi>Robert Parcks</hi> of the <hi>Newtown;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Owen O Roirk</hi> ſeizing upon all the Deponants Cows that were left him, onely allowing him one Cow for the relief of his children: the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponant being come to <hi>Newtown,</hi> acquainted Maſter <hi>Park</hi> with the manner of his parting with <hi>Owen O Roirk;</hi> and within a week after, this Deponant procured Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Letter to <hi>Owen O Roirk,</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Deponant, That the ſaid <hi>Owen</hi> then called Colonell <hi>O Roirk,</hi> would grant this Deponant two more of his own Beefs, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Deponant, his Wife, and Children, at Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Caſtle: Upon which Letter of Maſter <hi>Robert Parcks,</hi> the two Beefs were delivered, and the Deponant returned with a courteous kinde anſwer to Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Letter: And further ſaith, That he hath many times heard <hi>Owen O Roirks</hi> Souldiers brag, that the <hi>Newtown</hi> they held it their own, for they could have it at their pleaſure, having got <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle.</p>
            <p>This Deponant being further queſtioned, what Iriſh ſervants Maſter <hi>Robert Parck</hi> kept in his Caſtle, and how many of them went to Church; to this he depoſeth, he kept divers Iriſh ſervants, but he knew none of them that went to Church. Alſo <hi>Owen mac ô Bryan</hi> being queſtioned, if he heard of a quarrell betwixt <hi>Loghlan ô Diggennan,</hi> Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> footman, and one Engliſh-man, called <hi>Roger Guiſe;</hi> The Deponant to this ſaith, He was by when the quarrell began, and helped to part them, the quarrell beginning upon a report, that Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> had killed Colonell <hi>Owen ô Roirk,</hi> whileſt he beat his Regiment being incamped about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton:</hi> The ſaid <hi>Guiſe</hi> wiſhing a thouſand more of the like kinde were hanged or killed, whereunto the ſaid <hi>Loghlan</hi> replied, in the Deponants and others hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. That it were better, that the ſaid <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and a thouſand the like of him were hanged, then that the ſaid <hi>Owen ô Roirk</hi> ſhould be killed in that manner by Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton;</hi> and with theſe words, the ſaid <hi>Loghlan</hi> in the Deponants ſight, and others, ſtruck the ſaid <hi>Roger Guiſe</hi> over the mouth with his firſt, the Deponant and others parting them; the ſaid <hi>Guiſe</hi> with divers others of the Engliſh in the Caſtle,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:158501:39"/>much diſcontented at the ſaid <hi>Loghlans</hi> boldneſſe, complained to Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> of what had paſſed, but no reparation was made the ſaid <hi>Guiſe,</hi> neither was there any puniſhment inflicted upon the ſaid <hi>Loghlan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Deponant being further asked, if he knew one <hi>Mullmory ô Digg<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnan,</hi> or if he had heard of any words that had paſſed between Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Mullmory,</hi> concerning Sir <hi>Frederick Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton;</hi> if he was by, when the words were ſpoken, or if he heard what words they were: To this the Deponant anſwereth, That <hi>Mull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ô Diggennan,</hi> he knoweth to be Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Husbandman, and father to the ſaid <hi>Loghlan ô Diggennan;</hi> and did hear that Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> being one day in the Forge, within Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Bawn, <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan</hi> brought into the ſaid Forge ſome Plow-Irons; which Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant <hi>Heath</hi> perceiving, was ſaid to have told the ſaid <hi>Mullmory,</hi> it was a good ſight to ſee him provide for plowing, or words to this purpoſe; to the which ſpeech of Serjeant <hi>Heaths, Mullmory</hi> was ſaid to reply; it was to no purpoſe for any man in this Countrey, to Plough or Sowe, untill Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> were cut off: Theſe words the Dep<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant did not hear ſpoken by <hi>Mullmory</hi> himſelf, but did hear it from Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant <hi>Heath,</hi> to whom it was ſpoken, and heard divers others talking of it within the Caſtle, admiring that fellow ſhould be ſuffered to live: And further, this Deponant ſaith, That many Iriſh were daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and going to Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Caſtle, and Ploughing neer about it, ſuch as the three Brothers, <hi>Torilagh, Donnell,</hi> and another of the <hi>ô Boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> with one <hi>James ô Gallocher,</hi> Son in law to the ſaid <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan,</hi> having been a Souldier to the Arch-Rebell, <hi>Torilagh mac Caffry ô Donnell:</hi> This <hi>ô Gallacher</hi> going ſeverall times from the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town</hi> Caſtle, to <hi>Sligoe</hi> and <hi>Dromahear</hi> to Maſſe, and other times would be abroad two or three dayes, and ſo return, pretending to have been looking for Mares or Cattle of his Father in laws, and his own; when no good Subject of greater ſtrength then they, durſt wander abroad, or had any Cattle left them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:158501:40"/>
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>George Heath</hi> Serjeant, taken the 23. <hi>July,</hi> 1643.</head>
            <p>WHo being duely ſworn, depoſeth, That about the 24. of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> laſt, Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> hearing that Maſter <hi>Robert Parck</hi> of <hi>Newtown,</hi> (whoſe Serjeant, the Deponant then was) was beſieged, or blockt up in his Caſtle of <hi>Newtown,</hi> by the Rebels of the County of <hi>Sligoe</hi> and <hi>Letrim;</hi> for whoſe relief, the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> ſent his two Lievtenants, Lievtenant <hi>Leſly,</hi> and Lievtenant <hi>Vaughan,</hi> with a party of Horſe and Foot, with Orders, as the Deponant was told, to view in what Poſture the Rebels lay about us, and to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſpeak with Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> and to bring him and his men off, if he found himſelf unable with thoſe men, or feared his Proviſions; for the making good of that Caſtle: At the parties coming to us, Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <hi>Leſley</hi> found our Caſtle free, and delivered his Meſſage to Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> from his Colonell, withall, deſiring Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> anſwer, which was, That he would not leave his Caſtle, and that he much feared the parties danger upon their retreat, obſerving the Fields foul, and the Rebels gathering on every Hill round about us; whereupon Lievtenant <hi>Leſly</hi> deſired Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> for the better guard and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that party, which his Colonell had ſo ventured for his relief, that therefore he might be ſupplied with twenty or thirty of his men, he having ſufficient beſides to guard him in his Caſtle; which requeſt of Lievtenant <hi>Leſlies,</hi> was altogether denied by Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> though it was ſeconded, and much urged by the Deponant, and moſt of Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Souldiers, who told him, it would be a great ſhame for them all, to ſee thoſe men in danger to be deſtroyed, who had ſo ingaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for his relief: Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> anſwer was, That he would not ſpare a man, neither would he do any thing to provoke the Countrey againſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Deponant further ſaith, That ſhortly after this parting of Lievtenant <hi>Leſly,</hi> with Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> news was brought us by <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumry O Diggennan,</hi> who then ſerved Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> as his Bailiff, or Husbandman, that he had ſeen Sir <hi>Frederick Hammiltons</hi> party, ſore put to it, upon their retreat homewards, having been charged by neer ſix or ſeven hundred of the Rebels, having incountered them, and fought with them, as they were mid way, betwixt Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> and their Garriſon; which news, made the Deponant, and moſt of Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Souldiers much aſhamed of themſelves, and began to miſtruſt their own ſafeties in that Caſtle.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:158501:40"/>
            <p> Some few dayes after, this Deponant ſtanding and mourning upon the Caſtle-Wals of <hi>Newtown,</hi> did perceive four or five Horſemen riding from toward <hi>Sligoe;</hi> which Horſemen, the Deponant was told, was Captain <hi>Mac Donnaghy,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Taaffe,</hi> riding towards <hi>Mannor-Ham<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lton,</hi> to meet their Troops, having incamped about that Caſtle, they ſending a Horſeman before them, with a compliment (as this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponant was told) to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> and to ask leave freely to paſſe by his Caſtle, as they did to this Deponant, and others of the Souldiers great grief, if they durſt have followed this Colonell and Captain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not above five or ſix Horſemen in Company.</p>
            <p>W<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> f<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther depoſeth, That <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>onell <hi>Owen O Roirk,</hi> and his brother <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of the County of <hi>Sligoe;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Bryan Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagh</hi> had his Cows brought cloſe to the Caſtle of the <hi>Newtown,</hi> where they daily and peaceably grazed, with a ſmall guard of three or four heards, during the time the Camp lay about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> not a Souldier daring from <hi>Newtown</hi> Caſtle to meddle with a Cow of of them, though they were ſometimes in great diſtreſſe for victuals; this Deponant many times telling Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> what a ſhame it was to him, and how he might one day be put to anſwer it, for ſuffering the Rebels to graze their Cows ſo meanly guarded ſo neer his Caſtle, and ſo many of His Majeſties Subjects within his Caſtle in ſuch diſtreſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ab<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to ſupply themſelves and him both, if under the Deponants care and charge, he would ſuffer the men to venture for them; but the Deponant could never prevail with Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> to meddle with a Cow of them. Further the Deponant ſaith, That one night ſome of the Souldiers being in great diſtreſſe for victuals, <hi>John Powel</hi> and others, ventured with a Rope, to go over the Wals, and that night brought in thirteen Cows from the Rebels; wherewith one <hi>Walter Harriſon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acquainted, that ſo many Cows were brought by in two Souldiers, the ſaid <hi>Harriſon</hi> did alledge thoſe Cows to belong to his Foſter-Father ſwearing many oaths, that who ſhould meddle with thoſe Cows, he would have their hearts blood, and with this, acquaints Maſter <hi>Parck;</hi> who no ſooner heard of it, but in great anger, threatning, and checking the Souldiers, cauſed them to turn back all the Cows, not ſuffering a Souldier to kill a Beaſt of them: The next night, the ſame Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſore pinched with wants, for the relief of their Wives and Children, ventured as the night before, over the Wals, by the help of a Rope, and brought home that night ſome ſheep with them, which they ſpeedily kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the next morning they were challenged by a woman from the Rebels, who complained to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> that his Souldiers had that night
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:158501:41"/>brought away ſome of their Muttons; For the which, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> gave her preſent ſatisfaction, threatning the Souldiers to ſtop it in their allowances.</p>
            <p>The Deponant further ſaith, That neer about <hi>Candlemas</hi> laſt, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Forge, within the Caſtle Bawn of <hi>Newtown;</hi> one morning <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan</hi> came into the ſaid Forge with ſome Plough Irons in his hand, to whom this Deponant ſaid, it was a good ſight to ſee the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> provide for Plowing; to whom the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> replied in the preſence of <hi>Thomas Witticomb,</hi> Smith, that he the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> might provide what he pleaſed, but that he held it to no purpoſe, for any man in that Countrey, to provide either for Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Harrowing, untill Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> were cut off; whereunto the Deponant replied, It were better the ſaid <hi>Mullmory,</hi> and a thouſand, the like of him, were cut off: With which ſpeeches, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Parck</hi> was acquainted, who ſent for the Smith, <hi>Thomas Witticomb,</hi> asking if he heard thoſe ſpeeches of <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennans</hi> to Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> which the Smith juſtified, That he did hear them, this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant being preſent then; yet was not the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> queſtioned at all for thoſe ſpeeches, to this Deponants knowledge.</p>
            <p>And further ſaith, That about the time that <hi>Bryan Ballagh ô Roirk</hi> was incamped about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, this Deponant was informed, That the ſaid <hi>Bryan Ballagh</hi> had ſent a Web of neer fourty yards of Broad-Cloath, to be Woven by Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Weaver <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bryan;</hi> upon report, this Deponant went into the Work-houſe, where the ſaid Cloath was a working, and meeting with <hi>William Bryan,</hi> told him, that he would one day be hanged for working of <hi>Bryan Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagh ô Roirks</hi> Cloath, then in Rebellion; whereunto the Weaver repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That he did nothing in that, without the leave and orders of his Maſter.</p>
            <p>And further ſaith, That the news being brought to <hi>Newtown</hi> on Good-Friday morning, that Sir <hi>Frederick Hammiltons</hi> Souldiers had beaten <hi>Owen ô Roirks</hi> men, and all thoſe who were incamped about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle; upon which news, all <hi>Bryan Ballaghes</hi> Cows, which during the Camp about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> had ſo peaceably grazed about <hi>Newtown</hi> Caſtle, were that morning, all driven away; and a ſervant of <hi>Bryan Ballaghes,</hi> ſent to the Weaver to demand the Cloath, which at that time was not altogether finiſhed; the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger being moſt impatient (as the Deponant was afterwards told by the Weaver) to attend one hour for finiſhing of it; which Web of Cloath was delivered to the Meſſenger by Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> command, as the Weaver ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:158501:41"/>
            <p> The Deponant further ſaith, That ſhortly after the Camp was broke up, towards the latter end of <hi>April</hi> laſt, this Deponant was ſent, and one <hi>Roger Smith</hi> in his Company, with a Letter to Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> from Maſter <hi>Parck;</hi> and in our Companies went along, one <hi>Loghlan ô Diggennan,</hi> ſon to the aforeſaid <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan;</hi> this Deponant acquainting Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> what had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Father and the Deponant; at which time, one Maſter <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſall</hi> acquainted Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> that a Foot-boy of Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> had come to him the ſaid <hi>Hutherſall,</hi> who was ſitting upon the Hill, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Lievtenant as he was exerciſing of the Company; The ſaid Foot-boy of Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> telling Maſter <hi>Hutherſall,</hi> that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter remembred him kindly to him, and intreated him by all means to write unto him, the true ſtate of <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, and in what condition the Souldiers were in; how they were payed, and as they were pleaſed; and what other news the ſaid <hi>Hutherſall</hi> could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf beſides, and that this Letter muſt be delivered to the ſaid <hi>Loghlan</hi> with all ſecrecy, not to be known to Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> or <hi>Roger Smith,</hi> aſſuring Maſter <hi>Hutherſall</hi> of his Maſters thankfulneſſe: This curioſitie of the Foot-boyes, Maſter <hi>Hutherſall</hi> thought not fit to be concealed from Sir <hi>Frederick;</hi> upon diſcovery whereof, <hi>Loghlan ô Diggennan</hi> is apprehended, the Deponant, and <hi>Roger Smith,</hi> are return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> without any other Anſwer to his Letter, but that we ſhould tell Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> that his Footboy was taken upon ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that he was a Spie for the Rebels; and that it was reported, Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> had made his own conditions with them; upon which reports, Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> was jealous of him, wiſhing us to tell Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> That if he would have Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> truſt to his Loyalty, and had a minde to ſave his Footman from hanging, that betwixt, and the Friday following, he would ſend unto Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> the Father <hi>Mull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ô Diggennan,</hi> to anſwer and juſtifie himſelf and his ſon, both of them being Traitors, kept in by the <hi>O Roirks,</hi> about Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> (as Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> was informed) for their intelligence for our deſtructions. And that if Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> did not ſend the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> as was deſired, then would Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> hold Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> himſelf no good Subject afterwards: Which meſſage and information from Sir <hi>Frederick,</hi> was accordingly delivered by <hi>Roger Smith,</hi> and the Deponant, to Maſter <hi>Parck;</hi> who gave no other anſwer at that time, but ſeemed to be much vexed, for the leaving of his Footman behinde: Saying, he knew not where to finde <hi>Mullmory;</hi> yet the Deponant was informed afterwards, that whileſt he and <hi>Roger Smith</hi> went to ſleep, having marched that night, that Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> ſent one <hi>Rice Jones</hi> privately to <hi>Mullmory ô</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:158501:42"/>
               <hi>Diggennan,</hi> who was come to the Caſtle that morning, to adviſe the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> to ſhift for himſelf, for he durſt not longer keep him Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> having cauſed to apprehend his ſon, and ſent for himſelf that morning; and further this Deponant ſaith not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Roger Smith</hi> taken <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHo depoſeth, That towards the latter end of <hi>April</hi> laſt, being ſent with Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> from Maſter <hi>Robert Parck,</hi> with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton;</hi> Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> having a little before this, beaten the Rebels of the County of <hi>Letrim</hi> and <hi>Sligoe,</hi> which had long incamped about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle: during which time <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk,</hi> and divers others of the Rebels, grazed their Cattle neer, within a Musket ſhot, to Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Caſtle of the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town;</hi> and upon the Deponants return from <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Parck</hi> asked, if he had brought no anſwer to his Letter, who ſaid he had none but a Meſſage, That Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> being informed, that he had made his own conditions with the Rebels, who had promiſed to ſpare Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> untill they had got their will of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammiltons</hi> Caſtle, and that Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> had promiſed not any way to interrupt the Rebels, being daily ſo bold about Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> as not onely to graze their Cattle ſo neer his Gate, but in ſuffering them to make their daily paſſage thorow his Land with victuals and other relief for their Camp, whileſt they lay five weeks about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, without the interruption of Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> or any in his Caſtle, having at that time neer threeſcore of able men in it, wiſhing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponant, to tell Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> that unleſſe he would ſend him <hi>Mullmory O Diggennan</hi> (who as Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> was informed, had been fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings Souldiers) he would hold the ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> as a Traitor himſelf: Which meſſage, this Deponant in preſence of Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> delivered to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> he being in Bed, ſhewing a great deal of anger againſt the Deponant, for leaving of his Footman <hi>Loghlan O Diggennan</hi> behinde him: The Deponant being weary with the nights march, went to ſleep, and as he awaked, he was told, that <hi>Mullmory O Diggennan</hi> was run away; but afterwards, the Deponant heard <hi>Rice Jones</hi> ſay, that Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> had ſent him to adviſe the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> to ſhift for himſelf; ſhortly after, the Deponant and Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> had
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:158501:42"/>delivered their meſſage, that morning they came from <hi>Mannor-Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further depoſeth, That he did ſee a Cow which one <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> a poor Engliſhman had taken, while as <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> Cows grazed neer the <hi>Newtown</hi> Caſtle, during the Camp about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> and did ſee <hi>Bryan Ballaghes,</hi> Herdſman <hi>Thomas Carvell,</hi> complain to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> giving order to his Bailiff, <hi>Mullmory O Diggennan,</hi> to make ſearch for the ſame, who found the Cow killed by the Engliſhman, <hi>Norman</hi> and his Wife, whereat, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> was very angry: Saying, That was the way to bring trouble enough, and bring the Country upon their backs, wiſhing <hi>Mullmory O Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gennan,</hi> to tell <hi>Bryan Ballagh,</hi> that the Engliſhman ſhould no more come within his Gates, for meddling with <hi>Bryan Ballaghes</hi> Cows. And further ſaith, That the <hi>Newtown</hi> Caſtle was daily relieved with Milk from <hi>Bryan Ballaghes Bolly,</hi> during the Camp about MANNOR-HAMMILTON, the Herds Wife bringing of it freely.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Dermond O Ferry</hi> Harper, taken the 12. of <hi>January,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>WHo depoſeth, That upon Friday the 28. of <hi>January,</hi> 1641. this Deponant coming to the Church of <hi>Clanclare</hi> within half a mile to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, where he found that night Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>O Roirk</hi> with divers other Colonels and Captains, gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with intention, the next morning to burn off the Town and Garriſon of <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> with both the Water-Mills there; which accordingly was performed in this Deponants ſight, who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards got leave of <hi>Owen O Roirk,</hi> to go back to the Caſtle of <hi>Droma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Owen O Roirks</hi> Wife, and family lived, living him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with his Brother <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk,</hi> with five or ſix hunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more of the Rebels, incamped neer unto the Caſtle of <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> where they lay till Friday, the fourth of <hi>February</hi> following; which day, they were beaten from the Camp, where the ſaid Colonell <hi>Owen ô Roirk</hi> told the Deponant, he eſcaped narrowly himſelf, divers of his Regiment being killed, and the reſt chaſed.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:158501:43"/>
            <p> The Deponant further faith, That about the 20. of <hi>February</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he this Deponant obtained leave, that he might go viſit Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> at <hi>Newtown,</hi> whom he had formerly ſerved as his Harper; which granted him, conditionally, that he ſhould ſtay but one night with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Parck,</hi> and that this Deponant ſhould tell Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> That Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>O Roirk,</hi> and the reſt of their Army, were informed, that Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> had ſupplied Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> with what Powder was ſpent upon them, the laſt day they were beaten from their Camp; which if Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> had done ſo, it was more then they expected from his hands: For whoſoever ſhould lend Armes or Ammunition againſt them, was to be held, as much an enemy, as thoſe that fought againſt them.</p>
            <p>And withall, Colonell <hi>O Roirk,</hi> bid this Deponant tell Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> that he with his Brother <hi>Bryan Ballagh ô Roirk,</hi> had been deſired by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Letters from the Gentlemen of the County of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> to joyn with them in laying a Camp about Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> and his Caſtle, at the <hi>Newtown,</hi> which they both refuſed, adviſing the County of <hi>Sligoe</hi> Gentlemen, rather to joyn with them in camping about <hi>Mannor-Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> Caſtle, who had done them much hurt, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> having done them none; and being able to deſtroy Sir <hi>Frederick Hammiltons,</hi> Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> and his, would be eaſily their own. This Deponant ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving delivered his meſſage to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> letting him know withall, That he could ſtay no longer then that night, being ingaged by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to Colonell <hi>O Roirk,</hi> to return the next morning; whereupon Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> wiſhed the Deponant to tell <hi>Owen ô Roirk,</hi> that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever informed, that Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> was ſupplied by him with any Powder, wronged him much, for he was not ſtored, as to have ſpared his Father any: And further, the ſaid <hi>Parck</hi> told this Deponant, That though he was deſirous to have enjoyed his Company longer, yet ſince he was ingaged by his promiſe to Colonell <hi>O Roirk,</hi> to return the next day, he would by no means to have him break his word; Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> likewiſe telling the Deponant, That it was reported amongſt them, that Colonell <hi>O Roirk</hi> was likewiſe killed by Sir <hi>Frederick Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> at the breaking up of the Camp, till the Deponant aſſured him of the contrary; and that he was an eye-witneſſe that day the Town and Garriſon of <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> was burned: Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward asking this Deponant, what the Countrey ſaid was the reaſon for this Rebellion, they alledged the King to have incouraged them to it; which if he did ſaid Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> we muſt all do as the King will have us to do; but untill the truth of this appear, I will keep my ſelf quiet, and meddle as little as I can.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="deposition">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:158501:43"/>
            <head>The Depoſition of <hi>Thomas Jones</hi> Clerk, taken the 14. of <hi>July,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>WHo being duely ſworn, depoſeth, That in <hi>June</hi> laſt coming from <hi>Newtown</hi> to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> Maſter <hi>Robert Parck</hi> deſired the Deponant, to advertiſe him privately, if at any time he obſerved Sir <hi>Fred. Hammilton</hi> diſpleaſed towards him; or that the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> had any intention to take away his men from him; or any other matter that the Deponant thought fit to advertiſe him with privately, ſhewing the Deponant a peece of paper, cut in ſuch a manner, as a man might write by it to his friend, and none could read it, or make ſence of what they read, but by the like paper, which Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> called a mask for a Letter: And ſhortly after this Deponant being at <hi>Mannor-Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> had one of the masks cut in Parchment, and ſent from Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> by <hi>Rober Slixton,</hi> to the Deponant, which he preſently ſhewed to <hi>Rice Jones,</hi> who told this Deponant, That he the ſaid <hi>Rice Jones,</hi> was ſent by Maſcer <hi>Robert Parck</hi> (at ſuch a time, as Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> and <hi>Roger Smith,</hi> came from <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi>) to give warning to <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan</hi> to ſhift for himſelf, for he could no longer protect him, Sir <hi>Fred. Hammilton</hi> having ſent for him, and committed his Son in law.</p>
            <p>This Deponant further ſaith, That after the taking in of <hi>Sligoe</hi> by the Rebels, and the great murders there committed upon the Brittiſh, the Deponants Son in law, <hi>Humphrey Jones,</hi> told this Deponant, That he was ſent by Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> in the night time, with two peeces of Plate to <hi>Andrew Crean,</hi> to a place called the <hi>Armagh,</hi> where he borrowed from the ſaid <hi>Andrew,</hi> for the uſe of Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> eight pounds <hi>ſterlin.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Andrew Creans</hi> two ſons, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>William ô Crean,</hi> being at that time in open Rebellion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Rice Jones</hi> Gentleman taken <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Deponant by vertue of his oath, doth acknowledge to have ſeen the mask for a Letter, cut in Parchment, and ſent (as Parſon <hi>Jones</hi> told this Deponant) from Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> to Parſon <hi>Jones</hi> from <hi>Newtown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further this Deponant doth confeſſe, That morning after
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:158501:44"/>Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> and <hi>Roger Smith</hi> returned from <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> to <hi>Newtown,</hi> Maſter <hi>Robert Parck</hi> ſent this Deponant to <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan,</hi> to acquaint him, that Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton</hi> had cauſed to apprehend his ſon <hi>Loghlan Oge,</hi> and had ſent for the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> to be ſent him likewiſe; and therefore Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> wiſhed the Deponant to advertiſe him, and to adviſe him to ſhift for himſelf, for he durſt no longer protect him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>William Parkenſon</hi> of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town</hi> Butler, taken the 12. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>WHo depoſeth, that he was told by <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan,</hi> that he had procured for his Maſter, Mr. <hi>Robert Parck</hi> eight pound <hi>ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> of one of the <hi>Creans</hi> neer <hi>Sligoe,</hi> upon three peeces of Plate, which was ſent from his Maſter by <hi>Humphrey Jones,</hi> who received the Money and brought it to Maſter <hi>Parck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further depoſeth, That ſince this Rebellion, one Iriſhman cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Owen mac Bryan,</hi> told this Deponant one day in a great paſſion, that he hoped ere long, all the Engliſh Rogues or Engliſh Dogs, ſhould be cut in peeces and deſtroyed, or words to this purpoſe; with which words, this Deponant acquainted Maſter <hi>Parck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further depoſeth, That while as <hi>Bryan Ballaghes</hi> Cows grazed neer <hi>Newtown,</hi> during the Camp about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, this Deponant obſerved a Woman and a Wench, once or twice a week, to bring in Milk to the Caſtle of the <hi>Newtown,</hi> from <hi>Bryan Ballaghes Bolly,</hi> which was ſpent at Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> Table; but whether or not, this Woman was <hi>Bryan Ballaghes</hi> Cow-heards Wife, as by others is alledged, this Deponant knoweth not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Thomas Witticomb</hi> Smith, taken the 10. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>DEpoſeth, That about <hi>Candlemas</hi> laſt, one <hi>Mullmory ô Diggennan,</hi> ſervant to Maſter <hi>Robert Parck,</hi> coming to this Deponants ſhop with Plough-Irons in his hand. Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> meeting him there, told him, it was a good ſight to ſee him in theſe troubleſome times provide Ploughing; whereunto this Deponant heard the ſaid <hi>Mullmory</hi> reply, That they might provide what they pleaſed, but none of this Countrey would do any more good with Ploughing, untill Sir <hi>Fred. Hammilton</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:158501:44"/>were cut off, whereunto Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> replyed it were better a 1000. the like of <hi>Mullmory</hi> were hanged, than that Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> ſhould be cut off; And further this Deponant ſayth, that he was ſent for by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Parck</hi> to his own Chamber, and examined upon theſe words in preſence of Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> both of us juſtifying to Maſter <hi>Pa r</hi> that we heard <hi>Mullmory</hi> ſpeak theſe words.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>William Bryan</hi> of <hi>Newtown</hi> Weaver, taken <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHo being duely ſworn and examined depoſeth, that having ſerved Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> in his Town of <hi>Newtown,</hi> ſince <hi>May</hi> was a yeere, untill the beginning of this rebellion, that he got leave from Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> to put his Loomes in the Caſtle of <hi>Newtown,</hi> where he wrought for his Maſter and others as would pay him; and further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth that about Shrovetide laſt, whiles the camp lay about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, a ſervant of <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirke,</hi> whoſe name the Deponant knowes not, (who many times uſed to come to Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> houſe) did ask the Deponant if he would work a peece of cloath for his Maſter <hi>Bryan Ballagh,</hi> who anſwered if Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> would give him leave; the Deponant ſhortly finding Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> without the Caſtle-gate, told him that <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> man deſired him to work a peece of cloath for his Maſter, This Deponant asking Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> if he thought it would be any hurt for him to work it, whereunto Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Parck</hi> replied, that he hoped it would be no hurt for him at all; Some weekes after this <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> man coming againe to the houſe, this Deponant adviſed him to bring his Maſters yearn, which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly the man did towards the middle of Lent, the Deponant at that time having ſome of Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> own cloath in hand, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> coming into the work-houſe, asked this Deponant if <hi>Bryan Ballagh</hi> had not as yet ſent his yearn to be woven, which ſo ſoon as it came, imployed one <hi>William Morray</hi> a <hi>Scots</hi> man of his own Trade, to work the cloath for him, this Deponant during that time onely providing of the pernes, which cloath was a weaving untill good <hi>Friday,</hi> which was the day after the camp was beaten and broken up from about <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, which morning very earely before Sun riſing <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> man came for the cloath, the Deponant telling him it was not quit ready, wiſhing him to come in the afternoon, and he ſhould have it, but the meſſenger replied that he could not go without it, the cloath being ſhortly afterwards finiſhed Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> ſends one
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:158501:45"/>
               <hi>Anthony Collecarway</hi> a ſervant of his own, commanding ſpeedily to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the cloath to <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> man, this Deponant receiving for his work ſix ſhillings wanting two pence, the cloath amounting to ſo much, after the rate of two pence the yard weaving, this Deponant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther depoſeth. Whiles the Cloth was in the Loome a working, that Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> divers times came into the Work-houſe, telling this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent that he would be hanged for working of <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> Cloth then in Rebellion; the Deponant anſwering him, that he did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but he was commanded and warranted by Maſter <hi>Park.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="deposition">
            <head>The Depoſition of <hi>Willam Morray</hi> Weaver, taken <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHo Depoſeth, that about New-years day laſt, being kept at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> Caſtle, in the County of <hi>Mayo,</hi> and coming in that caſe towards Mannour <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and paſſing by Maſter <hi>Parkes</hi> mill, neere the <hi>New-town,</hi> one of the Rogues laid hand on this Deponant, not ſuffering him and one <hi>Edward Maxwell</hi> in his company, to paſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Enniskillin</hi> as they pretended, but adviſed this Deponant to go towards <hi>New-town,</hi> one of the Rogues ſpeaking good Engliſh; whom this Deponent hath divers times ſince ſeen at <hi>New-town</hi> Caſtle; where the Deponant being come he was imployed by Mr. <hi>Parke</hi> as other ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were, in ſtanding Centry, and doing duty about the Caſtle, and ſometimes working in his Trade; and at ſuch time as <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirks</hi> yearn was ſent to be wrought by <hi>William Bryan,</hi> Mr. <hi>Parke</hi> at that time commanded the Deponant to leave all other work, and to fall about <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirks</hi> cloth, promiſſing the Deponant he ſhould be exempted of all other work and duty, untill it were finiſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="deposition">
            <head>The Depoſition of <hi>Owen Mac O Bryan,</hi> Serjeant to Maſter <hi>Robert Parke</hi> taken the 15th. of <hi>July,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>VVHo depoſeth, that about the 20th. of <hi>January</hi> laſt in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being at <hi>New-town</hi> bruſhing his Maſters Cloths; the Butler <hi>William Parkinſon</hi> came to the Deponant, telling him there was a Horſe-man at the Gate deſirous to ſpeak with him, and as the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant went down the ſtaires he perceived Serjeant <hi>Heath,</hi> and a many of the ſouldiers upon the Bawn-Walls, gazing upon ſome Horſe-men
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:158501:45"/>riding by the Caſtle; and as the Deponant came to the Gate he did ſee <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kinſman of his own called <hi>Maurice mac O Bryan</hi> ſitting on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, who had formerly ſerved Mr. <hi>George Craſton,</hi> and was now in ſervice as he told the Deponant with Captain <hi>Bryan Mac Donaghie,</hi> who was riding by the Caſtle with Colonell <hi>Lucas Taffe,</hi> who had ſent him the ſaid <hi>Maurice</hi> to preſent both their ſervices to Mr. <hi>Robert Parck,</hi> and withall told the Deponant they were riding towards <hi>Mannor-Hammil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> where their Regiment lay with the Camp neere that Caſtle: whiles the Deponant was thus in diſcourſe with his Kinſman, <hi>William Parkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> the Butler called the Deponant to come in, that the Gate might be ſhut; but before the Deponant entred the Gate, Captain <hi>Mac Donaghie</hi> called to him <hi>Owen mac O Bryan</hi> how do you; but the Deponant being in haſte to ſhut the Gate made no anſwer, but preſently went to his Maſter being in Bed, acquainting him that Colonell <hi>Taffe,</hi> and Captain <hi>Bryan mac Donaghy</hi> were with four or five Horſe riding ſo neere the Caſtle towards <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> thinking Mr. <hi>Parck</hi> (they being ſo few) would have commanded men to have followed after them; but Mr. <hi>Parck</hi> being in Bed, obſerving ſo many come in unto him with theſe news, angerly bid them, let them Ride where they would for him, what had he to do with them; Mr. <hi>Parck</hi> at that time commanding neere ſixty or ſeventy able men within that Caſtle, moſt willingly to have been imployed.</p>
            <p>The Deponant further faith; that about Candlemaſſe laſt, one <hi>Cormick mac Robert MacTernan,</hi> then in Rebellion with <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Cormick</hi> being Foſter-father to <hi>Walter Harriſon,</hi> being then in the Caſtle with Mr. <hi>Parck,</hi> did ſend three Beeves about midnight to the ſaid <hi>Walter Harriſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Parck</hi> cauſing the Gate to be opened and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, one of the Beeves being beſtowed upon Mr. <hi>Parck,</hi> another was ſold for ten ſhillings to <hi>John Darrington,</hi> and the third ſold too, to <hi>Rice Jones,</hi> as this Deponant heard; and faith, that ſhortly after <hi>John Powell</hi> and others of the ſouldiers being not ſuffered by Mr. <hi>Parck</hi> to meddle with any of <hi>Bryan Ballaghs</hi> and the Rebells Cows which gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed daily neere to the Caſtle; in the night-time the ſaid <hi>John Powell</hi> and and others conveyed themſelves over the Bawn-walls with Ropes, and brought in ſome Cows with them that ſame night, which <hi>Walter Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon</hi> alleadged to be his Foſter-fathers <hi>Cormick mac Roberts</hi> Cows, and therefore would not ſuffer one of them to be touched but turned back to the Rebells. The next night the ſame ſouldiers ventured as before with Ropes over the Walls, bringing whom with them eight Cows, and thirty Sheep, wherewith Mr. <hi>Parck</hi> being acquainted got out of his Bed,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:158501:46"/>clapping his hands, and crying out, that they ſhould be all undone, cauſing them preſently to drive back, both the Cows and the Sheep, not ſuffering the Souldiers to kill one Beaſt of them. And further ſaith, that he did ſee <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirks</hi> herd brought to Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> by one <hi>Mullmory O Diggennan,</hi> complaining to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> that they had found one of <hi>Bryan Ballaghes</hi> Cows, which had been taken and killed by a poor Engliſhman, <hi>Thomas Normand,</hi> and his Wife, who were by Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> turned out of the Caſtle a little before that; upon which complaint, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> in a great anger, bid the ſaid <hi>Mullmory,</hi> and the Cowherd, do with the ſaid <hi>Normand,</hi> and the killed Cow, what they pleaſed, for he had before that, turned him and his Wife and Children, out of the Caſtle; and ſince had nothing to do with them: The Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd many times threatning the poor Engliſhman in Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that ſince it was ſo, he would have the ſaid <hi>Normands</hi> head for the Cow.</p>
            <p>This Deponant further faith, That he being in company with <hi>Walter Harriſon</hi> and <hi>Thomas Lambard,</hi> neer to the Caſtle of the <hi>Newtown,</hi> they all three went towards <hi>Torilagh O Boyland,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Donnell O Boyland,</hi> where they were a Ploughing within leſſe then Musket ſhot to the Caſtle; where the ſaid <hi>Donnell O Boyland</hi> ſhewed this Deponant ſeverall ſtobs and cuts which he had received in his Jerkin, that day <hi>Mullmory mac Ternan,</hi> and divers others of the Countrey Gentlemen were killed by Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> party, as they retreated from the <hi>Newtown.</hi> The Deponant asked the ſaid <hi>Donnell,</hi> how he durſt fight againſt any of the Kings Souldiers, who anſwered, That neither he, nor any of his Fathers Children would fight againſt any other, but ſuch as were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> who daily deſtroyed ſo many of them; the Deponant being asked, why they did not upon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, apprehend the ſaid <hi>Donnell,</hi> and carry him to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> the Deponant replied, That none of them durſt meddle with any of theſe <hi>O Boylands,</hi> nor any other of thoſe Iriſh that uſed daily about the Caſtle, and allowed by their Maſter to Plough, which he might eaſily ſee out of his Chamber Window; as alſo, the Deponant doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſeverall times, to have ſeen the Cloath while it was a Weaving within the Caſtle, by Maſter <hi>Parcks</hi> directions, for <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk</hi> at that time, whiles the ſaid <hi>Bryan Ballagh O Roirk</hi> was incamped about <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:158501:46"/>
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Walter Harriſon,</hi> taken the 13. of <hi>January,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>WHo acknowledgeth, That he the Deponant being in the Caſtle of the <hi>Newtown</hi> with Maſter <hi>Robert Parck,</hi> the Deponants Foſter-Father called <hi>Cornick mac Robert mac Ternan,</hi> did one night ſince this Rebellion, ſend by a Boy of the Deponants, called <hi>Teag mac Ternan,</hi> three Beefs, which this Deponant received about midnight, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> cauſing the Caſtle-Gate to be opened and to put them into the Bawn: Which three Beefs, as the Deponant alledgeth, were for the uſe of the Caſtle. The next night after, the Souldiers brought in five Cows more, which the Deponant believed, did belong to his Foſter-Father, telling them, if they were his, it was ſhame for them to bring in a poor mans Cows, who had ſupplied them the night before, there being ſo many of <hi>Bryan Ballaghes O Roirks,</hi> and others of the Rebels Cows, daily grazing ſo neer that Caſtle, and that it were better to ſeize upon them, then upon his poor Foſter-Fathers; whereupon by order, were commanded to forſake thoſe Cows: And the next night the ſame Souldiers brought eight Cows, and thirty Sheep from the Rebels, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> being acquainted, got out of his Bed in a great paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, clapping his hands, coming to the Gate, and many times crying out, now we are all undone, cauſing the Gate to opened, and to drive the Cows and Sheep towards the Rebels again.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Benjamin Alexander,</hi> Clerk, taken the 10. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>WHo depoſeth, That upon the rumour of this Rebellion, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponant being then at <hi>Sligoe,</hi> went to Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> with whom he remained in his Caſtle: and being there about the 20. of <hi>January</hi> laſt, being in Bed, This Deponant heard, that there was three or four Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains riding in haſte by the Caſtle, and that they had a compliment to Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> of their love and ſervice, and that they were going to Camp at <hi>Mannor-Hammilton;</hi> the Deponant being asked, what men as he thought was then in the Caſtle, the Deponant thinketh neer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt fifty and ſixty, and denieth to have heard of any motion for ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or following of them, which pretended to go to the Camp at
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:158501:47"/>
               <hi>Mannor-Hammilton:</hi> And further depoſeth, That at the ſame time, as Lievtenant <hi>Leſly</hi> was ſent with a party to have relieved Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> being then as was reported beſet with the Rebels, the Countrey being obſerved to be gathering together, to prevent the Lievtenant, and the parties return: This Deponant heard it mentioned to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> (but by whom he cannot tell) that the Drum ſhould beat, and that twenty or thirty of his men ſhould go along, as a guard to help the Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and the party; which motion was preſt by divers, but Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> would not yeeld to it: And further depoſeth, That one <hi>Roger Guiſe</hi> told this Deponant, that he had received a Box on the ear from an Iriſh footman of Maſter <hi>Parcks,</hi> for ſpeaking againſt <hi>Owen O Roirk,</hi> who was ſaid to be killed, when they were camping neer the Church of <hi>Clanclare.</hi> And further depoſeth, He heard that Serjeant <hi>Heath</hi> and <hi>Roger Smith,</hi> upon their return from <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> delivered a meſſage to Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> that he ſhould apprehend <hi>Mullmory O Diggen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan,</hi> and ſend him to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton,</hi> otherwiſe Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> would hold him as a Traitor.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <head>The Depoſitions of <hi>Connor O Fynny,</hi> taken the 13. of <hi>January.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>WHo depoſeth, That upon the Tueſday or Wedneſday before <hi>Eaſter</hi> laſt, the Rogues of the County of <hi>Sligoe</hi> and <hi>Letrim,</hi> lying their incampt neer <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Caſtle, the Deponant was ſent for by his Maſter, Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> of <hi>Newtown,</hi> and commanded him to carry a Linnen Bag with him, with ſome things in it along in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, with one <hi>Teage Reagh O Gillgan,</hi> a Tenant to <hi>Andrew Crean,</hi> dwelling at a Village called <hi>Curvulagh,</hi> on the way neer <hi>Sligoe;</hi> and as he went from his Maſter, he met the party <hi>Teage O Gillgan</hi> at the Gate, with whom the Deponant was commanded to go to his houſe, and there to have left the Bag, and to have brought to his Maſter from thence, an example of ſome Malt; but as the Deponant was going, he was commanded, within leſſe then a quarter of a mile to the <hi>Newtown,</hi> the Deponant was taken by half a ſcore of Rogues, calling themſelves Souldiers to <hi>Donnell O Connor,</hi> they taking the Bag from the Deponant, threatning to carry him to <hi>Mannor-Hammilton</hi> Camp, to their Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, where he ſhould be hanged; but by the perſwaſion of <hi>Teage O Gillgan,</hi> they meddled not with the Bag, but carried this Deponant a little way off, where they met with the two Captains, Captain <hi>John O
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:158501:47"/>Crean,</hi> and Captain <hi>Donnell O Connor,</hi> who by the perſwaſion of <hi>Teage O Gillgan,</hi> ſuffered this Deponant to return to his Maſter, after promiſe made by him, that he ſhould return to them the next day, having got his Cloaths, and that he ſhould bring a peece with him: being demanded whether there was Money or Plate in the Bag, by the vertue of his oath depoſeth, That he could not ſay what was in it, for he never opened it; but faith, ſo ſoon as the Captains came, the Bag was delivered to the party in his Company, as Maſter <hi>Parck</hi> had appointed, and that by the command of the two Captains, and the Deponant ſent home to his Maſter without further harme; who when he came to his Maſter, telling what had befaln him, his Maſter asked how he eſcaped, ſaying, that he was glad he ſo eſcaped, without any more harme; the Deponant not being from him above three or four hours, and asking what became of the Bag, the Deponant told him, the party had received it, by the Captains command whom he ſent it to: And further ſaith, That he was told that day by the Rogues, that the Sunday before they had carried away fifteen or ſixteen of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammiltons</hi> Horſes; and that before Sunday next, they were ſure to have his Caſtle, Bidding the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponant tell Maſter <hi>Parck,</hi> to yeeld his Caſtle, otherwiſe they had a Peece of Ordnance, and would beat it about his ears, when they came from <hi>Mannor-Hammilton;</hi> whether that day the Deponant ſaw the Rogues flocking towards the Camp in ſeverall numbers, as if they had been going to a Fair; being asked, whether or not to the Deponants knowledge <hi>Teage Reagh O Gillgan</hi> had ſpoken with his Maſter, that morning he received the Bag or not, to which queſtion, the Deponant faith, He doth not know, he meeting him at the Gate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>
               <hi>The Copy of a Certificate given under the hands of ſeverall Gentlemen, at the deſire of Sir</hi> Frederick Hammilton. <hi>Dated</hi> 14. <hi>of</hi> January. 1642.</head>
            <p>WE the undernamed perſons, do hereby ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to have been preſent, by the deſire of Sir <hi>Frederick Hammilton,</hi> Knight and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:158501:48"/>Colonell, while as he read the ſeverall Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Benjamin Alexander, Rice Jones, Thomas Jones, Roger Smith, William Parkenſon, William Morray, William Bryan, Dermond Offerry,</hi> and <hi>George Heath,</hi> concerning Maſter <hi>Robert Parck</hi> of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town,</hi> being perſonally preſent there himſelf, at the reading of the foreſaid Depoſitions; where the ſeverall Deponants did in all our hearings, acknowledge the Depoſitions to be the ſame, which upon oath they had deponed formerly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Sir <hi>Frederick.</hi> And thus much we have thought fit to certifie under our hands, being deſired ſo to do, leaſt hereafter any of the ſaid former Witneſſes ſhould miſcarry, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of His Majeſties future Service; which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we have done, As witneſſe our ſeverall hands hereunto ſet, the day and yeer aforeſaid.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Leſly,</hi> Lievtenant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Long,</hi> Preacher.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Cunningham,</hi> Preacher.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alex. Mountgumery,</hi> Preacher.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Sidney.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Vaughan,</hi> Lievtenant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Greere.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Baxton.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:158501:48"/>
            <head>The Copy of a Letter from the Lords Juſtices and Councell of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AFter our very hearty Commendations, on the 21. of this Moneth, We received your Letters of the 19. of <hi>November,</hi> and ſecond of <hi>December,</hi> and do acknowledge to you, with ſpeciall thanks, your good indeavours in thoſe parts; and although we cannot yet ſend you relief, as we deſire, yet we are aſſured, that in ſhort time, we ſhall be inabled to do it.</p>
            <p>There are arrived here this day, fourteen hundred men, ſent us forth of <hi>England;</hi> and further, powerfull ſuccours are in the way a coming, whom we expect to arrive ere long, and with them will come plentifull ſtore of Arms, whereby we ſhall be the better inabled to ſupply thoſe parts, as we much deſire to do.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, we think fit, that you reinforce the Foot-Company under your Command, ſo as they may conſiſt of a hundred men, and to Arm them the beſt way you can, untill by the coming of the ſupply of Arms, we expect, we may be inabled to ſend. Arms for them, which yet we cannot do with ſafety, if we had Arms here, untill by the ſtrength of His Majeſties Army, we ſhall cleer the paſſages thither, which by Gods help we doubt not in ſhort time to do: And ſo we bid you heartily farewell.</p>
            <p>From His Majeſties Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> 30. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>We ſend you here incloſed, a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for proſecution of the Rebels, with power of Martiall Law.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ormond Aſſery,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Parſons,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Borlaſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cha. Lambard,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adam Loftus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Temple.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:158501:49"/>
            <head>William Parſons, Joh. Borlaſſe.</head>
            <byline>By the Lords Juſtices and Councell.</byline>
            <p>TRuſty and Welbeloved, We greet you well, We having entred into a ſerious conſideration of the moſt Rebellious Inſurrections of divers falſe Traitors in the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and elſewhere in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of the moſt wicked inclination of many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall men, inhabiting upon the ſeverall Borders of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and elſewhere; who have already begun in the action of the moſt Rebellious conſpiracies now on foot, threatning a generall deſtruction to all His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good Subjects of this Kingdom. To cut off the ſaid deteſtable offenders, and to prevent the devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſpoil of His Majeſties good People, We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought fit, and ſo do Ordain, Require, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe you, to make diligent ſearch and inquiry throughout the Counties of <hi>Letrim</hi> and <hi>Sligoe,</hi> and the Borders adjoyning thereunto, for all Traitors and Traiterous perſons above mentioned, and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; And them to apprehend, and duely examine, concerning their Traiterous actions: And if you ſhall finde any perſon or perſons, that have committed or joyned, in any of the ſaid actions, to proceed with him or them, in the courſe of Martiall Law, by hanging him
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:158501:49"/>or them, till he or they be dead, as hath been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed in time of open Rebellion, as your conſcience and diſcretion ſhall guide you therein. And for the better execution of this Our Commiſſion, We do hereby Authorize you, to raiſe ſuch numbers of men of thoſe Counties, for your aſſiſtance, as you ſhall think fit; and to take Meat and Drink, not exceeding the value of ſix pence <hi>per diem</hi> each man, during the ſervice onely. And we ſtraightly Command the Sheriffs of the ſaid Counties, for the time being, and all other Officers, Miniſters and loving Subjects, to whom it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain, To be unto you in the due execution hereof, alwayes ayding, helping, and aſſiſting, whenſoever they ſhall be required by you, as they ſhall anſwer the contrary, at their uttermoſt perils; And that this Our Commiſſion ſhall continue, during Our pleaſure onely. As for your ſo doing as aforeſaid, This ſhall be your ſufficient Warrant. Given at His Majeſties Caſtle of <hi>Dublin, 30. Decemb. 1641.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>To Our Truſty and Welbeloved Sir <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick Hammilton,</hi> Knight.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ormond Aſſery.</item>
                     <item>Cha. Lambard.</item>
                     <item>Ada. Loftus.</item>
                     <item>Joh. Temple.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
